<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A calendar of prophetick time, drawn by an express Scripture-line, from the creation to the new Jerusalem demonstrating that the famous apocalyptick vision of the witnesses slain, truly explained, did determine at the Reformation begun by Luther, but that the time of their prophecy in sackcloth will not expire till the year 1697 : on which shall follow the fall of the tenth of the city Babylon in its ten horns, or kings separated intirely from it : and the Turkish woe passed, and the seventh trumpet sounding, there shall be a most loud and publick ministration of the Gospel, beyong any time, since the apostles, described as seven voices, or the seven thunders unsealed, Apoc. 14 : and at the year 1727 shall begin the final destruction of the beast by the vials, accomplished at the year 1772, in the New Jerusalem briefly described : with a postscript freeing this computation from objections rising from the sentiments of the most pious and learned expositor Dr. More, especially in his late Arithmetica Apocalyptica, and his answer to S.E.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 240 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 51 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A32163</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12116495</idno>
  <idno type="VID">54329</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240946129</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing C289</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R20247</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">12116495</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A32163)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 54329)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 760:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A calendar of prophetick time, drawn by an express Scripture-line, from the creation to the new Jerusalem demonstrating that the famous apocalyptick vision of the witnesses slain, truly explained, did determine at the Reformation begun by Luther, but that the time of their prophecy in sackcloth will not expire till the year 1697 : on which shall follow the fall of the tenth of the city Babylon in its ten horns, or kings separated intirely from it : and the Turkish woe passed, and the seventh trumpet sounding, there shall be a most loud and publick ministration of the Gospel, beyong any time, since the apostles, described as seven voices, or the seven thunders unsealed, Apoc. 14 : and at the year 1727 shall begin the final destruction of the beast by the vials, accomplished at the year 1772, in the New Jerusalem briefly described : with a postscript freeing this computation from objections rising from the sentiments of the most pious and learned expositor Dr. More, especially in his late Arithmetica Apocalyptica, and his answer to S.E.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 93 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for the author, and are to be sold by the booksellers,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1684.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Errata: p. 93.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">S. E., --  Mennonite.</term>
               <term type="personal_name">More, Henry, 1614-1687.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Time --  Religious aspects --  Christianity.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Apocalyptic literature.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-02 </date>
            <label>John Latta </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-02 </date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:54329:1"/>
            <p>A CALENDAR OF <hi>Prophetick Time,</hi> Drawn by an Express Scripture-Line; From the Creation to the <hi>NEW JERƲSALEM:</hi>
            </p>
            <p> DEMONSTRATING That the Famous Apocalyptick Vision of the Witnesses slain, truly explained, did determine at the Reformation begun by <hi>Luther.</hi> But that the Time of their Prophecy in Sackcloth will not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, till the year 1697.</p>
            <p>On which shall follow the Fall of the <hi>Tenth</hi> of the City <hi>Babylon,</hi> in its ten Horns, or Kings separated intirely from it. And the <hi>Turkish</hi> woe pass'd. And the seventh Trumpet sounding, there shall be a most loud and publick Ministration of the Gospel, beyond any Time, since the Apostles, described as seven Voi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, or the seven Thunders unsealed. <hi>Apoc.</hi> 14.</p>
            <p>And at the Year 1727 shall begin the final Destruction of the Beast by the Vials, accomplished at the year 1772, in the <hi>New Jerusalem</hi> briefly described. With a Postscript freeing this Computation from Objections rising from the Sentiments of the most pious and learned Expositor Dr. <hi>More,</hi> especially in his late <hi>Arithmetica Apocalyptica,</hi> and his Answer to <hi>S. E.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Dan. 12.6.7.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>How Long shall it be to the end of these Wonders? When he shall have ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>complished to scatter the Power of the Holy People, All these things shall be finished.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Apoc.</hi> 16.17.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>It is done.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Apoc.</hi> 21.6.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>It is done.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for the Author, and are to be sold by the Booksellers. 1684.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="calendar">
            <pb facs="tcp:54329:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:54329:2"/>
            <head>The Calendar.</head>
            <list>
               <item>FRom the Creation to <hi>Noah</hi>'s new Heaven and Earth after the Flood. 1656. Years.</item>
               <item>From thence to <hi>Abraham</hi>'s coming out of <hi>Chaldaean</hi> Idolatry into <hi>Canaan.</hi> 427. Years.</item>
               <item>From thence to <hi>Israels</hi> Redemption from the <hi>Egyptian</hi> Bondage, and the Tabernacle of Testimony. 430. Years.</item>
               <item>From thence to <hi>Solomon</hi>'s Temple, and during his Illustrious <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rusalem.</hi> 516. Years.</item>
               <item>From thence after the Revolt of the ten Tribes to <hi>Ezekiel</hi>'s Visio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Jerusalem and Temple fulfill'd, at which they shall be restored, 390. and <hi>Cyrus</hi> his Decree of Deliverance from <hi>Babylon,</hi> 40. 430. Years.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>From <hi>Cyrus.</hi>
               </head>
               <item>In a Vision, during from <hi>Babyl.</hi> Literal to <hi>Babyl.</hi> Mystical falling, call'd, the Vision of the Dayly, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> from its principal Notes of Time.</item>
               <item>A principal Line of 2300 Evenings and Mornings. <hi>viz.</hi> 2300 years.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>The <hi>Collateral</hi> Lines.</head>
               <item>From <hi>Cyrus</hi> to <hi>Artaxerxes</hi> his Munificent Decree, at his seventh Year, and the beginning of <hi>Daniel</hi>'s Weeks. 75. Years.</item>
               <item>From the beginning of the Weeks, to the middle of the last Week, at our Lord's Resurrection. 486. Years.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>
                     <hi>Ann. Dom.</hi> 235.</label> From thence to <hi>Alexander Severus</hi> the <hi>Roman</hi> Emperour, holding the Ballance of Time to the Beasts Rising. 202. Years.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>
                     <hi>A. D.</hi> 437.</label> From thence to the Beasts Rising with the 10 Kings, and the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire falling. 202. Years.</item>
               <item>From the Beasts Rising to the end of his 42 Months 1260 years; and with <hi>Daniel</hi>'s Addition 75. All which Time the two <hi>Maho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metan</hi> Woes. 1335. Years.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>A.D. 797.</label> From the Beasts Rising to the end of his first Time. 360. Years.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>
                     <hi>An.</hi> 1517.</label> From thence to the end of his two Times. 720. Years.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>
                     <hi>A.D.</hi> 1697.</label> From thence to the end of his Half Time and of the <hi>Mahometan</hi> Tyranny. 180. Years.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>1727.</label> From thence to <hi>Dan.</hi> Additional 30 Days or 1290. of the Voices. 30. Years.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>
                     <hi>A.D.</hi> 1772.</label> From thence to <hi>Dan.</hi> Additional 45 Days or 1335. of the Vials. 45. Years.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>
                     <hi>Ann. Mun.</hi> 5759.</label> From Term to Term. 2300. Years.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Within the Time from our Lord's Resurrection.</head>
               <item>
                  <label>
                     <hi>A.D.</hi> 725.</label> From the Mystery of Iniquity beginning to work in the Beasts Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception, to his great Character or Apocalyptick Number as an Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous Beast, in the History of his War for Image-Worship. 666. Years.</item>
               <item>From his Rising or Birth, to his appearing a Potent Beast in his Esta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blishing Transubstantiation, and Contesting the <hi>German</hi> Emperours in the end of the 10th, and beginning of the 11th Century. 666. Years.</item>
               <item>From thence to his Final Abolition, before the New <hi>Jerusalem,</hi> and being dealt with, as that Apocalyptick Beast. 666. Years.</item>
               <item>Both hearing some Proportion with his numeral Character in Time, and Nature, as a full Antitype of <hi>Antioch. Epiph.</hi> broken without hand; who, both as a Mark of <hi>Rome</hi>'s first Monarchickness, and Type of its Antichristianism, is so expresly remarked in <hi>Daniel.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:54329:3"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE TO THE DISCOURSE.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Affirm this to be a Scripture-Calendar: If it be so, it will be easily allowed, it should over-rule all other Registries of Time, and so the Distances of Chronologers will not affect it; and yet it is not so out of Compass with those that are esteemed most regular, but that it is as fairly reconcileable with any of them, as the Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sures they take, are one with another. That it is a Scripture-Calendar, I plead the Harmony of its Parts, in exact Agreement one with another, both for Number and Weight, and justified by a Course of Events, where it is most prophetical: tho two great Arguments for the Divinity of Creation, and of the Scripture. Before <hi>Cyrus,</hi> I have on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly drawn the Principal Line; and Difference of Years, till then, will not disturb me in my main Purpose; no not that formidable one of the <hi>Vossian 70:</hi> for the principal Drist till then, is to shew, Scripture hath taken care of, and fixed such a Line, and so re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark'd. Yet on many other Reasons I heartily espouse the <hi>Hebrew</hi> Copies, and so their Accounts, as the only safe <hi>Pandects</hi> of Original Verity. After <hi>Cyrus,</hi> the Principal is one entire Line, with which the Collaterals so exactly agree, as also among themselves, that one Joynt cannot be stretched, or contracted, without the Dissolution of the whole, or the loss of Scripture Authority for the Ground of the Calendar: and if that be lost, I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fess, All is nothing. As it is, I cannot expect Acceptance; for the Sacred Prophecy as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sures me,
<note place="margin">Apoc. 10.9.</note> but in such an Order and Time, the <hi>Book</hi> will not be pleasant within any one that eats, or endeavours to understand it. All that I desire is, It may be preserved to future Observation I hope it cannot be offensive; for I have unconcerned my self in any Christian Differences, only, against <hi>Antichristianism.</hi> Against Sedition, or Turbulency towards Government, I have fully declared my self in the Discourse; and do now enter this Solemn Protestation, That if the Events expectable according to this Calendar shall not be conducted by the most unquestionable, lawful Authority of every Nation, I own all I have writ groundless and mistaken; although I as yet believe it, as much as I do any thing, except Fundamentals of Scripture, of which I own Obedience to Magistrates a principal. Fanatical I am sure it cannot be; for I pretend to nothing, but what is manifest by Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, Reason, and History: nor can this Calendar be a Creature of Fancy, for such may be multiplied; but let any one try to draw such another so ratified: non will written Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, and in a certain Order, submit to Arbitrary Phantasie. I know many Applications of Prophetick Writing may seem so, but that being so framed, as both to discover and conceal, they must needs seem so to those that do not intently think: for the Lines that discover are drawn so exceeding small, that it will seem a Fancy, but to pretend to see them, when others do not, However, what is most Calendary I most justifie: The Ʋnderstanding of the Scope, and Contexture of this Discourse, depends on a diligent Compare with <hi>Daniel,</hi> and the <hi>Revelation,</hi> References to which, by Chap. and Vers. I have generally avoided, for it would have swell'd the Bulk too much, (which how little soever, will, I doubt, look too much:) and whoever does not care to read those Prophecies, so as to know them in general, will little value a Calendar drawn according to them: And they that do know them, but in general, will be easily led by general Mentions.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:54329:3"/>
            <head>A FURTHER ADVERTISEMENT TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>SInce the Imprinting this Calendar, almost two years ago, the Author hath, continual meditation and search, gone over it, and every Joynt of it again, with much ampler and larger Illustrations, with fuller, more convictive, and demonstrative Arguments.</p>
            <p>And although he hath not found reason to change any of his grand Principles, or Joynts of Calculation, yet he hath made severest castigations upon whatever was over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seen in Things of smaller Concernment.</p>
            <p>Among which, none seems worthier of particular Remark, in the Judgment of the Author, than his confounding (though with all the Interpreters he hath seen) the Gentiles, and the Beasts forty two Months, especially in their beginning, <hi>Epoch,</hi> and entrance.</p>
            <p>In his second Thoughts, he hath, even to Demonstration prov'd, That the fourty two Mouths of the Beast begin exactly at the cessation of the <hi>Roman Western</hi> Empire, in <hi>Momyllus,</hi> or <hi>Augustulus,</hi> in the year of Vulgar Account 475. And that they are Lunar Time to be guided by, and to follow the Solar Time of 1260 Days, in the same pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion, as Lunar and Solar Years answer one another.</p>
            <p>And thus they most certainly must end eleven years hence, or 1697. And then fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, They determine the <hi>Epoch</hi> of those 1260 Days to begin about 38 years before themselves, that so they may, as they must needs by the Prophesie end together. And this the Author confides he hath clear'd and made good against any possible Objection.</p>
            <p>By which Account we certainly know, when in Divine Estimation of things, the Witnesses enter'd into their Sack-cloth, and the Woman into the Wilderness; and consequently when the Apostasie began, and when it is to end, <hi>viz.</hi> At that Great Year, 1697. And then the Witnesses to come out of their Sack-cloth, and the Woman out of the wilderness. And as <hi>Daniel's</hi> 1290 days inclusively adding thirty to the 1260, begin at the taking away the daily; So the Gentiles Treading begins their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty two Months. And the Witnesses 1260 days in the <hi>Apocal.</hi> begin at the same time, and with them the Womans 1260 days in the wilderness, answering word for word with the taking away the daily by <hi>Antiochus</hi> his Gentiles; as by a compare of the <hi>Maccabean</hi> History, and the words there us'd, in the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or the sackcloth, and the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or wilderness, even to admiration. Here then the Apostacy began, and gave occasion to the Witnesses mourning, and the Woman's Wilderness-state, the 42 months of the Gentiles, and the 1260 days synchronizing in their Epoch, and then the Gentiles for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty two months coalesced with the Beasts 42 months at their beginning, and are merg'd in them at his 666, as is manifestly proved.</p>
            <p>There is also in the Review and Enlargement of this Calendar, an exact exposition of the <hi>Iconismo,</hi> or figures of the Beast, <hi>Apoc.</hi> 13. and 18. freeing it from all those per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexities and confusion, darkness of interpretation hath cast upon a Prophecy so mysti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal; which the Author hopes he hath clear'd to most evident correspondence between it and the Event, as much as the exactest picture ever yet answer'd the Life, and was verified by it.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:54329:4"/>
            <p> But this Calendar is not exact in their Delineation, though just in the main; And indeed in the whole is little more than an Index leading to Times and their Events, without Arguments adjoyn'd, equal to their support in such configurations of the one with the other. But the Law then allowing the liberty of the Press, which is now re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strain'd, That is now offer'd to view, which in regard of greater preparations, was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to have been suppress'd; with hopes I may procure a liberty to those prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions just now ready for the Press, and waiting for its Midwifry only.</p>
            <p>For the Author professes, he hath founded them so upon the Letter of Scripture-Types, and Numbers, compar'd one with another; justified them by rational Dedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions from those Types and Numbers; concerted them with indisputable History; so that he humbly, and with modesty, yet with great assurance, is ready to offer them (with leave) to Divines, Historians, Chronologers, of what persuasion soever, to be ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther accepted or refuted (if they can be) by the same Scripture, Reason, or History, without any Reflections, but upon the Merits of the Arguments themselves; and with obtaining for the Author the Liberty of like Rejoynder, and Vindication.</p>
            <p>And he further declares, the whole undertaking is so far from any seditious Inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, either in Church or State, that one Designation of the whole Frame, was laid to fore-close any such irregular motions, from making the least pretence from Scripture-Prophesie.</p>
            <p>May this Calendar then be accepted only as an Elenchus or Table of what is more fully explicated, and argumentarily treated in that larger Work, that prayes earnest<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by this to be made publick with consent of Authority, that it may be justified, or (if it can be according to Scripture) condemn'd.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:54329:4"/>
            <head>A CALENDAR OF <hi>Prophetick Time.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>GOD, the Lord of the World, and especially of his Church, who hath <hi>reserved Times</hi> and <hi>Seasons in his own Power,</hi> and <hi>changeth them as he pleases;</hi> hath in preserving the Accounts of Time, and his own Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment upon it, excell'd the wisest Princes, and States.</p>
            <p n="1">1. In Certainty, and Infallibility.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In Lastingness, and Perpetuity.</p>
            <p n="3">3. In Universality, and Extensiveness, so that what hath not yet come into Act, and History, he hath, as he pleased, fore-dated by Prophecy.</p>
            <p>Whatever <hi>Calendar</hi> of Time therefore can be truly derived from his Word, controuls all other appearances whatever.</p>
            <p>There is a Line of Time drawn out by Sacred Writ from the Creation of the World, to the glorious Kingdom of the <hi>Mes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siah;</hi> called the <hi>New Jerusalem;</hi> or from the <hi>first Heaven</hi> and <hi>Earth</hi> to <hi>all things made New,</hi> or from the <hi>seventh day Sabbath</hi> of Creation, to the first, or <hi>Lords day Sabbath</hi> of the Resurrection, and from that to the <hi>Sabbatism</hi> of the <hi>New Jerusalem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From <hi>Paradise in Eden,</hi> to the <hi>Paradise</hi> of God.</p>
            <p>From the <hi>first Adam, in whom all dye,</hi> to the <hi>second Adam,</hi> the <hi>Seed of the Woman, the first begotten from the Dead, and his ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lasting Dominion.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:54329:5"/>
            <p> From the <hi>first Death,</hi> to the <hi>first Resurrection.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From <hi>Satan,</hi> that <hi>old Serpent</hi> appearing <hi>loose</hi> in deceiving the World by the first Parents, to <hi>Satan bound,</hi> that <hi>he may deceive the Nations no more for a thousand Years.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Of this Line of Time, God hath pleas'd to be so careful, that it is exactly drawn in Words at length, in History, or precedently to any dark Times, to come upon his Church, he hath supplyed the <hi>Calendar,</hi> by <hi>Prophesie,</hi> but from <hi>Ezekiels first Vision, to the thousand years,</hi> onely using the prophetical Figure of <hi>Days</hi> for <hi>Years,</hi> of which he first gave a Key, before he used it, that we might know how to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstand prophetical <hi>Dayes</hi> ever after.</p>
            <p>In the Sacred Book there is one main, or principal Line of Time, which is corroborated with one, or more collateral Lines, that thereby there may be a more critical distinction, and also a more certain assurance of Time, and Times.</p>
            <p>There are three things observable throughout the whole Line.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That the parts of it are always fixed upon the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the Year, or very near it, as most certainly the very Season of the Worlds Creation, but especially for the sake of the Redemption, or Resurrection of <hi>our Lord</hi> at that Time; as also to prevent confusion in Computes.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That it is very often remarqued with <hi>sabbatical</hi> Indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations, and Respects, in Honour of the Rest of Creation, of Redemption, and of the <hi>New Jerusalem,</hi> which, when it is, will be understood to be the true <hi>sabbatism</hi> of the World, both in exact calculation of Time, as also of holy Rest.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Jubilees,</hi> though not noted in Scripture, (and so I un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake them not) will undoubtedly concert, when the whole Table of Time is opened, and that to admiration.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That its principal Epochs are adorned, and made il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lustrious with the Deliverances of the Church of God, and Ruine of its Enemies, or with some peculiar Favors to the one, and Judgments on the other: and so are they the most noted Periods and Determinations of each part also. But if
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:54329:5"/>not so, the Epochs or Beginnings are cardinalis'd by some notorious Defection from God; Affliction, or Judgement upon Gods Church, and the endings are Reformation, Res<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cue, and Deliverance most certainly.</p>
            <p>The first part of the principal Line runs through the <hi>Patriarchs Ages,</hi> before the Birth of the succeeding <hi>Patriarch,</hi> and ends in the Death of <hi>Terah,</hi> and not five years sooner: as I humbly conceive, notwithstanding the Judgment of some great <hi>Chronologers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Because the Command was to <hi>Abraham,</hi> to leave his <hi>Fathers House,</hi> and to come into a <hi>Land God</hi> would <hi>shew</hi> him; which was not done till he came <hi>into Canaan,</hi> and his Father dead, tho he had moved towards it, <hi>Terah</hi> being yet alive, and accompanying him.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The four hundred and thirty years of the subsequent Line, is dated by the Apostle from the <hi>Promise,</hi> which is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded to be after his Fathers Death, just at his departure from <hi>Haran,</hi> when he was seventy five years of Age.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The <hi>four hundred years Affliction in Egypt</hi> may be with every good Remarque dated from the <hi>Son of the Egyptian Woman</hi> his <hi>mocking,</hi> which the <hi>Apostle</hi> calls <hi>Persecution</hi> of <hi>Isaac</hi> the <hi>Seed,</hi> and so was not only symbolick, and prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick, but a very beginning of the great Affliction in <hi>Egypt,</hi> at the fifth year of <hi>Isaac,</hi> and not at his Birth; which five years of <hi>Isaac</hi> joyned to <hi>Abrahams</hi> twenty five, after the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mise, make the 400 and 30, and subducting the 30, the 400.</p>
            <p n="4">4. In expounding the principal Line, we are always to choose the most easie, and intelligible Sense, seeing one great use of that is to reconcile all doubts in the collata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Lines: Now the plainest and most obvious account of Time is to draw evenly to <hi>Terahs</hi> Death that principal Line: seeing Scripture expresses not his Age, at his leaving <hi>Ʋr</hi> of the <hi>Chaldees,</hi> nor how long he tarried in <hi>Haran</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he died: those five years are then but conjecturally placed, and the Account of Time thereupon, but precarious, but most certain to his Death, and from thence the 430
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:54329:6"/>years of the succeeding principal Line certain also, and all collateral times are to be concerted by them both.</p>
            <p>But yet this is not all we have, not only to assure us, but to direct us to be most exact, and critical in this Time.</p>
            <p>For <hi>Moses</hi> tells us, <hi>the Sojourning of the Children of Isra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el who dwelt in Egypt was four hundred and thirty years; And it it came to pass in the end of the four hundred and thirty years,
<note place="margin">Exod. 12.40, 41.</note> the self same day it came to pass, that all the Hosts of the Lord went out from the Land of Egypt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The same <hi>Moses</hi> had told us before, that when <hi>Abraham</hi> was come by Gods command into <hi>Canaan.</hi> It was was so or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered by Providence, that there was <hi>a Famine in the Land,</hi> and <hi>Abraham went down into Egypt to sojourn there.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 12.10.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Now the Apostle hath taught us how to interpret the Children of <hi>Israels sojourning by Abrahams sojourning;</hi> when he assumes, to say <hi>Levi by being in Abrahams Loyns paid Tyths.</hi> As <hi>Levi</hi> then <hi>paid Tyths, so the Children of Isra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el sojourn'd in Abrahams Loyns.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 7.9.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The first day therefore of <hi>Abrahams sojourning</hi> in Egypt must be the <hi>tenth day of the first Month,</hi> answering to the <hi>very self same day</hi> of the <hi>Israelites going out of Egypt,</hi> four hundred and thirty years before.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Terah</hi> then dying, the preceding year gave time for <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hams</hi> going out of <hi>Haran to Canaan;</hi> for Gods appearing to him in that great <hi>promise,</hi> on the tenth day of the first Month, the year following, for his moving up and down in <hi>Canaan</hi> for the best Forrage; but sinding a general Famine, he went down to <hi>Egypt,</hi> the same year, to begin <hi>Israels</hi> dwelling in <hi>Egypt</hi> at the very first of the 440 years.</p>
            <p>So the <hi>Law was four hundred and thirty years after the promise,</hi> being just at the <hi>sojourning:</hi> and the Children of <hi>Israels going out of Egypt</hi> at four hundred and thirty years end, answers to the very self same day of the <hi>sojour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in Abraham;</hi> and from Term to Term there was four hundred and thirty years <hi>sojourning,</hi> though it was not the whole time throughout, that they sojourned in <hi>Egypt.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:54329:6"/>
            <p> So we have from the Creation to the Flood dryed up in the beginning of the year, the first day of the first Month;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Anoble Type as appears</hi> Esa. 54.9. 1 Pet. 3.20. Apoc. 10.1. Gen. 8.13.</note> from that to <hi>Abrahams sojourning,</hi> necessarily at the same beginning also (else it could not answer) to the Children of <hi>Israels going out of Egypt the self same day</hi> of the yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning year, two thousand five hundred and thirteen years.</p>
            <p>The third part of the principal Line is, from the <hi>going out of Egypt, to Solomons beginning the Temple,</hi> which sacred Record emphatically assures us was in the four hundred and eightieth year after,
<note place="margin">1 King. 6.1.</note> and as near the beginning of the year, as the <hi>second day</hi> of the <hi>second Month;</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Chron. 3.2.</note> Thirty six years after this <hi>Solomon</hi> reigned, as is plainly expressed.</p>
            <p>Thus far our principal Line proceeds without any con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siderable remaining scruple. That doubt of the forty five years space of the <hi>Judges</hi> must certainly be reconcil'd by the principal Line, that being only a collateral,
<note place="margin">Acts 13.20.21.</note> and the seem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing variation either imputed to the Error of Transcribers, or that the Apostle enhansing the Dignity of <hi>David</hi>'s King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, the Type of <hi>our Lords</hi> Royalty, set out the Mise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of former times by accounting the years of the Oppres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sors, as if they lengthned out that tedious space of the <hi>Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es,</hi> under the Kings, <hi>(as it were)</hi> even as their Story is of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten darkned with this, <hi>There was no King in Israel, &amp;c.</hi> on account of which <hi>Sauls</hi> reign is also mentioned, and computed to that length under <hi>Samuel</hi>'s prefecture that sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported it, while he lived.</p>
            <p>In the succeeding parts of the Line, I acknowledge, I have presumed to beat out a Path untroden, so far as I know, by any, but I hope not without safe conduct of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. I therefore undertake to joyn to the four hundred and eighty, and <hi>Solomons</hi> remaining thirty six till the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volt of the ten <hi>Tribes from Davids House,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezek. 4.4.</note> the three hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and ninety dayes, <hi>Ezeckiel lay visionally or emblema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tically upon his left Side, bearing the Iniquity of the House of Israel, a Day for a Year,</hi> and ending on the very <hi>self same tenth day of the first Month,</hi> in the <hi>Vision</hi> of the <hi>New Jerusalem:</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:54329:7"/>As then after the four hundred and thirty years of sojourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ended, ensued speedily the raising of the moveable <hi>Temple</hi> or <hi>Tabernacle,</hi> and after the four hundred and eigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty years the building the magnificent <hi>Temple of Solomon,</hi> that had Foundations, but such as might be raz'd; so after the three hundred and ninety dayes, or the <hi>very self same day of the tenth Month</hi> (as it is most observably dated) the Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion of the <hi>New Jerusalem</hi> and its spiritual Temple,
<note place="margin">Ezck. 40.1.</note> that <hi>Foundations that cannot be moved,</hi> whose <hi>Builder and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker God is,</hi> was exhibited to <hi>Ezekiel</hi> in the thirty third year of <hi>Nebucadnezzer,</hi> fourteen <hi>years after the City smitten,</hi> which was in his nineteenth year:
<note place="margin">Jerem. 52.12.</note> of which <hi>Cyrus</hi> his <hi>Temple</hi> might be a thin shadowy Type.</p>
            <p>And to these are to be added the forty dayes <hi>Ezekiel</hi> lay <hi>on his right side, bearing the Iniquity of Judah,</hi> making up four hundred and thirty years, and they reach to the end of the Captivity,
<note place="margin">Ezck. 4.4. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> or <hi>Cyrus</hi> his first year: so that Time looks back historically upon the Kings of <hi>Israel</hi> and <hi>Judah,</hi> and that part of the <hi>Captivity</hi> before the <hi>Vision,</hi> and forward to the end of the <hi>Captivity</hi> after the <hi>Vision.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now in thus dissenting from the whole stream of Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preters, I here present several (as I understand them) for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cible Reasons.</p>
            <p n="1">1. It is expresly said, when the three hundred and ninety dayes were accomplished on the <hi>left side,</hi> the Prophet should yet lye on his <hi>Right side forty dayes,</hi> without the least Inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, that the one part, the forty dayes, should be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded within the other part, the three hundred and nine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty dayes: so that by all that is said by the holy Writer, the time is to be drawn out four hundred and thirty dayes at the full length.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The <hi>severe</hi> and <hi>unpleasant Diet</hi> is indeed said to be provided for the three hundred and ninety days in the <hi>strait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness of the Siege,</hi> but it is withall said, <hi>They</hi> of the <hi>Captivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> should eat <hi>their polluted Bread among the Gentiles,</hi> mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the whole time of the <hi>Captivity,</hi> which is on all hands
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:54329:7"/>agreed to exceed many dayes or years, the three hundred and ninety.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Let us allow a Contraction of fourteen years in the Reigns of some of the <hi>Kings of Judah,</hi> for they being as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sum'd into a Partnership of Government with their Fathers, some of the Sons Years of Reign fell under the Fathers, and so many are to be detach'd, as did so run under; This seems necessary by a commensuration of their Times with the <hi>Kings of Israel,</hi> and most <hi>Chronologers</hi> allow fourteen years and more; There will be then a great agreeableness of four hundred and thirty years, from <hi>Solomons</hi> Death and the Revolt after it to the end of the <hi>Captivity,</hi> as also with the years given by Scripture to <hi>Nebuchadnezzer</hi> in the mean space.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The Line of Scripture Time, of which it hath been so careful as to date the exact Time of the <hi>Patriarchs,</hi> and to express the very year after the Flood, <hi>Shem</hi> begat in. Also the tenth day of the first month, the self same day ending the four hundred and thirty years of <hi>Israels sojourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> which must needs constitute the Spring, the Beginning of years from the Creation to the sojourning (and so on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards to the end of Time) else it could not be the <hi>self same;</hi> all this, I say, argues such an Exactness, as the perplexed Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of this Time of the Kings of <hi>Judah,</hi> their Reign, as also of the Beginning of the Captivity could not comport with, without this so express and ascertaining Line, which answers the very beginning of the Year, in both the three hundred and ninety, and the forty dayes, as shall immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately appear, and so must sit most exactly: and then fills out the whole space from <hi>Solomon</hi> to <hi>Cyrus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. It serves no other purpose with a like Exactness; It is indeed probably a literal Measure of <hi>the dayes of the Siege,</hi> if we knew the History of its interruption and vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorous pursuit; but that it was not intended for that chiefly, is arguable, in that it takes no notice of such an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terruption in them, which not allowed, the Time the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:54329:8"/>allows to the <hi>Siege,</hi> exceeds the 390 dayes, with the 40 dayes added.</p>
            <p>Further, It concenters not with the Time of Gods pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience to the <hi>Israelites</hi> or ten <hi>Tribes;</hi> for they were carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed captive above an hundred <hi>Years</hi> before; and if they are considered in the union of some of them with <hi>Judah,</hi> yet the same Patience of God had so far deserted the House of <hi>Judah,</hi> as that they had in great part, been in Captivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty some years before the 390 <hi>dayes</hi> expired, and <hi>Jerusalem</hi> twice taken: besides, the very Bulk of the Vision suppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses <hi>Israel</hi> one <hi>House</hi> or Kingdom, and <hi>Judah</hi> another, and so not to be confusedly joyn'd in these <hi>years.</hi> What then shall we sind to match this Vision with a fuller Correspon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence. This (if I much mistake not) will do it:</p>
            <p>Each Term of the 390 and the 40 ends in a signal <hi>Vision</hi> proper to each.</p>
            <p n="1">1. At the end of the 390 <hi>Dayes,</hi> exactly in the <hi>beginning of the Year, the very self-same day,</hi> the very <hi>tenth day</hi> of the <hi>Month,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezek. 40.1.</note> answering that <hi>self-same tenth day</hi> of the <hi>Israelites going</hi> out of <hi>Egypt, Ezekiel</hi> had the Vision of the <hi>New Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rusalem</hi> (as I have already said) in Prophetick Schemes, after the so long and foul Idolatry of the <hi>ten Tribes,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any the least Lucid Interval, a certain Type of the same dark and much longer dated Idolatry, and Defection of the <hi>Christian Church,</hi> removed by the Appearance of the <hi>New Jerusalem;</hi> not in Prophecy, but Event, or its Grand Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect: as now it was after <hi>Ezekiels</hi> Typical <hi>bearing that Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity,</hi> by this <hi>visionall Jerusalem.</hi> And as <hi>Ezekiel</hi>'s Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy is Dated from <hi>Josiah</hi>'s Reformation or <hi>Famous Pass<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over,</hi> viz. in the thirtieth year after it, so about 49 years after it, as in a day of <hi>Jubilee,</hi> it ends in the Vision of the Holy City.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The forty <hi>Daies</hi> end in that most blessed <hi>Vision</hi> and <hi>Evangile</hi> vouchsaf'd to <hi>Daniel,</hi> as a man <hi>greatly beloved,</hi> and brought to him by the Angel <hi>Gabriel,</hi> which disco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered the true Expiation of the whole 390 and 40 <hi>Years
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:54329:8"/>Iniquitie,</hi> which <hi>Ezekiel</hi> bore in <hi>Vision,</hi> but the <hi>Messiah</hi> in greatest reality bore, and quite <hi>took away</hi> by the sacrifice of himself; and as it were on purpose to connect with the Vision of <hi>Ezekiel's Bearing,</hi> such a plenitude of Expression is us'd to set out its efficacy: <hi>To finish Transgressions, to make an end of Sin,</hi> and <hi>to make reconciliation for iniquitie,</hi> and to <hi>bring in everlasting Righteousness;</hi> Upon which immediately followed, (at the beginning of the year also) the Redemption of <hi>Cyrus,</hi> called in that respect <hi>Messiah,</hi> though a Pagan, as a great Type of him, the True and Great Redeemer.</p>
            <p>And as the 40 <hi>daies</hi> are taken out of the worst, and most idolatrous Years of <hi>Manasseh</hi>'s Reign, whose <hi>Iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty God would not pardon</hi> in general, but decreed for it to <hi>stretch over Jerusalem the Line of Samaria,</hi> and <hi>the Plum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met of the House of Ahab, and to wipe it as a man wipeth a Dish, turning it upside down,</hi> which was accomplished in the Siege, and what followed it; so the same <hi>Manasseh</hi> was in his own Repentance, and particular Pardon, and <hi>Release from his Captivity in</hi> Babylon, <hi>set forth as a Pattern of all long Suffering</hi> and Mercy to all them that should af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward believe in that Redemption of Christ, visionally presented to <hi>Daniel,</hi> at the end of the 40 dayes, and so be immediately set free from their Captivity by <hi>Cyrus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And in prospect of this Vision of Christs Redemption, <hi>Ezekiel</hi> at the end of the 390 dayes had the Vision of the <hi>New Jerusalem,</hi> and immediately after the <hi>City smitten,</hi> when the Intention or Signification of his lying on his Sides and bearing Iniquity was accomplished, he had the opening of his Mouth for the most part in Gospel Promises.</p>
            <p>The sum then is, from the Idolatry of the ten Tribes, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately after <hi>Solomons</hi> Death, to the <hi>Vision</hi> of the <hi>New Jerusalem</hi> at <hi>Nebuchadnezzers</hi> 33d year, near the midst of of the Captivity, are 390 years, and from thence to the Vision of <hi>Messiah</hi> given to <hi>Daniel,</hi> the first of <hi>Darius,</hi> are 40 years, where the Captivity ended. Which 430 years in
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:54329:9"/>sum <hi>Ezekiel</hi> represented, in a Day for a Year, by lying on each side, and bearing the Iniquity of <hi>Israel</hi> and <hi>Judah,</hi> till taken away by <hi>Messiah,</hi> as in the end of the Captivity.</p>
            <p>And to conclude this matter; This Vision of <hi>Ezekiel</hi> establishes to us the Use of the great Key of Prophetick Time, intimated before, a day for a year, and by Propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>Weeks,</hi> and <hi>Months</hi> of <hi>Days</hi> for <hi>Weeks,</hi> and <hi>Months</hi> of <hi>Years;</hi> and agreeably it teaches us to expound <hi>Time, Times</hi> and <hi>half a Time, and three days and a half,</hi> without which we can never unlock the secrets of Prophetick Time, since God is pleas'd to use this Cyphar of abbreviated Time, ever after he had settled the Interpretation of it, till he comes to the 1000 years of the <hi>New Jerusalem,</hi> when no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing shall any longer remain under Shades, Parables or Seals.</p>
            <p>The next generally acknowledg'd Line of Time, though it be not indeed the next, is the 70 <hi>Weeks.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But between the 70 <hi>years</hi> ending, and the 70 <hi>weeks</hi> beginning, both according to Scripture, and Foreign Chronology, an intermedious space of Time is to be found.</p>
            <p>That this may not be a void space, we are taught by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spired writing how to fill it up.</p>
            <p>First, by a Principal Line, then by Collateral Lines, disentangling those infinite Perplexities of Foreign Chro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nology, concerning the <hi>Persian</hi> Times.</p>
            <p>Upon the <hi>third year</hi> of <hi>Belschazzar,</hi> his undoubted last, was the Evening of the 70th year of Captivity, whose Even<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Morning may be reckoned as one Prophetical Day.
<note place="margin">Dan. 6.8.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The Morning, or Day to which Evening was <hi>Darius</hi> the <hi>Mede</hi> his first and only year; in which <hi>Messiah,</hi> the <hi>man in Linnen,</hi> strengthned <hi>Michael</hi> (the <hi>Jews Benign</hi> Angel) for a gracious Answer to <hi>Daniels</hi> Prayer, Tim'd on pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose to that year of <hi>Darius.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>On the fore-named prophetick Evening, the third of <hi>Belschazzer,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dan. 8.</note> did <hi>Daniel</hi> receive the Vision of 2300 prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical Evenings and Mornings (notnatural <hi>Nycthemers,</hi> as hath been generally interpreted, but) so called in resemblance
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:54329:9"/>of <hi>Moses</hi> his six dayes, and the seventh day Sabbath follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; because the first day of them was to open into the Redemption of the <hi>Jews,</hi> as a first day Sabbath by <hi>Cyrus</hi> his Decree; who as a grear Type of Christ herein is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led (as before noted) <hi>Messiah:</hi> and on the end of the 562d day or near it, into the Redemption of Mankind, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clar'd by Resurrection of Christ in the first day, or Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian Sabbath, a new Epoch of a collateral Line of the same Time; and a great Pledge of the Sabbatism of the <hi>New Jerusalem,</hi> and the first Resurrection upon that; And the last of them into the very Sabbatism of the <hi>New Jerusalem,</hi> of which the first, a Lords day Sabbath, and a new Epoch of the 1000 years, a Time beyond this; wherein is to be observed, in agreement with Scripture principal Epochs of Time; that both <hi>Cyrus,</hi> the Typical <hi>Messiah,</hi> and <hi>our Lord the True,</hi> appeared at the years beginning.</p>
            <p>Thus as the Destruction of literal <hi>Babylon,</hi> on the last Day Sabbath, and the Redemption of <hi>Israel,</hi> as a first day Sabbath, begin the Epoch of this Vision; so the destruction of mystical <hi>Babylon</hi> will be found to end this Vision, as the last day Sabbath, and the <hi>New Jerusalem</hi> begins, as a first day Sabbath, and a new Epoch of the 1000 <hi>years,</hi> as was said, which seems a very fair account, why the Holy-Spirit was pleased in this Vision to make use of <hi>evenings, mornings,</hi> and not of <hi>dayes,</hi> though alike prophetical.</p>
            <p>This Vision immediately respects <hi>Antiochus Epiphanes, and his taking away the daily Sacrifice, or service and set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up the Abomination, that maketh Desolate;</hi> and after that he is destroyed, and the <hi>Sanctuary cleansed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He is the Type, and every thing had a literal Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleion in him, so far as was necessary to a Type: Yet he was but a Type (as many great Reasons perswade) but by more general consent, a most lively Type of the <hi>man of Sin,</hi> or <hi>Antichrist.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Reasons that perswade he is but a Type;</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:54329:10"/> 1. The Vision, and not so much the things contained in it, is dated: <hi>The Vision of the sacrifice taken away shall be unto</hi> 2300 <hi>Evenings, Mornings,</hi> (<hi>not the taking away of the Sacrifice, and the giving the Host,</hi> &amp;c.) but the Vision shall extend to 2300, but the Vision, if <hi>Antiochus</hi> only be intended, begins sooner, for it begins in <hi>Belschazzars</hi> 3d: and so must extend to more dayes then 2300. But accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Sense I intend, <hi>viz.</hi> that it should be the time of 2300 prophetick Evenings and Mornings, the Vision shall begin and end with them; for which the manner of speaking being singular (<hi>The Vision shall be,</hi> &amp;c.) seems on purpose chosen.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Without this Line of Times from the 70 years, the Scripture Chronology would fail, which by the great care of the Holy Spirit, so far as to the end of the 70 years, before observed, and thence to the <hi>Messiah,</hi> by the 70 Weeks, and after that by a Line of 1260 Dayes often gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and with additional numbers, first of 30, making 1290: and then of 45, making up 1335 dayes to the end, when <hi>Daniel should stand in his Lot.</hi> It is not reasonably to be supposed, he hath not provided for the interval be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the 70 Years and the 70 Weeks, as also another in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terval betwixt the <hi>Messiahs Resurrection</hi> and the 1260 dayes (as is after to be observed) which can be only by these 2300 Evenings Mornings, as a principal Line.</p>
            <p n="3">3. We shall find this Line of 2300 years, agreeing in so admirable an exactness with the whole space of Time, betwixt the 70 years and the <hi>New Jerusalem,</hi> according to other prophetical Measures, and the suffrage of best Histo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, that it is a great Argument, it was so intended.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Whoever compares <hi>Daniels</hi> Vision of the <hi>little Horn</hi> on the fourth <hi>Beast:</hi> the Vision of <hi>the King, that does accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his Will,</hi> to whom <hi>Antiochus</hi> just tends, as the Type to the Antitype; and the defining of the Times for <hi>the end of these Wonders,</hi> and all things <hi>being sinished,</hi> shall find so many Correspondences in the Phrase, and manner of speak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:54329:10"/>as cannot but assure, they all are directed to the same point.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Particularly the so often mention of the <hi>End,</hi> and at that <hi>end</hi> the <hi>Vision shall be;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dan. 8.17.</note> just as it was at the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the 2300 the Vision was then, and at the end the very same Vision shall be found too: and the Times after mentioned, <hi>Dan</hi> 12, at the same <hi>End,</hi> do all strongly infer the Vision determines to the <hi>same End.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And I know no reason of remarquing the end of <hi>Antio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chus</hi> his Reign, as such a <hi>Chronical End,</hi> for it was the <hi>End</hi> of nothing but it self; the <hi>Jews</hi> Troubles still continued, and renewed afresh after him: The <hi>Messiah</hi> was a far off still: what end therefore could it be, if the Vision did not glide over him to a further and more monumental <hi>End.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Add hereunto <hi>Daniel's deep Sleep</hi> at the Vision, which seems to be symbolical of so long a Time, and is therefore renewed at the Vision of the same importance and date.</p>
            <p>This Line then thus interpreted, reaches to the 577th year of the World; which will be the vulgar year of our Lord 1772. And therefore it reaches to the <hi>New Jerusalem coming down from Heaven,</hi> seeing this Line of Time is the longest we can find in Sacred <hi>Chronology,</hi> and the <hi>New Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rusalem</hi> is the furthest off Object of Prophecy, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore these two must unite one to another, and joyn as close as the just preceeding point of Time does does to the next succeeding.</p>
            <p>When, I say, the furthest off Object of Prophecy, I ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept the <hi>Day of Judgment,</hi> which yet is rather Doctrine, and an Article of Faith, than Prophecy, and to that there is no Line of time drawn; for <hi>of that Day and that Hour knoweth no man:</hi> No not the <hi>Angels</hi> in <hi>Heaven,</hi> nor the <hi>Son,</hi> as Man, before his Resurrection, but <hi>the Father only.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This <hi>Calendar,</hi> calculated for the longest space of Time, comprehends within it self several other <hi>Calendars,</hi> greater and lesser within themselves, as greater and lesser Circles within this Undulation of Time, and all within this prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:54329:11"/>one, and it is the gage of them, both as to their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mensurations with it self, and within one another, that they neither swell beyond, or do not fill out their just spaces.</p>
            <p>As this great Circle of Time carries all the other along with it, so on the other side they distinguish that to the several points of Time, and the Events fix'd upon them; by which this measure of Time is adjusted to those Points, and is as it were guided, and inform'd to make Rests upon those nobler Events with which that Time is charg'd.</p>
            <p>The longest collateral Line of Time, most express and most noble, in which Interpreters most agree, is nearest to the Epoch of these 2300 <hi>Evenings, mornings,</hi> and is the <hi>seventy Weeks</hi> of years, or 490, to the Resurrection of the <hi>Messiah,</hi> or half one of these Weeks beyond it from the beginning of these <hi>Weeks.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The next longest collateral Line is the <hi>Beloved man Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niel's</hi> 1335 <hi>dayes,</hi> first proposed in a <hi>Time, times,</hi> and <hi>half a time,</hi> and that as two several Times, and is after expoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by the <hi>beloved Disciple</hi> and Apostle <hi>John,</hi> to be 1260 <hi>Daies,</hi> and compendiously <hi>three dayes</hi> and a <hi>half,</hi> and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied to the <hi>Beasts</hi> forty two <hi>months.</hi> And in the same Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy of <hi>Daniel,</hi> it is taken and joyn'd first with 30 Dayes, and then with 45 more, making up 1335, to the last <hi>End</hi> of all.</p>
            <p>Seeing then 490, and 1335 measur'd upon the Line of 2300, leave room still for 475, and that they cannot be seituated before the 2300, which begin the Epoch, or af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the 1335, which together with the 2300, <hi>end all;</hi> their place must either be before the 490, or continuously next to them, or some in the one place some in the other, as need requires: But that they must be some, and they a lesser number before, we have great Accounts of Scripture-Reason.</p>
            <p>And that they must be some, and a much greater part after, we have also as good and as great Scripture-Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:54329:11"/>joyn'd in both of them with solidest <hi>Chrono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So then these 70 Weeks, or 490 Years, in which most (at least) Christian <hi>Chronologers</hi> agree, stand as a most con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spicuous Boundary or Index betwixt the end of the 70 years, and the beginning of the 1335 dayes, and adjust each side of them to the 2300, or principal <hi>Calendar</hi> of Time.</p>
            <p>For the Time before the Weeks, we shall find is to be just 75 years, to be assign'd to the <hi>Persian Monarchy,</hi> e're the Angel <hi>Gabriels</hi> Epoch (the <hi>Word</hi> or <hi>Commandment</hi> to restore and build <hi>Jerusalem</hi>) had its true <hi>Exit,</hi> or <hi>Effect</hi> to begin the 70 <hi>weeks.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the time after the Weeks, we shall find it to be 404 Years, but because there will be an excess then of 4 dayes above the 2300, we must therefore consider; The true Epoch of the 404 Years is the Resurrection of Christ; so that these 404 Years joyn the Resurrection of our Lord most contiguously, and 4 years or thereabouts of the 490, shooting beyond his Resurrection, are cut off from being any part of the <hi>Calendar</hi> of the next succeeding time upon this our general Line, as the years of the <hi>Patriarchs</hi> Lives beyond their <hi>Paidopoia,</hi> or Procreation of Children, are all plainly lopp'd off from the <hi>Calendar</hi> of that Time, which is continued in the following <hi>Patriarch.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There are besides the bare Lines of Time, very signal and notable concurrent Events, that make these Lines, as surer, so much more conversable, and worthy of Remarque.</p>
            <p>For if Scripture had given us these principal and colla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teral Lines of Time, and no Indications of Matters of Fact, as Instances of his Government of the World in relation to his Church, they might look like imaginary Lines to us, but when we find them cloathed, or incarnate in Action, they will appear more substantial to us.</p>
            <p>I will therefore endeavour in the following of these Lines, to observe the Accounts of things themselves, grafted upon them by the Word of God, that may most consolidate them.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:54329:12"/>
            <p> The first part then of this Line of Time carries the <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sian Monarchy</hi> along with it, not in the whole Duration of it, but as it reaches to the 70 <hi>weeks.</hi> And this, as I shall give it, may, I confess, seem not an imaginary Line, but an Imagination upon that Line; For I derive it from just so many years, as are nam'd of the <hi>Persian</hi> Monarchy in Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture.</p>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Of <hi>Cyrus.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>3</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>The time of the <hi>Persian</hi> Prince <hi>withstanding Christ,</hi> Days for Years,</cell>
                     <cell>21</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>All which time <hi>Daniel</hi> solemniz'd a Fast, 3 <hi>weeks</hi> of <hi>prophetick Days</hi> just 21 also.</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Of <hi>Darius</hi> to the finishing of the <hi>Temple.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>6</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Of <hi>Xerxes</hi> or <hi>Ahasuerus,</hi> from the 13th of the Month <hi>Adar,</hi> to the 13th of the following Years Month <hi>Adar</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>13</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Of <hi>Artaxerxes Longimanus</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>32</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>Sum 75</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>And just 75 Years will be found betwixt the last <hi>rising of the Witnesses,</hi> at the <hi>seventh Trumpet,</hi> and the <hi>New Jerusa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem.</hi> Yet I should not have introduced this as a Chro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nological Line, but for these Reasons.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That it is agreed by the generality of Chronologers, there was a space betwixt <hi>Cyrus</hi> his Decree, and the seven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Weeks commencing, and yet it is of almost indetermi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable Controversie, what space it is.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That I make it but a collateral Line, assur'd and strengthened by the principal; which determines its just Bounds by a compare with after Times; and just so much as by that Compare is necessary.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That the Times thereupon affixable, and the Reign of each <hi>Persian</hi> Prince in that space, are such as agree with soundest Chronology, except in the allotment of ten years
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:54329:12"/>of <hi>Persian</hi> Monarchy to <hi>Cyrus,</hi> which yet some Learned men give him:
<table>
                  <row>
                     <cell>To <hi>Cyrus</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>10</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>To <hi>Cambyses</hi> and <hi>Smerdis</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>8</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>To <hi>Darius Hystaspis</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>31</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>To <hi>Xerxes</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>20</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>To <hi>Artaxerxes,</hi> to his Decree for <hi>Jerusalem</hi> in his 7th</cell>
                     <cell>6</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>Sum 75</cell>
                  </row>
               </table> For in that his 7th the <hi>Weeks</hi> set out; and so we have that Parabolical Sum the Scripture gives us, truly made up, while it did not please the Wisdom of the Holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit to give an exact <hi>Chronology</hi> of a <hi>Pagan</hi> Monarchy.</p>
            <p n="4">4. But especially I observe, Sacred Writing assumes to it self, while it preserves infallibly the truth of Things, and their <hi>Chronology,</hi> so far as it is pleas'd to intermeddle in them, yet where it is necessary to its purpose, it does in a figure prune off for its own Service, what really was, and represents it as if it was not. So it does <hi>Melchisedek</hi>'s <hi>Genealogy, Birth,</hi> and <hi>Death,</hi> as if they had not been, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though in due place it assign'd them all to <hi>Sem:</hi> So in establishing the <hi>Four Kings</hi> in our <hi>Lords Genealogy,</hi> it cuts off <hi>Joash</hi> and <hi>Amaziah</hi> as if they had not been, and yet writes their Reigns in its History.</p>
            <p>Now this part of the Principal, and collateral Line, is charged with these occurrents recorded in Holy Story.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Cyrus</hi> his Decree to build the <hi>Temple,</hi> and its Effect,
<note place="margin">Ezr. <hi>c.</hi> 1, 2, 3.</note> as far as setting up the <hi>Altar,</hi> and laying the <hi>Foundations</hi> of the <hi>Temple.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The Prohibition of any farther progress,
<note place="margin">Ez. <hi>c.</hi> 4.</note> in the ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence of <hi>Cyrus</hi> in his Wars (as may be well suppos'd) and the ill influence of
<note n="*" place="margin">Or <hi>Aha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suerus.</hi> Ezra 4.6.</note>
               <hi>Cambyses,</hi> during his Fathers Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence, and his, and
<note n="*" place="margin">Or <hi>Arta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xerxes.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>Smerdis,</hi> or <hi>Magus,</hi> their Countermand
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:54329:13"/>during their own Reign. So that it was not finish'd till the 6th of <hi>Darius Hystaspis,</hi> nor indeed till: <hi>Artaxerxes</hi> his 7th.
<note place="margin">Dan. 10.</note> The Presence of <hi>Christ, the man cloathed in Linnen,</hi> as the High Priest of his Church, overseeing the Building, was so necessary all that time, first, as by way of Contest against the <hi>Persian Prince,</hi> or <hi>Angel,</hi> till <hi>Darius</hi> his <hi>second Year;</hi> then by Encouragement to his <hi>sixth,</hi> that all that time of 21 prophetick Days, he could not come to give <hi>Daniel</hi> an answer, though his <hi>words were heard</hi> from the <hi>first day he chasten'd himself.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3.
<note place="margin">Cap. 10.</note> Christ, immediately after he had given <hi>Daniel</hi> that <hi>long Vision,</hi> before which he fell again into the former pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetical <hi>deep sleep,</hi> as at the 2300 <hi>Evening-morning-Vision</hi> return'd to the <hi>Persian</hi> Court, to fight with <hi>Xerxes,</hi> the then great,
<note place="margin">Dan. 11.</note> and of all the most Rich Monarch of <hi>Persia,</hi> but in the time of his going forth, the <hi>King,</hi> or <hi>Power</hi> of <hi>Grecia,</hi> would have defeated <hi>Xerxes</hi> his Expedition into <hi>Greece.</hi> Immediately after which, in his Thirteenth year, the beginning of it, the Letters were sign'd for the <hi>Jews</hi> Destruction on the <hi>twelfth month;</hi> upon which Christ <hi>fought</hi> with him and overcame him, so that all things were turn'd into another Channel in favour of the <hi>Jews:</hi> And Christ had no farther Contest with that Monarchy, till it was broken by <hi>Alexander</hi> the Great: on which Account <hi>Xerxes</hi> is so particularly describ'd, in the Prophecy, as lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the foundation of that Quarrel, <hi>Alexander</hi> so long af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter avong'd, in the Ruine of the <hi>Persian</hi> Kingdom.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Next follows the beginning of the <hi>Weeks,</hi> when the Command by <hi>Artaxerxes</hi> for the <hi>restoring</hi> and <hi>building Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rusalem,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ez. 7.11.</note> had its perfect and compleat <hi>Exitus,</hi> or <hi>going forth.</hi> For by <hi>going forth</hi> is not intended its Initial <hi>Going forth,</hi> as it were the first or half sound, but its effective comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental <hi>Going forth,</hi> so that it needed to go forth no fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; And that this was in <hi>Artaxerxes</hi> his 7th Year, Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture-History hath given us many assurances.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:54329:13"/> 1. Else if we account the Initial, or first <hi>going forth,</hi> we must account from <hi>Cyrus,</hi> which very few do, and against all consent of History is it, that the 490 Years to Christ should begin so high.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It is most probable this <hi>Artaxerxes Longimanus</hi> was the Son of <hi>Esther,</hi> under the good Education and Influence of <hi>Mordecai,</hi> who <hi>sought the Peace of his Seed.</hi> This <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taxerxes</hi> at his manly Age of 21, falling in the 7th Year of his Reign from <hi>Xerxes</hi> (or <hi>Ahasuerus</hi>) his Father's Death, sent forth this Literal Extensive Decree to all Things that might restore <hi>Jerusalem,</hi> and make it answer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to it self, even to the utmost of <hi>Ezra</hi>'s desire; at the beginning of the Year also corresponding with all Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Epochs.</p>
            <p n="3">3. It was the most solemn Decree, the Scripture re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords, for it joyns the <hi>King and his seven Counsellors</hi> in it, with the Complacency of all the <hi>mighty Princes,</hi> before whom <hi>Ezra found favour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. Scripture unites the <hi>Commandment</hi> of the <hi>God of Is<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael,</hi> the <hi>Command</hi> of <hi>Cyrus, Darius,</hi> and <hi>Artaxerxes, the,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ez. 6.7.</note> or that Eminent <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Persia;</hi> (and it may be inquir'd, whether by the <hi>God</hi> of <hi>Israel</hi> is not to be understood, the Son of <hi>God,</hi> the <hi>man in linnen,</hi> who was present in <hi>Persia</hi> on the <hi>Jews</hi> behalf;) Now it is observable, <hi>Artaxerxes</hi> his Decree makes a continual mention of the <hi>Law,</hi> and <hi>Will of God,</hi> by which All things were to be squar'd; so that it looks like that principal Command, that interlock'd it self thus with the Divine Command, which Command <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus</hi> acknowledged first, and the Angel to <hi>Daniel</hi> assures at his first praying, and <hi>Ezra</hi> names first, and till this the <hi>Temple,</hi> the principal part and Glory of <hi>Jerusalem,</hi> is not finish'd; so that <hi>Artaxerxes</hi> his Reign is anticipated as to the Time, but not as to the great Effect of <hi>Finishing the Temple.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. That which lastly confirms us, the <hi>Weeks</hi> begin at this Decree of <hi>Artaxerxes</hi> his 7th <hi>Year,</hi> is,
<note place="margin">Neh. 2.1.</note> That in his <hi>Twentieth</hi>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:54329:14"/>Year, in the Month <hi>Nisan,</hi> the beginning of the Year, He sent <hi>Letters</hi> for the <hi>building the Wall,</hi> Letters in pursuit of the Decree, not a new Decree; <hi>Ezra</hi>'s modesty by reason of the great Charge, might stop his proceedings in build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, though the Decree extended to all his desire; besides the slowness of People in Publick Undertakings; for that the private Houses were building with the Temple from <hi>Cyrus</hi> his first Decree, is plain from <hi>Haggai</hi>'s reproof, in <hi>Darius</hi> his second Year. <hi>Is it time for you, oh ye, to dwell in cieled Houses, while this House lies waste?</hi> But this particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar will be farther observable under the next Account of Time.</p>
            <p>We pass therefore upon the principal Line of Time, from the Epoch of the <hi>Weeks,</hi> to the Division of the <hi>Weeks</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves on that most Noble Line of Time, though Collate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral to the Principal, <hi>viz.</hi> the 70 <hi>Weeks.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And it is first given intire; To <hi>Messiah the Prince;</hi> writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten so at his Death by <hi>Pilate,</hi> consecrated so by God at his Resurrection and Ascension: The Kingdom God sets up in the dayes of the <hi>Roman</hi> Kingdom, that is to <hi>destroy</hi> all others, and to <hi>endure it self for ever,</hi> begins at the end of this Line, which is divided,
<list>
                  <item>1. Into 7 <hi>Weeks.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. Into 62 <hi>Weeks.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. Into one <hi>Week.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Into seven Weeks, assign'd to the <hi>Building</hi> of the <hi>wall</hi> and <hi>street,</hi> and settling the whole Defensive Polity of <hi>Jerusalem</hi> by <hi>Nehemiah;</hi> for which, after some pause from the <hi>going forth of the Command, viz.</hi> from <hi>Artaxerxes</hi> his 7th to his 20th, It is said, <hi>The street</hi> and the <hi>wall shall be built;</hi> a distinct member from the going forth of the <hi>word</hi> to build <hi>Jerusalem.</hi> Within seven Weeks then from the Epoch, or beginning of the Weeks, shall <hi>the wall and street be built,</hi> that is, the whole strength and order of the <hi>Jewish</hi> Affairs, be settled by <hi>Nehemiah;</hi> accordingly, that there might be space for it, these <hi>seven weeks</hi> are let into
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:54329:14"/>
               <hi>Darius Nothus</hi> his Reign,
<note place="margin">Nehem. 12.22.</note> which again secures us of the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of <hi>the weeks:</hi> For if they had begun at <hi>Darius Hysta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spis</hi> his second or sixth (much more if at <hi>Cyrus</hi> his first) there had been room for the 7 Weeks or 49 Years without the mention of <hi>Darius Nothus</hi> his Reign, above 60 years inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vening betwixt <hi>Darius Hystaspis</hi> his Sixth and <hi>Artaxerxes</hi> his Twentieth.</p>
            <p>On the other side, if they had begun at <hi>Artaxerxes</hi> his Twentieth, the mention of <hi>Darius Nothus,</hi> his Successor's Reign, had not been large enough to entertain these <hi>seven weeks,</hi> for allowing (at the most liberal rate) twenty six to <hi>Artaxerxes</hi> beyond his twentieth, and at most twenty to <hi>Darius Nothus,</hi> there was room only for forty six, not for forty nine: but from <hi>Artaxerxes</hi> his seventh to <hi>Darius Nothus</hi> his Reign, there is large Receipt, and to spare, for difference of Accounts, that can probably be: so that this short mention of <hi>Darius</hi> his Reign, gives us great light in stating this Time: for the sake of which it is mention'd, and but onely mention'd.</p>
            <p n="2">2. After the seven Weeks run out, by a short propheti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal dash <hi>(Times of Trouble)</hi> the whole History of the 62 <hi>weeks</hi> is compriz'd, which are more at large describ'd in <hi>Daniel</hi>'s last Vision. After the Demonarchizing of <hi>Persia</hi> by <hi>Alexander</hi> and <hi>Alexander</hi>'s <hi>Death,</hi> and the Division of his Kingdom to four, Christ appears no more as fighting for the <hi>Jews,</hi> but, offended at their Sins, so severely reprov'd by <hi>Malachi,</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferts them, and so <hi>Troubles</hi> succeed: For in the Conflicts betwixt the Successive Kingdoms of <hi>Syria</hi> and <hi>Egypt,</hi> the <hi>Jews</hi> were never secure: For their sakes therefore concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in them, there is so large an Account of their Commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions betwixt one another: as also to give some general Prospect of the Time till the Prophecy comes down to <hi>Antiochus Epiphanes,</hi> who is more largely describ'd:</p>
            <p n="1">1. As a Minister of Divine Vengeance upon the <hi>Jews Transgression,</hi> and <hi>Transgressors come to the fall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:54329:15"/> 2. As a Salvage Persecuter of the Church, and People of God, to be <hi>broken without Hand,</hi> that is, by an immediate Divine Vengeance, and therein a Type of <hi>Antichrist.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Upon him therefore, as a Bridge, does the Divine Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy pass first to the <hi>Roman Imperial</hi> Power; of which there had been a former Intimation under <hi>Antiochus</hi> the <hi>Great,</hi> whose <hi>Reproach</hi> (the <hi>Romans</hi> taking the Reproach offered to their Allies, as if to themselves) cast back upon him <hi>without their own Reproach,</hi> signifying their uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troulable Victoriousness. But more expresly does it pass to the <hi>Romans</hi> by <hi>Antiochus Epiphanes</hi> in the <hi>Ships of Chittim,</hi> or the <hi>Romans</hi> comming against him, and causing him to desist from his enterprize against <hi>Egypt;</hi> and yet more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presly by the Description of a King that shall do after his Will; in which the <hi>Roman</hi> or 4th <hi>Monarchy</hi> is in brief comprehended, as if it had been more largely in <hi>Nebuchad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nezzars Image,</hi> and <hi>Daniels</hi> Vision of the <hi>four Beasts</hi> in the first year of <hi>Belschazzar.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Upon the principal Line then we have;</p>
            <p n="1">1. The setting of the <hi>Babylonian Monarchy,</hi> just at the beginning of the Line, as was before described.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The rising of the <hi>Persian Monarchy,</hi> and its conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance to the 70 <hi>Weeks</hi> and an Age or more after.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Within the 70 <hi>Weeks,</hi> we have upon both the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal and collateral Line, the <hi>Persian Monarchy</hi> falling un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the King of <hi>Graecia,</hi> and the <hi>Graecian</hi> rising to its great height in <hi>Alexander,</hi> and after his Death <hi>divided to the four Winds.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. We have the <hi>Roman Monarchy</hi> declared to be risen in their Arbitrarious Controll of <hi>Antiochus the Great,</hi> and <hi>Antiochus Epiphanes</hi> his son. And so there remains the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing of the Kingdom of Christ in the dayes of the fourth Monarchy; for which this noblest of Lines is chiefly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, as was before noted, to <hi>Messiah the Prince.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the mean time it is to be observed,</p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:54329:15"/>
            <p> The chief Eye of <hi>Daniels</hi> Prophecy is upon the <hi>Roman</hi> Monarchy, as wherein the Kingdom of Christ was to rise.</p>
            <p>And in that, upon the <hi>little Horn with Eyes,</hi> and a <hi>mouth speaking great things;</hi> to whom it immediately passes from <hi>the King doing according to his Will,</hi> even to the <hi>Antichri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian King,</hi> whom all the rest of that Description touches, and him only: and so goes along to his end, in the end of <hi>Dan. cap.</hi> 11th and 12th, as is after to be shewn.</p>
            <p>And therefore the extraordinary notice taken of <hi>Antio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chus Epiphanes</hi> is, because in his Action in the World; in his Time 2300 <hi>evenings mornings;</hi> in his Destruction; and even throughout every one of these; he is an extraordinary and express Type of <hi>Antichrist,</hi> as is further to be shewn.</p>
            <p n="3">3. We are thus come to the third Division, the <hi>one</hi> or <hi>last Week,</hi> before which, in the latter end of the 62 <hi>Weeks</hi> our Lord is born, and his private Life shaddowed under a a Veil of secresie. At the beginning of the last Week he is baptized, and begins the <hi>confirming the Covenant with many for one Week</hi> in his publick Ministry. In the midst of it he causes <hi>Sacrifice</hi> to <hi>cease</hi> by the oblation of himself, and leaves the confirmation of the Covenant to go on by the Apostles: at the end of which the <hi>Jews</hi> are finally re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected to a Curse.</p>
            <p>On the third day after Death, <hi>our Lord</hi> rises again from the Dead, in the beginning of the Year also, and fixes the new Epoch of the <hi>Resurrection,</hi> the true Epoch of the whole Time of the <hi>Book</hi> of the <hi>Revelation,</hi> from which every particular Time is to be measured; so that though there is a <hi>half Week</hi> remaining, that runs under the time from this new Epoch, yet still the measure of Time is ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from the Epoch it self, that is, the measure of any Times in that Book is taken from thence.</p>
            <p>And though the calling of the Gentiles was not imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately after the the Resurrection of Christ, yet <hi>Christs ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding</hi> on <hi>conquering</hi> and to <hi>conquer</hi> is to be dated from thence, because that of the Epoch of the <hi>Apocalyps</hi> and the Epoch
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:54329:16"/>also of Christs Commission to the <hi>Apostles, to go into all the World,</hi> and <hi>to preach the Gospel to every Creature: To teach all Nations, because all Power was given to him in Heaven, and in Earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And though the <hi>Churches</hi> of <hi>Asia</hi> were not gathered at this Time, nor, as <hi>Epiphanius</hi> tells us, was <hi>Thyatyra</hi> at the very Time of giving the <hi>Revelation,</hi> founded, yet still they are visionally described, and the Time they denote is from the Resurrection of Christ; for that they are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presented as in Being, when one at least was not in Being, is an Argument they are chiefly made use of, as prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick Schemes.</p>
            <p>At this Time <hi>God set his King upon the Holy Hill of Zion,</hi> saying to him, <hi>Thou art my Son, This day have I begotten thee: Ask of me and I will give thee the Heathen for an Inheritance, and the uttermost parts of the Earth for a Possession.</hi> And because the <hi>Roman Empire</hi> did then in a manner embrace the World, and was that fourth <hi>Monarchy, in the days of which God would set up a Kingdom:</hi> There was a particular Aim of Christ, at being the King and Head of that Empire, as he did become at the Reign of <hi>Constantine:</hi> Of this as an Epoch there are these Assuran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</p>
            <p n="1">1. St. <hi>Johns</hi> being in <hi>the Spirit on the Lords Day;</hi> that is, not only on the Christian Sabbath, though that be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded, but the very day of the Resurrection is visionally recalled, and placed as the Epoch of the whole <hi>Apocalyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick</hi> Time.</p>
            <p>For in that Book, a mystical, prophetick figurative Sense (which is the first Rule of interpreting the <hi>Revelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> I would give) is as the litteral Sense to all other Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and therefore to be preferr'd, when it can possibly be chosen. Now St. <hi>Johns</hi> being <hi>in the Spirit</hi> on the <hi>Lords Day,</hi> as it gives Honour to that Day, as a Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Sabbath, and the first day of the Week is of no drift, or avail, as to the Prophecy, though its certain that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:54329:16"/>moral sense of the Holiness of the <hi>Lords Day;</hi> Yet the primary and of greatest Force in such a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetick Book is, that it fixes the Era, or Epoch of the whole, and so undoubtedly it does, as on the Day of the Resurrection of Christ.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In the first presatory Vision to the <hi>Revelation;</hi> Christ, as eying this Epoch, styles himself <hi>the Faithful Witness, the first begotten from the Dead,</hi> and <hi>Prince of the Kings of the Earth.</hi> And whether his calling himself the <hi>faithful Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness</hi> at the same Time, may not have some Relation to the securing the Duration of his Kingdom from that Epoch, in Allusion to <hi>Psalm</hi> 87. As the <hi>Sun the Faithful Witness in Heaven</hi> does the whole course of Time, may be inquired.</p>
            <p>He charactarizes himself, <hi>I was dead and am alive,</hi> and <hi>live for Evermore.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When in the second Visionall preface, he comes to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the <hi>sealed Book,</hi> and to open it, it was in the truth of the Matter to receive the Kingdom, and Dominion fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>told to him in <hi>Daniel,</hi> out of the <hi>Hand of him that sat on the Throne;</hi> In the <hi>midst</hi> of which, <hi>He stood</hi> as a <hi>Lamb newly slain,</hi> even just at his Resurrection, or <hi>Ascension,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>sitting down;</hi> Then they brought him nigh to the <hi>Anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent of Days,</hi> and he <hi>asked of his Father,</hi> and <hi>he gave him,</hi> &amp;c. As in the <hi>Psalm</hi> before; which may assure us, his very Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surrection is the very Epoch of the Prophecy.</p>
            <p>Thus we have brought our principal Line from the Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation down to <hi>Apocalyptick</hi> Time, and from <hi>Cyrus</hi> with its collataral Line, and both in Union one to another, so as to add strength to each.</p>
            <p>Now because what is done, is done chiefly for the set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling true <hi>Apocalyptick</hi> Time, it is necessary that we make Reflection upon what is past, that we may see what will from thence be contributed, to what is now to be under Consideration.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Let us make due observations upon all the Line foregoing, and we shall find the Joynts of its Continuati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:54329:17"/>remarqued by Rescues of the Church of God from some great Oppression of their Enemies general Defection from God, and his Judgment upon it.</p>
            <p>It must needs then confirm us in the belief there is such a Line drawn out by God: if we can find at the end of it Characters of such Dignity and Glory, as are equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valent to the Care of God over it, from the very first to the last in these Regards. And it must increase the Confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation very much, if we can observe all along such Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, and Types upon the Line, as that end hath in a por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traicture, to the Life, and of full Dimensions upon it self: Let us then lay our Eye directly to the end of <hi>Apocalyptick</hi> Time, and we there shall find the fall of <hi>Mystical Babylon,</hi> together with the <hi>Pagan</hi> Cities, and the Abolition of their Apostasie from God, and Tyranny over his Church; And the coming down of the <hi>New Jerusalem,</hi> the highest Estate of the Holiness, and Happiness of Gods Servants below the Supream Heaven. Both at the end of this Line.</p>
            <p>And that we may know,
<note place="margin">Apoc. 16, 17. c. 21.6.</note> these two are the Butts, and utmost Pillars, as it were, of all Prophecy, They are both of them engraven with <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>It is done, It is done.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Even as at the Lords-Death he Solemnly declared <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or <hi>It is finished,</hi> remonstrated his Death, and the Sacrifice of himself, as the end of all Prophecy, and typi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal History, so far as concern'd his Humiliation, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption.</p>
            <p>So these two are the Ends of the same Prophecy, and History, in what is collineated to his Exaltation, and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom in this World; And each of them in their kinds wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to be such Ends.</p>
            <p>And again, if we look back upon all parts of the Line, either in the several Joynts of the Principal, or the Collate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals, we shall find them full of Images, and Adumbrations si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milar to these Ends; especially the parts of the Principal are always so ennobled.</p>
            <p>And the Son of God, the <hi>Lamb</hi> continually present all
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:54329:17"/>along, and upon each part of this Line, and therefore is peculiarly styl'd in Relation to it, <hi>the Alpha,</hi> and <hi>Omega; the Beginning and the End;</hi> the <hi>First and the Last.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The signatures of the Beginning of the Line at the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, coming out of the Darkness of nothing, and confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion, I have already observed.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Flood upon the Ʋngodly,</hi> and the World rising, as a new Heaven, and Earth out of it, represent these final <hi>new Heavens</hi> and <hi>new Earth,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Covenant of God to drown the World no more, Types the <hi>no Sea</hi> of that State.</p>
            <p>The second and third Chapters of <hi>Peter</hi>'s second Epistle seem to make a compare, and I have before pointed to <hi>Esaia</hi>'s 54.9.10. Apoc. 10.1. alluding to it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Egypts</hi> enslaving <hi>Israel</hi> rescued by successive Plagues, as so many <hi>Vials</hi> poured out on <hi>spiritual Egypt,</hi> and <hi>Pharaoh</hi> like the <hi>Beast cast into the Red-Sea,</hi> as into a <hi>Lake of Fire,</hi> under the Ministry of <hi>Moses</hi> and <hi>Aaron, two Witnesses,</hi> on whom <hi>the Spirit of Life from God</hi> enter'd, are too manifest to need any more then their mention: upon which fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed the <hi>Tryumphal Song,</hi> and the Erection of the <hi>Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle of Testimony.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Solomons</hi> illustrious <hi>Jerusalem,</hi> and magnificent Temple, after the ignoble Times of the <hi>Judges,</hi> and the <hi>Israelites</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually <hi>trodden under Foot of the Gentiles,</hi> are plain prefigura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the new <hi>Jerusalem,</hi> and its <hi>richesse</hi> after so black a state.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ezekiels</hi> Visional Temple, and <hi>Jerusalem,</hi> and <hi>Cyrus,</hi> and the Kings of <hi>Persia</hi> restoring <hi>Jerusalem,</hi> and the Temple, are more then Types, as will appear.</p>
            <p>Our Lords Rejection by the <hi>Jews,</hi> his Death, Resurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and Ascension were Prophetick of his long Humiliati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in his Members, and his glorious Kingdom after.</p>
            <p>And what should I speak in the collaterals of <hi>Enochs Translation</hi> to Heaven.</p>
            <p>Of <hi>Sodom</hi> burnt, and Gods declaring it to <hi>Abraham,</hi> the grand Promissee of the <hi>new Jerusalem:</hi> and <hi>Lots</hi> Testimony
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:54329:18"/>against it in resemblance of <hi>spiritual Sodom,</hi> and the <hi>Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesses</hi> lying dead in the <hi>Street.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Of the slaughter at <hi>Megiddo</hi> of the Kings, and <hi>Deborahs</hi> Song of Victory.</p>
            <p>Of <hi>Elijah,</hi> and <hi>Elisha</hi> prophecying in that long Idolatry of <hi>Israel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Of <hi>Jehoshaphats Valley.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To all which, and many more the <hi>Apocalyps</hi> hath such frequent Reference.</p>
            <p>By all which we may know, what renowned ends of Prophecy these two are, and that in them the <hi>Mistery of God declared to his Servants, the Prophets,</hi> is to be finished, in Symbolism with our Lords <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>And this I think a valuable Reason; we may expect a principal Line in the Scripture, drawn out to these Ends, and Collaterals as parallell, as equal Lines are to equal.</p>
            <p>But yet further to confirm it, let us duely enquire the true sence of <hi>Apocalyps</hi> or <hi>Revelation;</hi> Why such a Title is given to a Book, we justly account so obscure.</p>
            <p>Far it is from the Sense of it, that the things contained in it are made plain, as other Scriptures, necessary to Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation; that every diligent Mind, though but of ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Capacity, may understand; but it hath these two great Senses.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That it is by Jesus Christ <hi>signified,</hi> or imprinted in such Types, and prophetick Schemes, as are much fuller and clearer, then those of the Old Testament, and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of the greater Light of the New.</p>
            <p>And such as in the State of the <hi>new Jerusalem</hi> shall ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it the Contemplation, and Admiration of all the happy Servants of Christ, who shall then fully compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend the wonderful Contrivance, and curious Artifice of it.</p>
            <p>And in the mean time, those whose Hearts God stirs up, and inables to search into it, may humbly derive Light from it, as far as they can, for the Instruction, and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solation
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:54329:18"/>of the Church of God, though they take in but a little of it, and are often in mistakes.</p>
            <p>Even as the Book of Creation and Providence shall in Eternity be fully understood, and now we may endeavour to know all we can, however we fall short.</p>
            <p>But still as the Gospel in all the parts of it, is the last Revelation of God to Man, so is this Book of the last end of things, and so the Lines run into it certainly to the end.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It is indeed the real sovereign conduct of things into their last Events, and Results by Jesus Christ, the Media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, who therefore appeared in the <hi>middle of the Throne,</hi> and especially, it is the Production of those two great ends, so often aforenamed.</p>
            <p>Thus to <hi>shew to his Servants things that must shortly come to pass,</hi> is to begin to derive them into effect, even as God is said to <hi>shew Christ</hi> at last, that is to give him Glory and Power before all the World, and as Christ is revealed, when he indeed comes.</p>
            <p>The receiving the <hi>Book</hi> therefore out of the <hi>Right Hand</hi> of him that <hi>sat on the Throne,</hi> was the <hi>receiving a Kingdom,</hi> and <hi>Dominion never to be destroyed,</hi> extending to that glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Kingdom of Christ.</p>
            <p>So it is the <hi>Revelation of Jesus Christ,</hi> which God gave to him, that is, Sovereign Rule of all to the end of the World.</p>
            <p>And none else could so much as <hi>look on the Book;</hi> that is, It was an incommunicable Authority given to Christ, and a Greatness above any meer Creature to sway such a <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation,</hi> or Government intended by it.</p>
            <p>From both which it is evident, that in this Book are to be found Lines, running out of the Prophecy of the Old Testament into it, and to the ends in it; and Lines in it self, with which those other unite at its Beginning, and Epoch; and so run together to the end and period of it, if not in express numeral Lines of Time, yet of History, Fact, and Event.</p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:54329:19"/>
            <p> Or if but partial Lines, they fall in at the just point with the same Lines, as given in the <hi>Apocalypse,</hi> and continue with them, as far as they goe,</p>
            <p>And according to these, the supream Power of Christ produces, gives Being and Event to all things, to the end,</p>
            <p>And proportionable to the Sense of <hi>Revelation,</hi> is that of <hi>Reading,</hi> and <hi>Hearing</hi> it, and the <hi>Blessedness</hi> pronounced upon them that <hi>Read</hi> and <hi>Hear.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For it is not the Intention of the Holy Spirit, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fine and restrain the Blessedness from very many, that both <hi>Read</hi> and <hi>Hear</hi> it in the true Sense, though they never made an attempt to expound it, or receive Expositions of it; nay, it may be thought a presumptuous Attempt so to do: But it means,</p>
            <p n="1">1. That the Lord Jesus does guide, and manuduct his Servants, that sincerely Love and Fear him, to <hi>Teach, Worship, Pray,</hi> and <hi>Practise,</hi> and also to <hi>Suffer</hi> according to the true <hi>Apostolical</hi> measures of that Book, though they dare not assume to understand it: so multitudes have <hi>read,</hi> and <hi>heard</hi> it, that never proceeded farther in it: And such <hi>wise</hi> shall <hi>shine as Stars</hi> in the <hi>Firmament,</hi> and be blessed in <hi>Reading,</hi> and <hi>Hearing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>On the other side, many by contrary Action have <hi>ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded,</hi> and <hi>taken away,</hi> and so forfeited their part in the Blessings, and drawn upon themselves the <hi>Plagues</hi> of it, that never intermeddled any way with the Text,</p>
            <p n="2">2. It is a figurative Expression of Christs Allotment to his Servants, and certainly leading them that look for it, into the Fruition and Happiness of the <hi>New Jerusalem,</hi> though we cannot yet apprehend the various Methods, and Degrees of his so doing: Thus, <hi>blessed is he that waiteth</hi> and <hi>cometh</hi> to the 1335 dayes, that is, to the enjoyment of that State, and to <hi>read,</hi> and <hi>hear</hi> by enjoying: on the other side <hi>without are Doggs, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. This does not exclude the due Recompences of all humble, sincere, and holy Researches into this Book, to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstand, or to make others understand it.</p>
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:54329:19"/>
            <p> Nor exempt them from its <hi>Anathema,</hi> who wilfully, and with violence endeavour to force it from its True sense, by wresting Interpretations: Hating that, they sus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect its meaning, they deride all wise and prudent At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts for the Explanation of it.</p>
            <p>This therefore being Prefac'd, we shall find Apocalyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick Time ascertain'd to us three ways.</p>
            <p n="1">1. By Characters of Time of its own, and which lye within it self, and that these should be concerted, none can deny.</p>
            <p n="2">2. By the so often Commemorated principal Line of 2300 <hi>Evenings</hi> and <hi>Mornings,</hi> and allowing it to be such a Line, it must be necessary to seek Counsel and Aid of it.</p>
            <p n="3">3. By a right we have of comparing these with <hi>Daniel</hi>'s Times, seeing they point directly to <hi>the End:</hi> and that very <hi>End of Days,</hi> wherein Prophets, Apostles, and Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs, with all other the most Eminent Servants of God shall stand, all in their own Lot, as <hi>Daniel</hi> is assur'd as to his own.</p>
            <p>And in all of these kinds of Time, their Exact Agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment one within another, do assure they were all intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded as Lines of the same Calendar, either Principal or Collateral; seeing Numbers do not use fortuitously (throw them which way you will) to jump constantly into an exact Harmony one with another.</p>
            <p>Seeing then the <hi>Time,</hi> Times, and <hi>Half-Time</hi> in <hi>Dani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el,</hi> or the 1260, into which it is varied in the same <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niel,</hi> with the Addition of first 30, <hi>viz.</hi> 1290, and then with the addition of 45, <hi>viz.</hi> 1335 Days, will be found most exactly to agree with <hi>Apocalyptick Time</hi> in the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal Line, and in that History that stands also as a Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lateral Line in the <hi>Apocalyps.</hi> And that it is the Incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municable property of that Book to produce the <hi>Finishing of Wonders,</hi> and the <hi>Last End,</hi> it cannot be doubted they are the same with the 1260 Days In the <hi>Apocal.</hi> and in
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:54329:20"/>the 30 and 45 additionals, to run along with the History after, and so one and the same Time to <hi>the End.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Even as it cannot be doubted, the <hi>Time, Times, Half-Time</hi> in <hi>Daniel</hi> are the same with the 1260 in <hi>Daniel,</hi> though joyn'd with 30 more, then that the 1290 are the same 1290 in the 1335, though joyn'd to 45 more; as they were, when by themselves.</p>
            <p>The Characters of Apocalyptick Time within it self are,</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Prophetick Church-History, for so I will be bold to call it, extending it self from the Apocalyptick Epoch; in <hi>Six Churches to New Jerusalem.</hi> The Seventh <hi>Church</hi> joyns with a short Appendix, <hi>Apoc.</hi> 20. after the 1000 years to the Day of Judgement, of which the <hi>Apocal.</hi> does not so professedly treat, being the Doctrine of all Plain Scripture.</p>
            <p>The second Character of <hi>Apocalyptick Time</hi> is of the <hi>Seales</hi> and their History, beginning at the same Epoch with the Churches, but making only a Collateral Line to that general period aforenam'd, <hi>viz.</hi> the 1260.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The third is of the <hi>Six Trumpets,</hi> a second part of the same Line, which is distinguish'd within it self, into the first 4 Simple or Plain <hi>Trumpets,</hi> and after them the 2 first <hi>Woe Trumpets,</hi> and the History of each.</p>
            <p>And with the six together concurs most evenly that Collateral Line of Time, <hi>viz.</hi> 1260 Days; call'd al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so <hi>Time, Times, Half a Time,</hi> and 3 <hi>Days</hi> and a <hi>Half,</hi> and 42 <hi>Months,</hi> all Styles of the same Time, and a History pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to them in each of those Styles.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The fourth Character of <hi>Apocalyptick Time</hi> is the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth <hi>Trumpet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Time of the sound of that is measured out by seven <hi>Voices,</hi> beginning as <hi>Thunder,</hi> and drawn out according to the utterances of the seven <hi>sealed Thunders.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And by the Pouring out of 7 <hi>Vials,</hi> which touch the <hi>end it self.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:54329:20"/>
            <p> But this is not all we have to guide us in the setling <hi>Apocalyptick Time.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For, if we closely observe, we shall find, That <hi>Daniel's</hi> Prophecy; so much of it as was <hi>clos'd, shut up,</hi> and <hi>seal'd;</hi> and the <hi>Revelation</hi> contain the same things.</p>
            <p>The one in darker and more antique Figures;</p>
            <p>The other in newer, and, as it were, more modern Emblems:</p>
            <p>The one in fewer, and smaller;</p>
            <p>The other in more various and larger Sculptures:</p>
            <p>The one clos'd, shut, and seal'd up to the <hi>End,</hi> as not yet in an order of coming to pass.</p>
            <p>The other (though, but gradually) unseal'd, and opened; the Epoch of that end being come, and fixed, and things being on a Line, and in a Series of passing into Event; though that Line being long, and of many Years, the end was at first far off:</p>
            <p>As then, the <hi>Beginning of the Gospel</hi> of the <hi>Evangelist Mark,</hi> conjoyns it self with the <hi>end of the Prophet Malachi; Elijah</hi> in the one, being <hi>John the Baptist</hi> in the other.</p>
            <p>Even so does the <hi>Revelation</hi> concert it self with <hi>Daniels closed</hi> and <hi>sealed Book.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And just at that very Crisis of Time, when the <hi>Revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> opens, there did <hi>Daniel</hi> first begin to <hi>seal;</hi> For Sealing and Revelation so strictly correlate one another.</p>
            <p>And that was even at <hi>Messiah, the Prince,</hi> and his Resur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, the Epoch of the <hi>last Times,</hi> and of the <hi>Ends of the World.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So much of the Descriptions of the <hi>Throne,</hi> and the <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient of Dayes sitting</hi> upon it; of the <hi>Son of Man,</hi> his Glory, and Kingdom, as are given in the <hi>Apocalyptical</hi> Prefaces, so much was sealed up in <hi>Daniel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So much Time of the Empire, and of the <hi>Autocratorical</hi> Power of the Emperors, as remained just at <hi>Messiah, the Prince</hi> risen, so much was <hi>shut up,</hi> and <hi>sealed</hi> in <hi>Daniel.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:54329:21"/>
            <p> Even in every one of <hi>Daniels</hi> Visions, particularly that of <hi>Antiochus, his taking away the daily Sacrifice,</hi> the Type of the <hi>End,</hi> and therefore <hi>shut up;</hi> whatever was not ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled before the Resurrection, was sealed, and then opened in its Time, in the <hi>Revelation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And indeed from this very point of Time the <hi>Resurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of our Lord;</hi> all <hi>Apocalyptical</hi> Time is created, and hath its original.</p>
            <p>For just then was the <hi>Kingdom under the whole Heaven</hi> due to the <hi>Great Son of Man,</hi> the <hi>King of Kings,</hi> and <hi>Lord of Lords,</hi> newly risen from the Dead:</p>
            <p>But he, according to his Fathers Counsel and Decree, gives with a most <hi>folemn Oath,
<note place="margin">Dan. 12.</note> Time, Times, Half a Time</hi> to the Kingdom of the <hi>Beast;</hi> and accepts instead of it a Spiritual, Evangelical Kingdom, and this Apocalyptick and Providential Supremacy, untill the Expiration of this Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple Time;
<note place="margin">Apoc. 10.</note> when he <hi>swears again,</hi> There shall be <hi>no more Time,</hi> or <hi>Delay,</hi> but his Kingdom shall come.</p>
            <p>Hence, even from this Delay, arises the <hi>Patience</hi> joyned to the <hi>Kingdom of Jesus Christ.</hi> Apoc. 1.9.</p>
            <p>Now when this <hi>Time, Times, Half Time,</hi> were thus gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to that earnest and early <hi>working Antichristian Kingdom,</hi> in which <hi>Sathan</hi> hath so great an Interest and Efficacy; It was necessary to embarr it, that it might not start out be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore its Time, and so <hi>seven Seales</hi> foreclose it.</p>
            <p>These <hi>Seals</hi> are seven spaces of Time, granted to the <hi>Roman Empire,</hi> before which the <hi>Beast</hi> should not rise into the Power, nor Account of a <hi>Beast</hi> before God.</p>
            <p>Yet were even these spaces, speedily after the <hi>Evangelick Kingdom of Christ</hi> begun in the World, granted to the <hi>mysterious working,</hi> or Conception of <hi>Antichrist</hi> in secret, as it were in the <hi>lowest Parts of the Earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But because, assoon as ever the <hi>last half Time</hi> had in any Moments of it been enjoyed by the <hi>Beast,</hi> the Lord, even as he rose from the dead early in the Morning of the <hi>third Day,</hi> might have entred on his Kingdom, notwithstand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:54329:21"/>his <hi>Oath,</hi> and that his Servants earnestly hoped and desired, he would do so.</p>
            <p>He is pleased after some claims of his Right, and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulgations of it by a <hi>Cry</hi> as the <hi>Roar of a Lyon, the Lyon of the Tribe of Judah,</hi> and seven <hi>Thunders</hi> attendantly <hi>uttering their Voyces;</hi> His Ministers declaring his Kingdom; He is pleased, I say, to <hi>seal</hi> down all again, and to make this <hi>Half Day,</hi> excepting that partial Reformation begun <hi>Anno</hi> 1517. a Time of <hi>Delay,</hi> and all things <hi>continuing as they were.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus the words are again declared <hi>sealed in Daniel,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dan. 12.9. Apoc. 10.</note> and the <hi>Thunders utterances in the Apocal.</hi> and the <hi>Beast</hi> is like to have his <hi>Half Day,</hi> though in a more contracted Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, it being now near its <hi>End</hi> also.</p>
            <p>And whether some Provocation from the Reformed Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches concurr'd not herein, we may have Reason to suspect;</p>
            <p>But the <hi>seventh Trumpets sound</hi> is near, and then his <hi>Oath</hi> obliges him to hasten his Kingdom.</p>
            <p>First, by <hi>seven Voyces</hi> preparatory; of 30 D. space.</p>
            <p>Then by <hi>seven Vials</hi> consummative of the <hi>Mystery of God</hi> in the <hi>Fall of Babylon</hi> and the <hi>comming down of new Jerusa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem</hi> at the end of the 45 D. added more.</p>
            <p>Hence therefore, and thus hath arisen the whole <hi>Dani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elian</hi> and <hi>Apocalyptick Time:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And the date of the 1335 <hi>Dayes, from the taking away the daily Sacrifice,</hi> as by <hi>Antiochus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dan. 12.11.</note> can be no objection to him that considers <hi>Antiochus,</hi> and his <hi>taking away the Daily Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice,</hi> or Service, (for that it may not be restrained to <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice,</hi> the word <hi>continuall</hi> is only used, without any word signifying <hi>Sacrifice, Oblation</hi> or <hi>Offering,</hi> as generally, if not always in other Scriptures.) This <hi>taking away,</hi> I say, was but Typical of the <hi>taking away</hi> the True, constant, publick, divine Worwip by the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the King, that does after his Will.</p>
            <p>For first <hi>Antiochus,</hi> as a <hi>wicked one,</hi> was conceived in se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret Intelligences with wicked Men; Then grown into Power by smiting <hi>Egypt,</hi> he ravag'd <hi>Jerusalem,</hi> from which
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:54329:22"/>Time his <hi>taking away the daily Sacrifice</hi> was dated; Then about two years after, he actually took it away; and set up the <hi>Abomination</hi> that, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Even thus, <hi>the Beast</hi> was first conceived in secret Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties: then in Power, yet as an Infant King, but of much longer and so slower growth, then <hi>Antiochus.</hi> Then he open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly commands one Pagano-Christian Idolatry, and so takes away the <hi>Daily Service</hi> or <hi>Worship.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But from his being a King, though but in a Cradle, the <hi>daily Service</hi> is accounted <hi>taken away</hi> by <hi>Him,</hi> because much polluted then, and He was born the King of that Pollution.</p>
            <p>And from this <hi>taking away</hi> only, can a term worthy of that Pronuntiation be found; <hi>Blessed is he that waiteth, &amp;c.</hi> or of <hi>Daniels standing in his</hi> Lot at <hi>the End of it. Dan.</hi> 12.</p>
            <p>We have then whole <hi>Apocalyptick Time</hi> standing before us.</p>
            <p>In the <hi>Apocalypse</hi> it self.</p>
            <p>In <hi>Daniels</hi> Numbers.</p>
            <p>In our general principal Line.</p>
            <p>In humane History, grown more certain, since our <hi>Lords Era</hi> undoubtedly by Divine Care; and exactly ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>justable to Events, and Times, as made famous by Sacred Account; and that beyond the Force of Controversy.</p>
            <p>And by all Accounts both of Time, and History Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred, we shall sind <hi>Apocalyptick Time</hi> is a Line of 1739 years, from our <hi>Lords Resurrection;</hi> of which have alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy run out with this year current 1651; and so rest 88.</p>
            <p>To which, that we may see how they have been ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pended according to Scripture Prophecy, we shall now apply the Dates of Time, and Events of History foretold in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and verified by general Chronology and Story,</p>
            <p>If it may add any thing to our Understanding the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the Prophecy, and its <hi>Revelation,</hi> to consider the <hi>Book</hi> it self, its <hi>Seales</hi> and <hi>opening;</hi> we may thus conceive it.</p>
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:54329:22"/>
            <p> Let us suppose a <hi>Book</hi> of single Leaves, <hi>written within,</hi> and <hi>on the back side,</hi> as comprizing all the <hi>Apocalyptick Visions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then this Book rolled up in a Cylindrical Form, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der seven Labels fastned with <hi>seven Seales.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then suppose the <hi>first Seal opened,</hi> and the Label remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved; according to the first draught upon the Roll, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the first Label, <hi>John</hi> had the Vision of the <hi>first Rider,</hi> and so on to the <hi>seventh opened:</hi> each of the Sculptures being inlarged with <hi>Visions</hi> and <hi>Voyces,</hi> and illustrated, so as was necessary to <hi>John</hi> by the <hi>Lord</hi> himself.</p>
            <p>The <hi>seven Seales</hi> being <hi>opened,</hi> the Book might be unroll'd, which could not be till the last opened.</p>
            <p>It being then unrolled, the six <hi>first Trumpets,</hi> and their <hi>Visa</hi> appeared on the <hi>back side</hi> of the <hi>Book.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After the Vision of the <hi>sixth Trumpet,</hi> the <hi>Book,</hi> eased of the Labels and Seals, became a <hi>little Book,</hi> was opened, and visionally eaten, and according to it the Visions given in their Order; which order had, as we shall see, its great signification; For in so curious and exact a draught of things, there is not the least Word, Repetition, Reference, nay, not so much as the Order of giving the Visions, without its great Importance, Design, and Highest Artifice.</p>
            <p>That the Beasts Kingdom, after it was unsealed into Event, was yet visionally placed within the Book, so as not to be given, till the <hi>Book</hi> was opened, and some time after, under the seventh <hi>Trumpet,</hi> is not without its Mystery (as is to be shown when we come to it) because in that Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der was the Prophecy received and believed.</p>
            <p>There is yet one thing more to be added, to clear our following Application of History and Events to their just Time, and that especially in Relation to the Church-Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>story, and of very great moment it is to it, as we shall see.</p>
            <p>And that is to concert a true Sense to the <hi>four living Creatures,</hi> inconveniently renderd <hi>four Beasts,</hi> because of
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:54329:23"/>the branded <hi>Apocalyptick Beast,</hi> differing as much from these, as <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> from <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, but because the Translation hath prevailed, we may promiscuously use either.</p>
            <p>They are a Representation of the Apostles, the great Ministry of the New Testament, posted at the four Angles <hi>of the Throne,</hi> as an universal Ministry, diffusing the Gos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel into all Parts of the World: even as the pure <hi>Israelitish</hi> Ministry is Typed by the twenty sour <hi>Elders,</hi> or Heads of <hi>Davids Courses of Priests.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This appears in the living Creatures being employed in all the Services of the New Testament-Time; as in these first <hi>Seales;</hi> saying, <hi>Come and see;</hi> while in that Time the Gospel was spread all over the Empire.</p>
            <p>And the twenty four <hi>Elders</hi> are used in explaining the Prophecies of the old Testament, as an <hi>Elder</hi> informed <hi>John</hi> of <hi>the Lyon of the Tribe of Judah prevailing to open the Seals,</hi> and of the Glories of Christian Martyrs after Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings, even one representing the <hi>Beloved Man Daniel,</hi> who had prophecyed of both before, informed <hi>John the Beloved Disciple.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now of how great moment, the right apprehending the four <hi>living Creatures,</hi> and twenty four <hi>Elders</hi> is to the Church-History, I will very briefly present in these Parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars.</p>
            <p n="1">1. They are placed about the <hi>Throne,</hi> that their Service sometimes, sometimes their Approbative Audience may be Testimonies of the Churches Purity, as Universal, and Catholick, or in that particular matter, they are conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sant about; And their Retirement, and non-Appearance may be an Indication of its Impurity, as in that conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of Catholick and Universal: And the appearance and Service of the twenty four <hi>Elders</hi> alone, without any of the four <hi>Beasts,</hi> is a more lively Emblem of the Church of the New Testament, not being universally pure, though it was in part;
<note place="margin">Apoc. 11.16.</note> seeing in a Song of Praise one alone could not with the Decency of the Type, appear without the
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:54329:23"/>Rest;
<note place="margin">Apoc. 15.7.</note> while within the same confines of Time one of the four Beasts delivers the <hi>Vials.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The order of their Service is first of the four <hi>Beasts,</hi> and then of the twenty four <hi>Elders,</hi> till just upon the <hi>new Jerusalem;</hi> then that order is inverted,
<note place="margin">Apoc. 5.9.</note> and the twenty four <hi>Elders</hi> begin first;
<note place="margin">Apoc. 19.4.</note> And this undoubtedly indicates first the <hi>Jewes</hi> Rejection in their Body, and then their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception at last into their Primogeniture, as <hi>one Body</hi> with the Gentiles.</p>
            <p>And this I conceive will much illustrate the History of the <hi>seven Churches,</hi> which is so inlaid with the History of the whole <hi>Apocalyptick Time;</hi> that though it cannot be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstood alone, yet it cannot be separated without Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, and Deformity to all Parts; but compared, is a great assurance of Time, and History.</p>
            <p>How natural, even Native a soil of Prophetick Schemes relating to the Churches Purity, Apostasy, Recovery, are Churches themselves: so that if any thing in the whole Prophecy pertains to the Church, sure this most of all.</p>
            <p>Nor does it appear condecent to so August a Prophecy, that seven of the obscurest Christian Churches, and none of the longest Survivers, and one at the time of their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing written to, not as yet existing, should receive the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour singled from all the rest, of the Supreme <hi>Apocalyptes</hi> walking in the midst of them, as seven <hi>golden Candlesticks,</hi> and <hi>holding their Angels</hi> particularly as <hi>Stars</hi> in his <hi>Right Hand,</hi> and directing so majestique a Book by Name to them only.</p>
            <p>Their Names (for Names make every where a great part of Prophetick Scripture) besides what other circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stances we know not, undoubtedly made them fit to sustain Prophetick Schemes above others.</p>
            <p>Sure if <hi>Rome</hi> had not been too much a Subject, to be made use of only, as a Scheme; or Schemes not at all in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, It might have lookt to have been preferred, and would, if possible, have made advantage of it.</p>
            <pb n="40" facs="tcp:54329:24"/>
            <p> And though indeed the True Church, as Catholick, be but one, yet as it is always in the New Testament di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versisied by Places, so may it well, yea, and must be, as we see here it is, diversified by Times, and its various states; if there was first an Apostolical Purity, then a Gradual Apostasy, then a Recovery, and that in parts, not all of a Degree, and Elevation in Reformation.</p>
            <p>And if there were any Vertues, or Errors of any of these Churches, that gave them a greater meetness for these <hi>Epistles,</hi> as I do not know any reason to suppose, besides what was common to all the Churches; I should only from thence esteem them fitter to bear the Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy laid upon them.</p>
            <p>Let us then, having thus premis'd, take a view of <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>calyptick Time,</hi> and History, in Concert with the Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of <hi>Daniel,</hi> as it hath been set before us.</p>
            <p>And first of the Space of the <hi>Seales</hi> before the <hi>Beasts Time, Times,</hi> and a <hi>Half,</hi> which by the Principal Line, by the Private Mark of Time in the midst of the <hi>Seales,</hi> by the best Evidence of General History, we affirm to be 404 years to greatest Exactness granted to the <hi>Romane</hi> Imperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Power, first Heathen, then Christian, before Bestian; as the upper side of the <hi>Prince that does after his Will in Daniel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The first Space of it is most justly peculiar to the Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Kingdom of <hi>Messiah,</hi> the <hi>Prince,</hi> purely and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly Divine, and <hi>Apostolical,</hi> and like it self.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Gentiles</hi> are summon'd by the first <hi>Living Creature,</hi> speaking in the deep note of <hi>Thunder; Come, and See.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It was with our Lords <hi>Half-week</hi> of <hi>Confirming the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant,</hi> near 40 years; a Time of Calling to Repentance; but from the Resurrection to <hi>Vespasian</hi> about years 36.</p>
            <p>Christ went out on his <hi>White Horse,</hi> with his <hi>Bow,</hi> making an offer first to the <hi>Jews,</hi> but to found a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom among all Nations, and his <hi>Bow return'd not empty.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="41" facs="tcp:54329:24"/>
            <p>
               <hi>The Woman,</hi> the Church was now <hi>cloathed with the Sun,
<note place="margin">Apoc. 12.1.</note> crowned with twelve Stars,</hi> and the <hi>Moon,</hi> that after had the Ascendent in the 42 <hi>Months, under her Feet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Church of <hi>Ephesus</hi> was the Type of this <hi>Apostolick</hi> Church, while she <hi>tried those that said they were Apostles,
<note place="margin">Apoc. 2.1.</note> and were not, and found them Liers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Tryal is by the Scriptures, into which the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles consigned all truly <hi>Apostolical,</hi> without which, Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity is but like <hi>Nicodemus</hi> his <hi>Mothers Womb;</hi> and return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing into it <hi>the second Time, to be born</hi> in order to Regenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or Reformation, would be to come out again with the same Corruption in the Seed. For out of many Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cencies, and good meanings of Antiquity, all the Churches defilements sprung up.</p>
            <p>When this <hi>Seal</hi> had been opened betwixt 20 and 30 years, the <hi>Beasts Kingdom</hi> begun to look out; <hi>Sathan, the Old Serpent, Deceiver of the Nations</hi> into Idolatry and Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perstition, early attempted Christianity this way,
<note place="margin">2. Thes. 2.70.</note> in <hi>Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shipping Angels,</hi> and other <hi>Ordinances</hi> of Men, and the <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stery of Iniquity begun to work.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There were many other Heresies in the Church in all Times, but which ought to be, and were convinced; but this is the great subject of Prophecy: the farewell of the Epistle of the <hi>Apostle,</hi> and great <hi>Prophet</hi> of the <hi>New Testa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> after the declaration of the <hi>one God,</hi> and the <hi>one Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diator,</hi> was, <hi>Little Children, keep your selves from Idols. Amen.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Jo. 5.21.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The second <hi>Seal</hi> is a space designed to <hi>Jewish</hi> Desolations, foretold by <hi>Daniel</hi> and <hi>Messiah,</hi> and so certainly described in this Prophecy.</p>
            <p>A true, though not so high an <hi>Apostolick</hi> Ministry, calls to behold the Vengeance, as an Evidence of the Truth of Christianity; which also approves it self by Doctrine, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Life and Sufferings throughout all the <hi>Seales,</hi> till <hi>Smyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na,</hi> in the true Members of the Church of <hi>Ephesus,</hi> continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing till then.</p>
            <pb n="42" facs="tcp:54329:25"/>
            <p> And yet the <hi>Mystery of Iniquity</hi> by necessary Supposition works on; which not being espyed, and remonstrated to, and separated from, as is represented in <hi>Smyrna, trying those</hi> that said, they were <hi>Jews, &amp;c.</hi> the whole Church is charged and censured: as innocently paying some Devotions, that after became soul Corruptions:</p>
            <p>The opening of this <hi>Seal</hi> especially removed the <hi>Jewish Pretensions</hi> of being the Supream Church of God, from stand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the way of the <hi>Beast.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It had its Operation from <hi>Vespasian, Titus</hi> first appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on the <hi>Red Horse</hi> of War, and Blood, to <hi>Hadrian's last,</hi> and most fatal. Conflicts with the <hi>Jews,</hi> when the <hi>Great Sword</hi> recolled so fiercely on the Empire it self, and it cost his Army so dear, that he omitted that usual Salute in the Imperial Letter, <hi>Ego quidem &amp; exercitus Valemus;</hi> it lasted till <hi>Hadrian's Death,</hi> years 68.</p>
            <p>The space of the <hi>third Seal</hi> is granted to the Humane and virtuous Government of the <hi>Antonines</hi> at the beginning, and the most Recordedly just Reign of <hi>Alexander Severus,</hi> Son of <hi>Mammaea</hi> at the end of it.</p>
            <p>He is the solemn Rider of the <hi>Black Horse, with a pair of Ballances in his Hand,</hi> and the so cautions and exact Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juster of prices, who is so famous for carrying always with him, and in open view, that so Righteous Beam, our Saviour gave the World; <hi>What ye would have Men do to you, do you also to them and no other.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The time of this <hi>Seal</hi> was most notable for those excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent <hi>Apologyes</hi> of Christianity, by <hi>Justin Martyr,</hi> at the Begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning; <hi>Tertullian's</hi> and <hi>Origen's</hi> at the end of it.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Third living Creature,</hi> the still Apostolical Ministry, says, <hi>Come and see.</hi> Behold Christianity offering it self to the Seales before the wifest and justest of the Emperours, <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets of your own.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And <hi>Alexander</hi> gave Judgment for it, by the very light of Nature, for without being so much as <hi>almost a Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an,</hi> he would have built a Temple in Honour of Christ.</p>
            <pb n="43" facs="tcp:54329:25"/>
            <p> This was a grand experiment of <hi>Divine Patience</hi> leading a Pagan Empire to <hi>Repentance:</hi> For at his Death Venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance pursued it, till it became Christian in <hi>Constantine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But further, by an admirable Artifice of the Divine Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy, here is, though very covertly placed the Boundary of the <hi>Half Time</hi> of the <hi>Seals.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Of Gods long suffering to the Empire, before the <hi>Trumpets sounded</hi> its Ruine.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Concurrently of the Churches Purity, before the <hi>Beasts</hi> rising, as will thus appear.</p>
            <p n="1">1. It is evident to any Considerer, these 7 <hi>Seales</hi> are se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven Spaces of the Time of the <hi>Romane Empire,</hi> after the Resurrection.</p>
            <p n="2">2. There is besides the usual Voice, <hi>Come</hi> and <hi>see,</hi> an extraordinary note of Attention, not by, but to,
<note place="margin">Apoc. 6.6.</note> or in the midst of the <hi>four living Creatures,</hi> a <hi>Measure of Wheat, &amp;c.</hi> to move extraordinary inquiry after the meaning.</p>
            <p n="3">3. By Inquiry into History, it fits none as <hi>Alexander, Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verus,</hi> so just a Prince.</p>
            <p n="4">4. By Inquiry into the Time, He died 202 years after our Lords Resurrection, in the beginning of the year, to correspond it: which doubled reaches to the Empire, torn on all sides by the <hi>Barbarians,</hi> and the 10 <hi>Kings ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing;</hi> besides other concurrent marks of the <hi>Beasts rising.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. By compare upon our principal Line, 404 years neither more nor less from the <hi>Resurrection,</hi> are necessary to adjust the 2300 <hi>Evenings Mornings,</hi> to the last of <hi>Daniels</hi> 1335 <hi>Dayes,</hi> what then can we conclude, but the Ballances divide the Time, as it were by exact weight, one half against the other; and so, precisely define the Time of the <hi>Seals,</hi> the exact Time of the <hi>Beasts rising,</hi> and so of his end, no where else so defined in Scripture: which hath obliged this longer stay upon it.</p>
            <p n="6">6. The <hi>Mystery of Iniquity was still promoting it self:</hi> and made that notable appearance towards the end of this <hi>Seal</hi> in <hi>Victor Bishop of Rome,</hi> his affected Domination, and Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perstition
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:54329:26"/>concerning the nice Time of <hi>Easters</hi> Celebration: but being generally censured, and condemned the Church continued still Apostolical, although it is to be feared <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phesus</hi> was now, if not before in its declining state.</p>
            <p>The whole time of this <hi>Seal</hi> was about 98 years.</p>
            <p>The space of the fourth <hi>Seal</hi> is seized by divine Venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, beginning on the Empire, as Heathen, in the <hi>four Judgments: the Beasts of the Earth:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezek. 14.21.</note> The tyranical Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours, and their bloddy Assassinates; <hi>Sword, Pestilence, and Famine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Emperours were so short lived, that by an elegant Emblem, not an Emperour, but <hi>Death</hi> is the Rider of the <hi>Pale Horse.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And the Mortality so great, that <hi>Hades, Hell,</hi> or the <hi>Grave,</hi> are the only Ensignes.</p>
            <p>The <hi>fourth living Creature</hi> sayes, <hi>Come,</hi> behold the Desola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions wrought by God for the space of 67 years on an Empire impersuasible by all the Methods of Grace.</p>
            <p>This <hi>Seal</hi> opened to the <hi>Beasts</hi> Kingdom, as the uneasiness and continual slitting of the Imperial Power from one to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, was a symptom of its approaching end, as Heathen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ish; which was the principal <hi>Lett</hi> of the <hi>Man of Sin,</hi> as the <hi>Apostle</hi> told the <hi>Thessalonians</hi> in private, though not so fit for an Epistle.</p>
            <p>In the Time of this <hi>Seal, Ephesus</hi> had <hi>left its first Love;</hi> for the <hi>Apostolical</hi> Ministry by divine Forecast ceases from any farther Service, till the <hi>Vials on the Beasts Kingdom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But Indulgences having not the least shew in Antiquity, to shew how distinct the Prophecy is, it returns back to say, <hi>Ephesus</hi> 'in its worst Time, <hi>hated the Deeds of the Nicolatians,</hi> which after became the <hi>Doctrine of Indulgences.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ephesus,</hi> its <hi>Candlestick</hi> is <hi>removed out of its Place,</hi> there being no longer any the Church bearing the Type of the pure, and visible universal <hi>Apostolical Church;</hi> but <hi>Smyrna</hi> rises by the next <hi>Seal</hi> with a <hi>Synagogue of Sathan,</hi> near the appearance <hi>of a Church,</hi> to mask, and ready to over-shade it.</p>
            <pb n="45" facs="tcp:54329:26"/>
            <p> From about the Time of the <hi>Mistery of Iniquity working,</hi> or 25 years after the <hi>Resurrection;
<note place="margin">Dan. 11.36.</note> The King that does after his Will</hi> in the <hi>Heathen Emperours</hi> had been speaking <hi>mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vellous Things against the God of Gods,</hi> by Persecution of Christians down to this Time; and, as a <hi>Red Dragon,</hi> had elpecially carried <hi>Blasphemy, Idolatry,</hi> and <hi>Blood</hi> upon his <hi>Head,</hi> with whom the <hi>Beast</hi> unites after, so as to become <hi>One</hi> with him, though distinct also from him.</p>
            <p>The fifth <hi>Seal</hi> and its space are allotted to <hi>ten prophetical Dayes,</hi> or <hi>Years</hi> of extreme Persecution, and Sufferings of the Christian Church under <hi>Dioclesian.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This was the sinke of Time, into which all the Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Blood flowed, that had been shed by Paganism, and was <hi>required of it in this Generation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Woman</hi> was at this Time in <hi>Pain,</hi> and <hi>cryed out to be delivered,</hi> while the <hi>Dragon waited to devour the Birth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Smyrna</hi> was now risen, as appears by the <hi>ten Daies Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secution,</hi> and being separated from the <hi>Synagogne of Sathan,</hi> is honoured exceedingly by God, even above <hi>Ephesus,</hi> that was the Type of the <hi>Apostolick Church</hi> in its first State. But the <hi>Mystery</hi> of <hi>Iniquity</hi> fermenting, and not understood, nor counterwrought, as it ought to have been, <hi>Ephesus</hi> is in the Type severely rebuked, and <hi>Smyrna</hi> commended only: <hi>Ephesus</hi> loses the <hi>Birth-right,</hi> not <hi>excelling</hi> to the last: and <hi>Smyrna,</hi> though <hi>sorely grieved by Archers,</hi> hath, the <hi>Crown of Life,</hi> and <hi>Philadelphia</hi> after the <hi>Kingdom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This time was reserved by Christ from the <hi>Beast,</hi> by suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings in his Members, being so pleased to <hi>enter into the Glory,</hi> of becomming by the profession of him, and his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, the <hi>Prince of the Empire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But it opened a large Avenue to the <hi>Beasts Kingdom,</hi> see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in nothing had it a greater advantage, then it took from the <hi>Martyrs</hi> Sufferings: This was the Foundation of his Idolatrous and Bloody Sovereignty: The Honour of <hi>Martyrs,</hi> their <hi>Temples, Memories</hi> and <hi>Festivals:</hi> Hence sprung their <hi>Altars,</hi> the <hi>eating the Sacrifices of the dead,</hi>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:54329:27"/>and <hi>Things sacrificed to Idols,</hi> in the first appearance of the <hi>Beast</hi> like himself.</p>
            <p>It is therefore said to the <hi>Souls under the Altar, they should rest,</hi> till their number was <hi>silled up by their Brethren,</hi> and <hi>fellow Servants,</hi> that should in the <hi>Beast Reign</hi> be <hi>killed,</hi> as they were for <hi>flying from Idolatry.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here is therefore at the opening of this <hi>Seal</hi> no voice of the <hi>Apostolick Ministry,</hi> saying, <hi>Come and see,</hi> though other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise so glorious to Christianity.</p>
            <p>The <hi>sixth Seal,</hi> and its Time, is given to the <hi>Typical Day of Judgment</hi> upon <hi>Heathenism,</hi> its <hi>Gods, Temples, Princes,</hi> and <hi>People, great</hi> and <hi>small.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus it <hi>became the Son of God,</hi> (his Church yet so far pure) to <hi>Judge</hi> this <hi>World</hi> and the <hi>Prince</hi> of it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Jesus Christ</hi> proclaimed thus in the <hi>Empire, King of Kings,</hi> &amp; <hi>Lord of Lords,</hi> was the <hi>manly Birth, caught</hi> up to the <hi>Throne of God,</hi> from which he could never be since brought down: The attempt of <hi>Julian</hi> being both short liv'd and feeble.</p>
            <p>Now was the <hi>Dragon cast down to the Earth,</hi> and the <hi>Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuser</hi> of Christianity, as the disturbance of the World, and Government, <hi>thrown out of Heaven,</hi> or the Imperial Throne.</p>
            <p>There was a <hi>Voice in Heaven loudly saying, now is come Salvation,
<note place="margin">Apoc. 12.10.</note> &amp;c.</hi> but the Church is so far declined, that the four <hi>living Creatures</hi> and the 24 <hi>Elders</hi> appear not.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Smyrna</hi> now receives a <hi>Transitory,</hi> and <hi>emblematical Crown of Life,</hi> but no more for 82 years.</p>
            <p>For as this <hi>Seal</hi> forepriz'd from the <hi>Beast</hi> this due Glory to Christ; so it opened a Gate to his comming by the <hi>Abundance of the Gentiles uncircumcised in Heart and Flesh,</hi> and their <hi>Heathen Rites,</hi> laying the <hi>Carcases</hi> of those they esteemed <hi>Heroes</hi> in the <hi>High places,</hi> as they after did the <hi>Martyrs,</hi> crowding into the <hi>Courts of God,</hi> as will be seen un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the next <hi>Seal.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Servants of God</hi> are therefore <hi>sealed in the</hi> very be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of Danger (for the Veils sake) as by the <hi>Trumpets,</hi> but indeed from that of the <hi>Beasts</hi> concurrence with them;
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:54329:27"/>
               <hi>sealed</hi> to <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>od, that is, secured, but <hi>concealed,</hi> and <hi>hidden</hi> from the World; who would not believe them the Servants of God, being <hi>Witnesses in Sack-Cloth, to be slain by the Beast,</hi> and to make up the number of the <hi>innumerable Companies of Palm-hearers,</hi> with other Prophets, Apostles, Martyrs, and Consessors at <hi>the New Jerusalem,</hi> crowned indeed with <hi>Smyrna's Crown of Life,</hi> that sadeth not away, at the Vision whereof the 4 <hi>Beasts</hi> and 24 <hi>Elders</hi> appear as <hi>Auditors of the Tryumphal Song;</hi> and congratulate with it.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Woman</hi> at the same time in <hi>plain</hi> prospect is <hi>flying</hi> into the <hi>Wilderness.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The last <hi>Seal,</hi> and its space, is reserved for the rallying of <hi>Heathenism,</hi> and its Force, that it may be finally destroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by <hi>Theodosius the Great,</hi> in the overthrow of <hi>Eugenius</hi> and <hi>Argobastes,</hi> and the Paganish Force under them.</p>
            <p>This, the Church continuing in Gods gracious Accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance the yet <hi>pure Church of Smyrna,</hi> though with a <hi>Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagogue of Sathan</hi> over-louring it, was obtained by the <hi>Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of Saints,</hi> and of <hi>Theodorus</hi> in the midst of the Battel, mingled with <hi>much Incense,</hi> to shew the Divine Accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and in <hi>the Smoke of which they ascended before</hi> God, and had most merciful Audience of him.</p>
            <p>The People at this time were waiting with <hi>Silence</hi> in the <hi>outer Court,</hi> at the time of <hi>Incense,</hi> according to custom, as appears, <hi>Luc.</hi> 1.10. This shews the <hi>outer Court within Measure</hi> yet not <hi>trodden under Foot by the Gentiles,</hi> but pure.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Coals from the Altar</hi> thrown upon the Earth, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouced <hi>Voyces, Thunderings, Lightnings,</hi> and <hi>Earthquakes,</hi> the constant signification of the Gospels prevalency in this Book, as now the second Time over <hi>Heathenism.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This pertain'd at least, (if not the principal) to <hi>that War in Heaven</hi> when <hi>Michael,</hi> and his <hi>Angels,</hi> and the <hi>Dragon</hi> and his <hi>Angels fought,</hi> but <hi>prevailed not, nor was their Place found any more in Heaven</hi> after this Time; here therefore the <hi>Doxology</hi> was compleated.</p>
            <p>This Time was also most justly due to the Lord of all.</p>
            <pb n="48" facs="tcp:54329:28"/>
            <p> But now were all the <hi>Seals opened,</hi> that em<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>rred the <hi>Beasts Kingdom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Angels</hi> had therefore in the beginning of this <hi>Seal</hi> the <hi>Trumpets</hi> given them, at the sound of which <hi>the Beast</hi> was to be <hi>born King</hi> of the <hi>Antichristian Kingdom:</hi> this was the first step.</p>
            <p>Then they <hi>prepared themselves to sound</hi> a second step; but they did not actually <hi>sound</hi> till 43 years from this <hi>Seal</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning.</p>
            <p>The great service the opening this <hi>Seal,</hi> and the ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of it all along, performed to the Beasts Kingdom, was;</p>
            <p n="1">1. That the Emperours from the Time, they became Christian, were a disguise to the <hi>Beasts receiving</hi> the <hi>Seat, Authority,</hi> and <hi>Power</hi> of the <hi>Dragon,</hi> which had it been open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly observed and understood, must have been affrightful to Christians, and so have hindered the rising of it.</p>
            <p>The Donation of his Power from the Christian Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours was the plausible cover of this; first exalting him to an <hi>Arch-Bishop,</hi> then to a <hi>Patriark,</hi> then to an <hi>Ʋniversal Bishop,</hi> and <hi>Head</hi> of the whole Church, while indeed his true Power was derived to him another way, as will be seen in the third particular.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The comming in of the Amplitude of the Empire to the Profession of Christianity, was necessary to the Gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dieur and Splendor of his after Sovereignty.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Which was the most essential, the Christian <hi>Earthly Church,</hi> which was now becoming the greatest part, and was sunk deep into the Veneration of <hi>Saints</hi> and <hi>Martyrs,</hi> were prepared on one side; and the new Imperial Converts com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing reeking out of the Temples and Idolatrous Worship of the Heathens, were on the other side fit to receive the new Form of their old Idolatry, as it was now prepared by this <hi>Pseudo Christianity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus the <hi>Dragon</hi> being wholly disinteressed, (that is, the Rule of <hi>Sathan</hi> in Heathen Idolatry being at an end)
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:54329:28"/>the Serpent by this Juggle and Cheat upon the World gives his <hi>Throne, Power,</hi> and <hi>great Authority</hi> to the <hi>Beast.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And in this manner the <hi>Dragon</hi> and the <hi>Beast</hi> are <hi>wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shipped</hi> together; <hi>The Dragon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Apoc. 13.4.</note> that gave his <hi>Authority</hi> to the <hi>Beast.</hi> The <hi>Beast,</hi> that <hi>received</hi> it, and became so great by it; that <hi>they said; who is like the Beast,</hi> that hath so compounded Pagan and Christian Idolatry together, as to please both parts? <hi>Who then can make War with him,</hi> or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sist him, that is thus strengthened with this double Idolatrous Interest?</p>
            <p>Thus the <hi>Head</hi> of the <hi>Dragon,</hi> that <hi>had the wound</hi> first by <hi>Constantine's,</hi> then by <hi>Theodosius his Sword; was healed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus by the end of the space of this <hi>Seal,</hi> the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of the yet <hi>Youngling Beast</hi> was prepared.</p>
            <p>Just about the end of it, the <hi>Woman</hi> was speeded into the <hi>Wilderness</hi> by the two,
<note place="margin">Apoc. 12.14.</note> the Eastern and Western Wings of the great Imperial <hi>Eagle,</hi> grown both so foulely Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous, that the <hi>true Church</hi> was out of slight.</p>
            <p>At the same time, the <hi>Dragon cast the Flood</hi> of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganish <hi>Barbarians,</hi> as it were <hi>out of his Mouth,</hi> to have swallowed up the <hi>true Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But the <hi>earthly Church,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Apoc. 12.15.</note> only at this time visible in the outward Pomps of Religion, and the Splendor of this World, was forced to receive the <hi>Flood,</hi> for such a State suffers most by such Inundations.</p>
            <p>Yet it was not long, ere it <hi>drunk up the Flood</hi> by <hi>prose<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyting those Barbarians</hi> to its <hi>Pseudo Christianity,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Apoc. 17.12, 13.</note> when the <hi>ten Kings</hi> gave their <hi>Strength,</hi> and <hi>Power,</hi> and <hi>Kingdom</hi> to the <hi>Beast</hi> with <hi>one Consent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus we are come to the <hi>Beasts</hi> 42 <hi>Months,</hi> all alike under the Governess of the Night; common to him with the <hi>Gentiles</hi> and their Idolatry defiling the <hi>outward Court,</hi> and <hi>treading the Holy City under Feet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To the <hi>Witnesses</hi> in <hi>Sack-cloth,</hi> and the <hi>Woman in the Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derness,</hi> their 1260 dayes are alike too, under the Gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of the Light, and the Day; as also the <hi>Witnesses three
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:54329:29"/>Dayes</hi> and <hi>a Half,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Apoc. 11.2.3. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> for their continual succession, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief one of another; these slain, others rising; as if none had had their turn longer, then <hi>three Dayes and a Half.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And at the same time we are come to the <hi>Beasts Time, Times,</hi> and <hi>Half a Time,</hi> that is to the Distinctions obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vable in his 42 <hi>Months.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And to the <hi>Woman in the Wilderness, Her Time, Times,</hi> and <hi>Half a Time,</hi> connoting the Distinctions in her 1260 <hi>Dayes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By which Computation of her <hi>Time, Times, Half a Time,</hi> we know they are interlocked with the same of the <hi>Beast,</hi> and that it is the <hi>Beast,</hi> that persecutes the <hi>Woman</hi> by Depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation from the <hi>Dragon,</hi> and not the <hi>Dragon,</hi> but at the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry first by this <hi>Deputation,</hi> that is, the <hi>Serpent</hi> or <hi>Sathan</hi> not in the Heathenish, but Christian-Idolatrous <hi>Power</hi> into which the Heathenish was translated.</p>
            <p>And by the Compellation of her 1260 <hi>Dayes,</hi> we know they are interlocked with the Witnesses 1260 <hi>Dayes,</hi> and that the <hi>Woman</hi> and the <hi>Witnesses</hi> her <hi>Seed,</hi> that keep the <hi>commands of God,</hi> and have the <hi>Testimony of Jesus,</hi> are vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually the same; for while she under the Notion of a <hi>Church,</hi> is hid from the <hi>Serpent</hi> in the <hi>Wilderness,</hi> both concealed and secured, she is yet visible, and <hi>to be found in her Seed.</hi> So that the <hi>Dragon,</hi> that <hi>makes War with</hi> her <hi>Seed,</hi> does it by the <hi>Beast,</hi> that made <hi>War with</hi> the <hi>Witnesses,</hi> as before explained.</p>
            <p>And thus we are ascertained both in History, and Time.</p>
            <p>And that we have no mention of years, is both to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port with the Secresy of the Prophecy, and to avoid any controversy concerning years, General and Solar be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing only to be understood.</p>
            <p>We are then come to the <hi>first Time of the Beast,</hi> under the Distinction of a <hi>Time.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And from the first moment of it,
<note place="margin">Apoc. 17.10, 11.</note>
               <hi>the daily Sacrifice</hi> is to be dated, taken away: so that here begins <hi>Daniels</hi> 1335
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:54329:29"/>
               <hi>Dayes,</hi> in the 405th year after the <hi>Resurrection,</hi> the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of it; the 438 of vulgar account.</p>
            <p>And from the very first moment, he is in sacred Chro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicle the <hi>eighth King,</hi> and the seventh <hi>Head,</hi> whose Name or Title is, <hi>was, is not, yet is,</hi> for he was not in the Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Emperours but is in the <hi>Popish,</hi> and yet not the same, but an Image only of that Idolatrous Power, being Paga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no Christian, as Dr. <hi>Moore</hi> fully hath declared; for the seventh <hi>King</hi> is another, even the Christian Emperours; who were not come at the <hi>Epoch</hi> of the <hi>Revelation,</hi> but when they <hi>came,</hi> were but to continue a <hi>short Space,</hi> and so we find.</p>
            <p>This <hi>Idolatrous Head</hi> therefore, though in order the <hi>eighth King,</hi> is of the <hi>seven Heads</hi> of <hi>Blasphemy.</hi> And in <hi>Daniel</hi> is esteemed <hi>one King,</hi> and indeed principally intended, by that <hi>one King; that does according to his Will,</hi> and <hi>speaks marvellous things against the God of Gods.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Even as he is the <hi>Little Horn,</hi> that had <hi>Eyes</hi> as <hi>the Eyes of a Man,</hi> and a <hi>Mouth speaking great things,</hi> and he <hi>opens his Mouth</hi> in <hi>Blasphemy against the God of Heaven.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Just thus he is described in the <hi>Revelation</hi> by his <hi>Eyes</hi> as a <hi>Prophet</hi> or <hi>Seer,</hi> for so the <hi>two horns</hi> of a <hi>Lamb,</hi> intitle him: by his <hi>Mouth speaking great things</hi> and <hi>Blasphemyes, by opening his Mouth in Blasphemies against God,</hi> and his <hi>Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle,</hi> and them <hi>that dwell therein:</hi> even <hi>Idolatrous Blas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemies.</hi> By <hi>wearing out the Saints,</hi> and <hi>warring against them:</hi> and continuing <hi>Time, Times,</hi> and <hi>half a Time,</hi> or 42 <hi>Months;</hi> so he <hi>spake</hi> and did as a <hi>Dragon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And as an <hi>eighth King,</hi> he is described by the <hi>Feet</hi> and <hi>Toes of Clay,</hi> that fignifie a Kingdom, not strong, or war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, even as the <hi>Horns of a Lamb,</hi> an unwarlike Creature import him.</p>
            <p>An Idolatrous Power, that is but an <hi>Image</hi> of a <hi>Power,</hi> but as it is inhabited, acted by a <hi>False Prophet,</hi> as the <hi>Dae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon of it,</hi> who by <hi>Lying Wonders</hi> after the Efficacies of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than</hi> procurates the Power to it: Honouring a <hi>God his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:54329:30"/>knew not: viz.</hi> Our Lord, unknown to Heathen Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours, honouring <hi>Saints and Angels</hi> as the great <hi>Tutelars,</hi> or Defenders, bringing in the Doctrine of <hi>Daemons,</hi> not <hi>regard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the love of Women, forbidding to marry.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All these are his lively Characters.</p>
            <p>But no Description so definitive, as that which sets him out, making an <hi>Image to speak,</hi> and to cause, <hi>that all that will not worship the Image, should be killed;</hi> And <hi>that none shall buy or sell,</hi> that will not <hi>receive a mark suitable to</hi> that Idolatrous Negotiation, and then giving a Character of the Time, wherein he should arrive to, and obtain this pitch; and <hi>that is the number</hi> 666, is so assuring that nothing can excell it.</p>
            <p>For beginning at the <hi>Epoch</hi> of the <hi>Apocal.</hi> so often said to be our <hi>Lords Resurrection,</hi> and so descending to the year 666 from it, it carryes us upon the year 700 or very near it; and being easily convey'd from thence to the Famous History of the <hi>Iconoclastick Emperours,</hi> beginning in <hi>Leo Conon Isaurus,</hi> and the Excommunication of him for deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Worship of Images; and so on in his Successors, we have such a fulfilling of that latter part of <hi>Apoc.</hi> 13. that none that compare it can but say, certainly <hi>it was then ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled,</hi> and was rather a <hi>History</hi> then a <hi>Prophecy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Again,
<note place="margin">An. D. 72.</note> let us measure from that year in which that so fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous History began the vulgar, <hi>Anno Dom,</hi> 725, 666 back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, and we may be sure then the Conception of the <hi>Beast</hi> was about 26 years from the <hi>Resurrection,</hi> then the <hi>Mystery of Iniquity begun to Work,</hi> then was the Departure from the <hi>Apostolick</hi> 12 rising to an opposite number, to the 144, according to Mr. <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>otters</hi> most ingenious Discourse; so that both by the Time, and its History, and the Intimate Sense of that <hi>number,</hi> a Deviation from the <hi>true Apostolism</hi> and pure <hi>Israelitism,</hi> we are most certain who this <hi>Beast</hi> is, what is his <hi>Bestianism,</hi> when he was grown up from his Conception; from his Birth also by consequence, to be <hi>that Beast;</hi> His <hi>first Time</hi> then was exhausted in the utter de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>basement
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:54329:30"/>to the very Ground of <hi>Imperial Rome,</hi> in the <hi>se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth King;</hi> that this <hi>eighth King,</hi> and <hi>seventh Head</hi> might rise, and grow up to the height of a <hi>King,</hi> as he did, in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posing <hi>Childerick,</hi> and exalting <hi>Pipin</hi> to be King of <hi>France;</hi> and to the strength of an <hi>Idolatrous Beast,</hi> as he did in the Excommunication of <hi>Leo Conon,</hi> and his Son <hi>Constant. <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>opronymus,</hi> and all this within his <hi>first Time.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now were the <hi>Witnesses in Sack-cloth, the Woman in the Wilderness;</hi> The <hi>Synagogue of Sathan</hi> was become a <hi>Throne of Sathan,</hi> and so overtopped <hi>Pergamus,</hi> as it signifies the <hi>true Church,</hi> that there was nothing to be seen, but that <hi>lofty Idolatrous Pergamus</hi> or <hi>Rome;</hi> only to God, who saw the <hi>true Church</hi> under that Name, and most evidently pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounces the Censure and Doom upon the <hi>false Church, guilty</hi> of Balamitism, and Nicolaitanism by the <hi>true Church,</hi> carrying its name, which, who ever considers, will find a most plain Church History;</p>
            <p>The <hi>two Times</hi> are much alike throughout, for though towards the end of the <hi>third Time,</hi> before the <hi>Half Time,</hi> there were some risings of the Church of <hi>Thyatira</hi> in <hi>Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>life, John Huss, Jerome</hi> of <hi>Prague,</hi> the <hi>Bohemians,</hi> Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runners, yet they made no visible Change.</p>
            <p>The <hi>eighth King</hi> then, in these <hi>two Times</hi> raises the gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deur of <hi>Rome,</hi> by creating <hi>Charles the Great, August Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour,</hi> although he, and his Successors in the Name, are but one of the <hi>ten Kings</hi> in sacred Style.</p>
            <p>And above these he exalts himself, as above <hi>every God</hi> in <hi>Daniel,</hi> and above <hi>all that is called God</hi> in the Apostles Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage: as was most evident in the History of the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours in the tenth and eleventh Centuries.</p>
            <p>He proceeds in his Idolatry, as is manifest by the <hi>Icono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clastick</hi> History, continuing on the first of the <hi>two Times,</hi> till the opposites of the Idolatry, first by <hi>conciliary</hi> Power, and after by the <hi>Imperial Power,</hi> were quite overcome, that they never had any of the Freedom of Life, that did not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the <hi>Mark</hi> or <hi>Name, or number</hi> of the <hi>Name,</hi> that Counter-Apostolick
<gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:54329:31"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:54329:31"/>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:54329:32"/>Apostolick Doctrine, that so signaliz'd the Year 666, from the working of the Mystery of <hi>Iniquity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Witnesses</hi> are all these <hi>two Times</hi> in a continual Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cession, under the <hi>War, Victory,</hi> and <hi>Slaughter of the Beast;</hi> Their Testimony being had in Detestation, and anathema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiz'd as Heresie. But their word's of so great Account with God, that they bring down <hi>Fire from Heaven, and smite the Earth with Plagues,</hi> the Indignation of God being just<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly kindled at so great an abuse of his Truth in their mouths; and they shut <hi>Heaven, that it rains not;</hi> There is no Dew of Heavenly Doctrine, but what came down in their Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nistry; an eminent Character of that Time, so notorious for Barbarity and Ignorance in all true knowledge, but especially Sacred. <hi>Pergamus</hi> and <hi>Thyatyra,</hi> from whence these two <hi>Witnesses</hi> rise, are the two <hi>Candlesticks standing suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessively before the God of the whole Earth,</hi> the only Churches. Besides the invalidating their Testimony, they are in plain sense destroy'd, and slain by the <hi>Beasts</hi> Cruelty, in the col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lective name of <hi>Antipas;</hi> not only in single Persons, but whole Companies; the <hi>Waldenses</hi> and <hi>Albingenses.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Balaam,</hi> agreeable to the <hi>Beast</hi> with two <hi>Horns, as a Lamb,</hi> brings in the <hi>Fornication</hi> of committing Idolatry with Saints, and their Images, by the degrees of keeping <hi>Festival dayes</hi> in remembrance of them, which were made the <hi>Snare.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Doctrine of <hi>Indulgences,</hi> and freedoms to sin, veil'd under this <hi>Nicolaitanism</hi> of the first Times, succeeded in its season, and was annex'd to the fore-going Idolatry, as the great Encouragement to it. Publick Worship was so pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luted, that the true Church retires to <hi>Hidden Manna, wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derness fare,</hi> the Service of God, and Celebration of the Lord's Supper in secret; which e're the end of the first of the Two Times was most infamously defiled with the Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry of the <hi>Mass.</hi> The <hi>Oracles</hi> of God, or the <hi>Ʋrim</hi> and <hi>Thummim</hi> of Scripture, and the gracious Absolutions and Consolations of the Gospel, were as <hi>a white stone,</hi> with a
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:54329:32"/>
               <hi>new Name written in it, that none knew,</hi> but <hi>they who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd it,</hi> Scriptures being hidden from almost all by one means or other. The Servants of God serv'd him within the <hi>measur'd Temple,</hi> and at the <hi>Altar,</hi> by their <hi>Doctrine, worship, Prayers,</hi> and <hi>sufferings.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yet the True Church carries the Charge of having them that hold the Doctrine of <hi>Balaam</hi> and the <hi>Nicolaitans,</hi> and the names of <hi>Pergamus</hi> and <hi>Thyatyra</hi> as the true Church,
<note place="margin">Hose. 1.</note> the Prophets Visional Children, for Idolatrous <hi>Israel</hi>'s sake, did of <hi>Lo Ruhamah</hi> and <hi>Lo Ammi.</hi> The <hi>True Church</hi> did indeed disown All, but because of its being so deeply hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den under the False Church, it supports the Doom but so, that it is made to slide off it. For those great and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicated Evils of <hi>Balaam's</hi> Doctrine, and the <hi>Nicolaitans,</hi> are but a <hi>Few,</hi> and <hi>small things,</hi> as against the <hi>true Church,</hi> that abhorr'd them all, though most prodigious in the <hi>Apostatick Church,</hi> the Censure therefore does not make so deep a Dint as on <hi>Ephesus,</hi> when Christ sayes to that, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>I have against thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And while it is to convey the command of Repentance to that <hi>Apostolick Church,</hi> yet the threatning slips off from the <hi>true Church, I will fight not against thee,</hi> but <hi>them, with the Sword of my Mouth,</hi> even as <hi>Antipas</hi> was slain, not by you, but <hi>among you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is no Promise made to them recorded in the state of the <hi>New Jerusalem,</hi> as to all the other <hi>six Churches,</hi> to shew in a Type how low this Church was from all sight of Redemption.</p>
            <p>And all these things considered, as they stand in the <hi>Epistle</hi> to the <hi>Church of Pergamus,</hi> and duely laid together, amount to a very considerable <hi>Church-History</hi> of that Time.</p>
            <p>Concurrent with this Time according to <hi>Daniel,</hi> toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with <hi>Christ Jesus,</hi> the <hi>God strange</hi> to the <hi>Roman Empire,</hi> the <hi>Beast honours,</hi> as so many <hi>Fortresses</hi> of Cityes, and Countryes, the presidentiary Saints and Angels, to whom the <hi>Land is divided for gain;</hi> being constituted over <hi>several
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:54329:33"/>quarters</hi> to receive Devotions and Offerings, with which, what can be more agreeable, then the practise of these <hi>two Times.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But is the most high asleep at this Season, and did he forsake the Christian World?</p>
            <p>No, the two first <hi>woe Trumpets sound,</hi> thence argued to <hi>sound against the Beast,</hi> because they are of a kind with the <hi>third woe Trumpet;</hi> which, we are sure, sounded his Destructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; God alarmed the World with these.</p>
            <p>For against the time, the <hi>Beast</hi> would be a grown <hi>Beast,</hi> the <hi>Mahometan</hi> Superstition glorying in the Worship of one God, without Images; (in all things else portentously senseless) rises to be a scoff upon <hi>Pseudo Christianity,</hi> and a scourge to it.</p>
            <p>First, in the <hi>Saracens,</hi> the <hi>King of the South pushing at the Beast;</hi> then in the <hi>Turks,</hi> that <hi>King of the North, coming</hi> with <hi>Chariots</hi> and <hi>Horses</hi> as a <hi>Whirl-wind</hi> against him: and so Victorious, that few escaped him, particularly <hi>Jerusa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,</hi> and its Countryes were swallowed up by him.</p>
            <p>Each of which, with their poysonous <hi>Syrma</hi> of false Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, have such accurate, and yet more florid Descrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, <hi>Apoc.</hi> 9. that I shall only leave the Ingenious Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to observe them.</p>
            <p>The first are warned <hi>to hurt none,</hi> but those that had not the <hi>Seal of God in their Fore-heads,</hi> to shew, they are rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed up against the Idolatrous Church.</p>
            <p>The Second are noted to come at the Voice from the <hi>four Horns of the golden Altar,</hi> the Servants of <hi>Jesus</hi> perse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted by the <hi>Beast,</hi> as the Christians were before by the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, who therefore gathered to the <hi>Altar of Incense</hi> by their Prayers, and cryed aloud for Vengeance, and in this, as one instance, is the <hi>fire proceeding out of their Mouths,</hi> and the smiting <hi>the Earth with Plagues.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The end, or towards the end of this Time, is remarqued with the Ruine of the <hi>Graecian</hi> Empire, and <hi>Constantinople,</hi> the Imperial City, becomming the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Port.</p>
            <pb n="57" facs="tcp:54329:33"/>
            <p> And after it to the end of the <hi>two Times</hi> waits the divine Observation, and Expectation of the Repentance of the <hi>Apostatick Church,</hi> and Idolatrous <hi>Western Empire,</hi> and they repented not. <hi>The Wicked will do wickedly,</hi> and <hi>will not understand.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The last Scene of the <hi>Bestian Time,</hi> is his <hi>Half Time:</hi> of which I have already given so full an Account, the less is now necessary.</p>
            <p>The first rising of the <hi>Witnesses</hi> in <hi>Luther,</hi> and those that followed him, is so exact on the very Morning of the <hi>Half Time,</hi> 1517, as it were on purpose, to justi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie the Account of Time hitherto.</p>
            <p>There are great Commotions hereupon in the <hi>Bestian Kingdom,</hi> a considerable part like the <hi>tenth part of the City falls,</hi> as it were in an <hi>Earthquake,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Apoc. 11.13.</note> and something like the <hi>Voices,</hi> and the <hi>pouring</hi> out of the Vials ensues, but not as they shall be at the end.</p>
            <p>And this, as I said before, arose from the <hi>Roaring of the Lyon,</hi> and the seven <hi>Thunders,</hi> but on the sudden, the cry of the <hi>Lion</hi> ceased, and the <hi>Thunders</hi> were <hi>sealed up.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Book was open</hi> a while in the <hi>Hand of the Angel,</hi> but it was presently <hi>eaten,</hi> and hid as it were in the <hi>Bowels</hi> of some few Interpreters, who might have a present pleasure in the Interpretation, <hi>sweet to the Taste,</hi> but it was <hi>bitter within them,</hi> both for the Difficulties, wherein the Interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation was intangled, and the very unkind Acceptance, their Interpretations met with from others. <hi>Daniels Cogi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations troubled him,</hi> and <hi>he told the Vision to no man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And the only <hi>Vision</hi> given before the seventh <hi>Trumpets sound,</hi> is of the <hi>Temple,</hi> and <hi>Altar measured,</hi> and the <hi>outer Court left out,</hi> and <hi>the Witnesses slain,</hi> that is, especially their Testimony discredited, and anathematiz'd as <hi>false Testimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, Heresie,</hi> and <hi>Blasphemy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And this is therefore given before the seventh <hi>Trumpet,</hi> because the <hi>Apostasy</hi> of the Christian Church, and the truth of God, with those that testified against that <hi>Apostasy,</hi> their
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:54329:34"/>just Cause, as of the Servants of God, and their Sufferings in that Cause, as <hi>Martyrs,</hi> hath been, and must needs be generally believed in the <hi>reformed Churches,</hi> to justify their Separation from <hi>Rome,</hi> and yet, even that will not be fully understood, nor believed in the great Circumstances of it, till the end of this <hi>half Time,</hi> and the last rising of the <hi>Witnesses;</hi> which will be as certainly at the end of this <hi>half Day,</hi> and near the year 1697, as <hi>Luther,</hi> and the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation</hi> consequent was at the beginning, or morning of this Time, or at the year 1517.</p>
            <p>So that <hi>this</hi> is no wonder, the <hi>Beast</hi> yet survives a <hi>Beast,</hi> though in a retrench'd Dominion: that he shewed himself after this, so potent a <hi>Beast</hi> in the <hi>Councel of Trent,</hi> that he hath still so much to do in the World, for his Kingdom is granted to him, till the last of the 42 Months, of which yet remain thirteen prophetical Dayes, or Years, his last <hi>Month</hi> being spent to that small remainder.</p>
            <p>Nor is it any wonder, that the <hi>Turks</hi> Tyranny, or <hi>the second woe</hi> continues, for being the Vengeance of God since its rising upon the <hi>Bestian Idolatry,</hi> it shall run paralel with him to the very last of his Time, and thereupon to pray for the Ruin of the <hi>Turk,</hi> is in true <hi>Apocalyptick</hi> Sense, to pray for the Expiration of the <hi>Papal Reign</hi> first.</p>
            <p>That which is the yet grander Concernment of this <hi>half Time,</hi> is the Prophetick Church-History of those three, <hi>Thyatira, Sardis,</hi> and <hi>Philadelphia,</hi> which I shall as briefly as I can, give in their several particular Characters, just named; without taking upon me to assign them to any particular Churches of <hi>Protestants,</hi> or to so much, as mean any, but as the very sacred Prophecy will by express Words lead necessarily the considering Mans Thoughts.</p>
            <p>But that I may lead to the Mark I design, more exactly, I must premise these two things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. As to the Character of the Times of these six Churches, the <hi>three first</hi> run out their just Intervals, and then cease from being any longer Prophetick Types.</p>
            <pb n="59" facs="tcp:54329:34"/>
            <p> The <hi>three last</hi> run their Course together to the <hi>New Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rusalem; Thyatira</hi> by some noted Periods and Intervals; the two other evenly.</p>
            <p>This appears by the Promises made to the <hi>three first,</hi> postpon'd to that general Alarm, <hi>He that hath Ears, let him hear,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>The three last</hi> have the same presixed to the Promises, by which variation so obvious, we are moved to Inquiry, and this upon Observation offers it self.</p>
            <p>The <hi>three first</hi> have their Promises so general, that they do not imply a Conjunction betwixt their Time, and the <hi>New Jerusalem.</hi> The <hi>three last</hi> have in those Promises such Clauses as do necessarily suppose their Contact, if I may so speak, with that <hi>Jerusalem,</hi> besides other congenial Times of it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. As to the Inoffensiveness of this <hi>Church-History</hi> to Christian Minds, that have a Reverence for the Church, especially Primitive.</p>
            <p>It may seem strange, that <hi>Ephesus,</hi> a Type of the <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stolick Church</hi> should be so severely censured, as to <hi>leave its first Love,</hi> and <hi>Smyrna</hi> be prefered before it.</p>
            <p>And that <hi>Sardis,</hi> a <hi>reformed Church</hi> should be so sharply reproved, and more severely treated, then <hi>Pergamus,</hi> or <hi>Thyatira,</hi> as they connoted <hi>the True Church;</hi> and <hi>Phila<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delphia,</hi> a much Inferiour Church in Appearance be so far honoured before it.</p>
            <p>But to this we are to return in satisfaction. <hi>He that walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in the Midst of the golden Candelsticks,</hi> hath declared himself, in <hi>Thyatira,</hi> as in the midst of <hi>the Churches,</hi> and a Rule for them all; that he would have <hi>all the Churches, the seven Churches to know,</hi> that <hi>he searches the Hearts,</hi> and tryes <hi>the Reins,</hi> and <hi>gives to every one according to their Works.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He saw therefore in <hi>Ephesus,</hi> in its declining Time, such Propensions to the after Corruptions, at that time under Innocent appearances, and so little Regret to them, as that they <hi>leavened the whole Lump.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="60" facs="tcp:54329:35"/>
            <p> In <hi>Smyrna</hi> he observed, though the <hi>Corruptions</hi> had eaten wider, and deeper, yet such a Separation from them, as that he honours the good among them till the very rising of the <hi>Beast,</hi> as a <hi>pure Church,</hi> and the bad he condemns, as a <hi>Synagogue of Sathan,</hi> and so <hi>Pergamus</hi> and <hi>Thyatira,</hi> that were covered, one all over, the other surrounded with <hi>Sathans Seat,</hi> and Kingdom, are more acceptable then <hi>Sar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dis,</hi> that let the Principles of Reformation languish so much, as to have <hi>defiled Garments,</hi> although not the gross Impurities, the <hi>false Church</hi> so overgrew <hi>Pergamus</hi> and <hi>Thyatira</hi> with; because these two Churches were more perfect with God in the true Reasons of <hi>Reformation,</hi> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifested by their Renunciation of the other Impurities, even to <hi>Martyrdom,</hi> though with less light then <hi>Sardis; For the Lord seeth not as men seeth; For Man looketh on the outward appearance, But the Lord seeth the Heart.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This premis'd, I begin with <hi>Thyatyra.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Title of Christ is, <hi>He that hath his Eyes like a flame of fire;</hi> shewing his sharp and piercing insight into all the gloz'd Corruptions of the <hi>false Church,</hi> and his <hi>Feet as fine Brass,</hi> as if they <hi>burnt in a Furnace,</hi> as is added, <hi>Apoc.</hi> 10.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Synchronous</hi> with this, He purified his <hi>Servants, even in the Flames; many shall be purified and made white,</hi> while the wicked do wickedly, and <hi>will not understand,</hi> but <hi>the wise shall understand:</hi> Thus our Lord's Titles are agreeable to the Time. In <hi>Ephesus,</hi> as proper to the first Apostolick Church, he holds the seven Stars <hi>in his right hand,</hi> and <hi>walks in the midst of the golden Candlesticks.</hi> In <hi>Symrna,</hi> first dying, and then receiving, <hi>a Crown of Life,</hi> He is <hi>He that was dead,</hi> and is alive; In <hi>Pergamus,</hi> he hath the <hi>sharp Sword with two Edges,</hi> setting out the Power of his Word against the <hi>Man of Sin,</hi> till he is consum'd and cut off by it.</p>
            <p>The Name <hi>Thyatyra</hi> is sitted to <hi>Jezebel,</hi> and the Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man describ'd <hi>Apoc.</hi> 17.</p>
            <pb n="61" facs="tcp:54329:35"/>
            <p> There is mention of many Graces of this Church, each proper to its Time, Faith, Charity, Service, Patience, as Characters of Honour to it, without any blemish or allay.</p>
            <p>The <hi>last works are more than the first,</hi> for the <hi>second Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing of the witnesses</hi> in this Church, will be greater and more perfect than the first; and so at the very last; This Church will be serviceable to the Final Abolition of <hi>Babylon,</hi> in a very high degree.</p>
            <p>The <hi>suffering the woman Jezebel</hi> is only a prophetick Type, shewing in the <hi>True Church,</hi> as in a pure Mirror, the state and Deformity of the <hi>False;</hi> the Prophecy dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daining to have to do with it immediately in these Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles, as God calls the <hi>Jews</hi> the Prophet's People, and speaks to Idolatrous Israel by <hi>Hoseah</hi>'s Visional Children, so the Impotency of the True Church to suppress or reform the False, is charg'd as a <hi>Schematick Fault</hi> upon it, to set out the obstinacy, impenitency, and Insolency of that <hi>Imperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, whorish Woman.</hi> Else to <hi>suffer Jezebel</hi> had not been <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>small things,</hi> but of heinous guilt.</p>
            <p>The Woman <hi>Jezebel</hi> signifies the False Church, under that enchanting Name of the Woman of <hi>Rome,</hi> or the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Catholick</hi> Church, the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> distinguish'd from the <hi>Court</hi> or <hi>Beast</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> This is <hi>Babylon,</hi> the <hi>Mother</hi> of <hi>Harlots.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>She <hi>repented not</hi> in that especial space given her, after the loss of the <hi>Greek Empire,</hi> and desolation of that Church, which she had subjected under her self and her Idolatry, and so is reputed one with her.</p>
            <p>God therefore will cast her into a <hi>Bed</hi> of <hi>languishing,</hi> and <hi>Death, and kill her children with Death;</hi> by the <hi>Vials, except they repent;</hi> an intimation of a further space of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance under the <hi>Voices.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By this time the Idolatry of the <hi>Mass</hi> was grown the Paramount Idolatry, or <hi>height</hi> of Fornication; including that with Saints and Angels as a lower degree.</p>
            <pb n="62" facs="tcp:54329:36"/>
            <p> That was indeed the Highest in the first Times of <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gamus,</hi> modestly introduc'd by Christians, meeting at the places of Martyrs Interrments, to worship God, and cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brate the Lord's Supper: Thence it grew to building Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples carrying their Names, and their Images plac'd in them; setting apart dayes of their Commemoration, making those dayes Festivals, and all these as Memories of them: Daily by degrees, it came to Veneration, worshipping, Altars, Invocation, or the very <hi>Sacrifices</hi> of <hi>the Dead,</hi> and <hi>eating things sacrificed to Idols.</hi> All which are justly branded, <hi>Fornication,</hi> in a spiritual sense.</p>
            <p>But the <hi>Sacrifice</hi> of the <hi>Mass,</hi> falsly founded on so Divine an Institution, as the <hi>Remembrance of,</hi> or <hi>Feast upon our Lord's Sacrifice,</hi> was now become the Height of <hi>Fornica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;</hi> although nothing of the other is abated; and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bauch'd into <hi>Eating things sacrific'd to Idols,</hi> and the foulest Idolatry.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Nicolaitanism</hi> is not named, being so fiercely thundred against by the first Reformers, that however it continued the practise of <hi>Rome,</hi> yet it is not charg'd on <hi>Thyatyra,</hi> that so may arise a private Character of that Time.</p>
            <p>The <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or the <hi>(Rest)</hi> with the <hi>(You)</hi> in <hi>Thyatyra</hi> speaks the succession of this <hi>Church,</hi> to the precise Time of the <hi>Vials,</hi> when the last of it is call'd out of <hi>Babylon,</hi> as is after to be shewn.</p>
            <p>For so <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> are us'd, to signifie <hi>succession</hi> to the <hi>new Jerusalem,</hi> or very near it; as might be made good in many Instances, were it not too long.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Depths of Satan</hi> speak the <hi>Beasts Kingdom,</hi> grown old in all Policies, or <hi>Arcana Imperii,</hi> but <hi>Thyatyra</hi> disco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered them, and in common Language <hi>(or as they speak)</hi> call'd them <hi>Depths of Satan,</hi> as they were: for <hi>Sathan</hi> was the True Supreme, had his <hi>Throne, Dwelling, Synagogue</hi> in the <hi>Beasts Kingdom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To shew <hi>Thyatyra's suffering Jezebel</hi> was a fault only in a Prophetick Scheme, she had <hi>no Burden</hi> laid upon her, not
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:54329:36"/>so much, as to suffer <hi>Jezebel</hi> no longer; but only to <hi>hold fast,</hi> till <hi>Christs coming, viz.</hi> first at the beginning of the <hi>half Day,</hi> then at the end of it; and last of all in the <hi>pour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out of the Vials</hi> to their end, which is the <hi>breaking the Nations in shivers,</hi> and <hi>ruling over them:</hi> in all of which it hath, as being so much concerned, <hi>the Morning Star,</hi> or first dawns of the Lords Appearings.</p>
            <p>To conclude then, this Church consists of the Servants of God, either rising at any time by the Resurrection out of the false Church, even to every single Convert, till the <hi>Vials:</hi> when the last call out of <hi>Babylon; Come out of her my People;</hi> or when call'd out, still surrounded with Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and Powers devoted to the <hi>Bestian Kingdom;</hi> or em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed in a singular way in the execution of Divine Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments upon <hi>Babylon,</hi> as those last call'd out, especially seem to be, by being pressed to <hi>reward</hi> her, as she had them in their Predecessors.</p>
            <p>The two <hi>Churches</hi> of <hi>Sardis</hi> and <hi>Philadelphiae</hi> remain to be considered.</p>
            <p>They are certainly <hi>Churches reformed,</hi> though of a very different Elevation in the Reformation from all the Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions of <hi>Babylon,</hi> and preparation to the <hi>New Jerusa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem;</hi> to which two all things in this Book have a Refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, and so to be interpreted, as being the two ends of all <hi>Prophecy,</hi> and much more of this, as I have already said.</p>
            <p>But because they are <hi>Protestant Churches,</hi> I shall make not so much as the least Intimation of Allusion to any of them in the Exposition, to avoid all offence; but only of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer the very prophetick Characters themselves: <hi>Sardis</hi> hath the Precedency, whether in Time, or on other Accounts, I will not determine.</p>
            <p>Its Characters of Time are.</p>
            <p n="1">1. From the Lord's Titles, <hi>He hath the</hi> 7 <hi>Spirits of God,</hi> and <hi>the</hi> 7 <hi>Stars</hi> in allusion to <hi>Ephesus</hi> the first Church; but by way of Diminution, from true Apostolickness; It is not added; In his <hi>Right Hand.</hi> Yet signifiying the Church upon
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:54329:37"/>a new Epoch, as of Formation at the first in <hi>Ephesus,</hi> so of Reformation now.</p>
            <p>Which is also intimated in its being call'd to <hi>Remember,</hi> how it had <hi>receiv'd and hear'd,</hi> as an Admonition of its first, and Better Original. There is nothing of the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of <hi>Balaam, Jezebel,</hi> and their <hi>Fornication,</hi> nor of <hi>Nicolaitanism</hi> imputed to it, shewing its being come out of <hi>Babylon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And let not these Hints seem Fancies, for in <hi>Propheticks</hi> the shades of Concealment are broad, but the Lines of Discovery very small: the leaving out in <hi>Jeconiah,</hi> the <hi>Je;</hi> and calling him <hi>Coniah</hi> only, is observ'd by Interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, <hi>Jerem.</hi> 22.8.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Continuation of this Church is all along the <hi>Half Day,</hi> the Time in which the <hi>Bridegroom delaying his coming,</hi> it falls into a <hi>slumber,</hi> as is whisper'd to it in the Command to be <hi>watchful.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. The last term of its Continuance as <hi>such a Church,</hi> is very plainly, though after a Prophetical manner, made known by compare, with what Christ sayes at the <hi>sixth Vial, Apoc.</hi> 16. <hi>Behold, I come as a Thief, &amp;c.</hi> when he u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses in a manner all the very same words, as an Alarm to it, that were here given it so long before.</p>
            <p>The Characters of this Churches State.</p>
            <p n="1">1. It is in a state of <hi>Splendour,</hi> by its name, <hi>Sardis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. It hath a <hi>Name to live,</hi> that is, It is a Church Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd.</p>
            <p n="3">3. It lost it self (as <hi>Ephesus</hi>) though in a much shorter time) for <hi>it is dead.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. Our Lord is most abundant in most gracious Admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitions to it self; as shewing his great Love and esteem of it; and not to any other Church for it; while <hi>Pergamus</hi> and <hi>Thyatira</hi> bore all Christ had to say to the <hi>Apostatick Church.</hi> Thus, as to <hi>Laodicea, whom I love, I rebuke,</hi> &amp;c. and it is most hopeful, very many have been, and will be prevail'd upon by this Grace.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:54329:37"/> 5. It hath not that vigorous sense of the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the Preparations of it self to the <hi>new Jerusalem</hi> and its state, nor of the utmost pursuit of the Principles of Reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to <hi>make them perfect before God,</hi> and therefore it is called back to those very Principles, to grasp them closer, and <hi>repent</hi> according to them.</p>
            <p n="6">6. It is hardly perswaded to believe a Coming of Christ before the last Judgment, and so <hi>watches not</hi> for it.</p>
            <p n="7">7. If therefore it does not <hi>repent</hi> and <hi>watch,</hi> Christ will come, <hi>as a Thief,</hi> at that unexpected hour, upon it, and appear in dislike of it as a <hi>Reformed Church,</hi> to its horri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <hi>Amazement</hi> and <hi>shame.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="8">8. It may be communicated with, without defilement by the mere Communion; There are therefore <hi>Names in Sardis,</hi> that <hi>have not defil'd their Garments.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="9">9. There is yet danger to those that run with the most, and are not Cautious. For there are but a <hi>Few Names.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Characters of Time we may find upon the Church of <hi>Philadelphia,</hi> are,</p>
            <p n="1">1. That it begins with the <hi>Reformation,</hi> for till then, from the <hi>Apostacy,</hi> Christ appeared not with the <hi>Key of Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid,</hi> nor opened any door to the <hi>new Jerusalem,</hi> the <hi>City</hi> of <hi>David.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. That it runs along the <hi>Half Day</hi> of Delay; in which it keeps the <hi>word of Christs Patience,</hi> or stay for his <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom;</hi> All which Time none could <hi>shut that door,</hi> that is, could reduce <hi>Philadelphia</hi> from its true State, however it was endeavour'd, and therefore it continues to the <hi>new Jerusalem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Characters that most distinguish its state, are; to give them comprehensively;</p>
            <p n="1">1. That it is founded especially upon the Laws of <hi>Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly love.</hi> Not outward Force or Might, of which it hath very <hi>little</hi> or none, but is in an outward, low condition.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That it is as <hi>Smirna,</hi> kept down by a <hi>Synagogue of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than,</hi> some <hi>that say they are Jews,</hi> or <hi>Reform'd,</hi> that are
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:54329:38"/>not truly so; who would have it to be no <hi>Church,</hi> nor <hi>lov'd by Christ,</hi> as a <hi>Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This <hi>Synagogue</hi> seems to be some within the Appearance of the <hi>reformed Church,</hi> that are retiring as far back to <hi>Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon,</hi> in Superstition and <hi>Domination,</hi> (for so the <hi>Synagogue of Sathan</hi> implies) as <hi>Babylon</hi> was advanc'd in the Time of <hi>Smyrna,</hi> or near <hi>Constantine,</hi> towards the same Points, but shall never proceed, as that did.</p>
            <p>But that this may reflect on no <hi>Protestant Church,</hi> in its whole Body or Constitution; It is call'd a <hi>Synagogue</hi> of <hi>Sathan,</hi> implying, it is only some Faction of Men unapprov'd by any <hi>reform'd Church,</hi> and its <hi>True</hi> Constitution, and therefore not any <hi>reform'd</hi> Church it self, though this <hi>Synagogue</hi> may find place within one or more of them.</p>
            <p n="3">3. This Church comes nearest in its Graces and Constitutions to the <hi>Apostolick</hi> Church, and to the <hi>New Jerusalem,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore through the infinite Grace of Christ, it is only commended, as <hi>Smyrna,</hi> with which it symbolizes in its <hi>Poverty,</hi> or <hi>little Power;</hi> The <hi>Synagogue of Sathan</hi> emulating it; <hi>Its Crown:</hi> and therefore the Lord Jesus styles himself the <hi>Holy,</hi> and <hi>True,</hi> in writing to it as a <hi>Church,</hi> he hath so prepared to the <hi>New Jerusalem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now we have thus far pursued the Church-History, before we pass to the further times of it, we may observe, There is in these six <hi>Churches</hi> a near Alliance, between <hi>Ephesus</hi> and <hi>Sardis, Smyrna</hi> and <hi>Philadelphia, Pergamus</hi> and <hi>Thyatira,</hi> in each of the two, the former plac'd in the Descending Times to, the latter in the As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cending Times of the <hi>Church</hi> from <hi>Babylon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And so I am come to the End of the Prophetical Description of the state of Things, to near the End of the last <hi>Half Time</hi> of the <hi>Beast, viz.</hi> to the 167th of the 180 last years, in this present year 1684, and we have hitherto seen it, since the first <hi>Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> a Time of Delay; both as to the <hi>Popish,</hi> and <hi>Turkish</hi> Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny; as also, the Estate of the <hi>Churches,</hi> and as they have All continued much alike since then; so it is still to be expected they should do till the End, or nearer than we are yet to the End of this <hi>Half Time.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And also the opening of this Book of the <hi>Revelation,</hi> and the General understanding of it is such, as agrees with the Time of the <hi>Thunders seal'd,</hi> the Book eaten, and hidden, as it were in the Bowels of Interpreters; and very bitter for its difficulties, and unacceptance with others.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="appendix">
            <pb n="67" facs="tcp:54329:38"/>
            <head>AN APPENDIX, OR, A Survey of the Time to the End, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the general Importance of the <hi>Apocalyptick Prophecy;</hi> from the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent Year 1684.</head>
            <p>AT the End, or before the full End of <hi>the Half Time,</hi> these Things shall certainly come to pass.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The <hi>Beast</hi> shall be no longer in the <hi>Potency</hi> or <hi>Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny of a Beast;</hi> His Power to <hi>Continue</hi> or to <hi>Effect,</hi> will be out-dated, tho he vet continue in Being: for then shall <hi>the tenth Part of his City fall in an Earthquake,</hi> and all those things come to pass that are written, <hi>Apoc.</hi> 11.13. in their Perfection.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The <hi>Turkish Tyranny,</hi> which is the <hi>Second Woe,</hi> shall <hi>pass</hi> off in the Scourge and Terror of it, from the Christian World; that <hi>Bestian Power,</hi> as a Plague to which it was raised, and continued, being ceas'd.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The <hi>Witnesses</hi> shall be taken out of their <hi>Sack cloth,</hi> and <hi>call'd up,</hi> and enfranchiz'd, by a Voice from the <hi>Heaven</hi> of the most <hi>lawful Authority.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Especially Those within the Range of the Beast, and whom he is till this Time, as yet victorious over.</p>
            <p n="2">2. All the <hi>Servants of God</hi> of the <hi>Graecian Churches,</hi> that then shall survive of any part of the 14400 <hi>Sealed,</hi> that are kept low by <hi>Popish</hi> or <hi>Mahometan Influence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Whoever of the <hi>Church of Philadelphia</hi> are by the <hi>Synagogue of Satan</hi> over power'd and obscur'd.</p>
            <p n="4">4. There shall be a general Understanding of the Vision of <hi>the Witnesses</hi> in <hi>Sack-cloth;</hi> who they are, and who was the <hi>Beast</hi> that overcame them.</p>
            <pb n="68" facs="tcp:54329:39"/>
            <p> And immediately upon this <hi>Half Time</hi> ended, and the Events fulfill'd, the seventh <hi>Trumpet sounds.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And in the first Place, as the Prophecy leads us up, There is the first <hi>Vision</hi> of the <hi>Beast,</hi> and his Idolatrous and Bloody Reign, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der an universal Cognisance through the <hi>Reform'd Churches,</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the whole <hi>Apoc. cap.</hi> 13.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The <hi>Sound of the seventh Trumpet</hi> propagates it self into those <hi>great Voices</hi> in <hi>Heaven,</hi> saying, <hi>The Kingdoms of the World are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the Kingdoms of the Lord and his Christ:</hi> Now hath <hi>Philadel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phia,</hi> a <hi>Door of Ʋtterance, opened of the Lord,</hi> together with all the <hi>Servants of God,</hi> and <hi>his Witnesses</hi> in the World, prepar'd for them by that fore-mentioned <hi>Voice, Come up hither.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Voices</hi> are drawn out according to the seven <hi>Thunders seal'd</hi> till now, and now not written as <hi>Thunders,</hi> because not Events, but as <hi>Ministries of the Gospel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. A Communication of the most true, pure, spiritual, and intimate Sense of the Gospel of Christ the <hi>Lamb,</hi> as he is the <hi>Lamb,</hi> here, and often so styl'd in this Book,
<note place="margin">Apoc. c. 14. throughout</note> as most contrary to the <hi>Beast,</hi> &amp; his False Gospel, is as the <hi>Voice of Thunder.</hi> And it is peculiar to the 14400 <hi>Sealed,</hi> or Concealed <hi>Servants</hi> of God, till this Time, when they appear not in <hi>a Wilderness,</hi> but on <hi>Mount Zion,</hi> and with <hi>the Lamb;</hi> not <hi>Sealed</hi> on their <hi>Fore-head,</hi> but having the <hi>Name of God written openly,</hi> and <hi>at length</hi> there. They learn <hi>the Song of Redemption, Apoc.</hi> 5. so long out of general Use, that the <hi>Angels</hi> first sing it, <hi>as it were a new Song,</hi> and the 14400 only first learn it, to communicate it in general to the Church.</p>
            <p n="2">2. An <hi>Angel</hi> flies through <hi>the midst of Heaven;</hi> viz. <hi>The Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters</hi> of the <hi>Everlasting Gospel</hi> make some great and effectual Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration for the Reclaiming the whole World to the Worship of the one True God; under the Sense of the Approach of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments on <hi>Pagan</hi> and <hi>Pseudo-christian</hi> Idolatries, which had quarter'd <hi>Heaven, Earth, the Sea, and Fountains of Water, to their Idols.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. The third <hi>Voice</hi> declares the Effective Destruction and <hi>Fall of Babylon,</hi> immediately at the seventh <hi>Vial</hi> to ensue.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The fourth remonstrates the Danger of continuing to <hi>Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship the Beast, and his Image,</hi> or to <hi>Receive his Mark;</hi> which Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger would come upon them, at the very first of the Approaching <hi>Vials:</hi> till when, A Time of Respite was given for <hi>Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. The fifth <hi>Voice</hi> gives some lively Assurance of the <hi>first Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surrection</hi> of Martyrs, within the next Interval <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p n="6">
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:54329:39"/> 6. The sixth <hi>Voice</hi> is the Sound of the earnest Prayers of the Servants of the <hi>Crowned</hi> Lord of the Harvest, with his <hi>sharp Sickle</hi> in his Hand for the Reaping the Earth, or Conversion of the <hi>Jews,</hi> and the <hi>Bringing in the Fullness of the Gentiles.</hi> And it was immediately executed, as in Prophecy, by the Assurance it should be so, the <hi>Command</hi> going out, as to <hi>Damel,</hi> though not imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately executed.</p>
            <p n="7">7. The seventh is the same earnest Supplication of the <hi>Angel,</hi> that had <hi>Power over the Fire,</hi> Apoc. 8. to scatter it to the Dectru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the <hi>Heathenish Army</hi> gather'd against <hi>Theodos.</hi> so of those<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to be gathered in <hi>Armageddon:</hi> upon which there was such a <hi>Treading of the Wine-press without the City,</hi> that is, such a Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the <hi>Guilt of Babylon,</hi> and its <hi>Bestian King,</hi> by Christ in his Ministers among all the <hi>Reformed Churches,</hi> that <hi>Blood,</hi> or the Guilt, was enough for the <hi>Beasts Armies</hi> to swim in, wherever they should be embattell'd: Christ himself, as Mediator, <hi>treads the Wine-press,</hi> and pleads <hi>Babylon</hi>'s Guilt, and all his Ministers under him: And out of this Exundation of Guilt were the seven <hi>Vials</hi> fill'd <hi>with the wrath of God,</hi> at the End of <hi>Daniel's Thirty Prophetick Days,</hi> or <hi>Years.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And here begins the pow'ring out of the Vials in the last forty five Years. Now as the Voices were Authoriz'd by Supreme Magistrates of most lawful Authority, so the Vials are given to Angels <hi>in pure</hi> and <hi>white Linnen;</hi> not so in the <hi>Trumpets,</hi> to shew the unstain'd and unblemish'd Instruments God uses at this Time, not chargeable with any thing like Sedition, or Rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but having Sovereigns joyn'd with them; or rather, being so themselves: for, God puts it into the Heart of the <hi>Kings to hate the Whore,</hi> &amp;c. who had <hi>agreed to give him their Power;</hi> When his Words were to be fulfilled of 42 M. allowed to the <hi>Beasts King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,</hi> they submitted their Crowns and Scepters to him; and now that his <hi>Words</hi> for his Destruction were to be fulfilled, They obey in this also: for, the <hi>King of Kings,</hi> and <hi>Lord of Lords overcomes</hi> them. Nor by the Rebellion of Subjects, but as he did <hi>Ahasuerus,</hi> when he fought with him by <hi>Trains of Providence,</hi> and made him favour the <hi>Jews,</hi> whose Destruction he had first sign'd, as we read in <hi>Esther</hi> the whole History; the <hi>Jews,</hi> as his Subjects, being most obedient all the while: For the <hi>Hearts of Kings are in his Hand, and he turns them as the Rivers of Waters,</hi> as he pleases. Before <hi>the pow'ring</hi> out of the <hi>Vials</hi> there is the <hi>Song of Triumph over the Beast,</hi> as upon the Edge of the <hi>Red Sea,</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luding
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:54329:40"/>to <hi>Moses his Song;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Apoc.</hi> 15.</note> and the <hi>Tabernacle of Testimony seen open,</hi> a higher Discovery of the purest <hi>Church State,</hi> but not to be enjoyed, till the <hi>Vial's poured out.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>One of the four <hi>Living Creatures,</hi> that is, the <hi>First,</hi> for so <hi>One</hi> signifies all along in this Prophecy; <hi>viz.</hi> the Pure Apostolick Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nistry, by the <hi>undefiled Names in</hi> Sardis <hi>and</hi> Philadelphia, gives the <hi>Vials to the Angel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>First Angel of the Vials</hi> gives <hi>John</hi> the History of the <hi>Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Chap.</hi> 17.</note> and the <hi>Beast carrying her,</hi> the <hi>Roman Church,</hi> as it is call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, being hardly believed to be so bad, or so doom'd to Destru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; and therefore <hi>John</hi> was <hi>prophetically reprov'd</hi> for his <hi>Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical Wonderment</hi> at her.</p>
            <p>He also gives him the Description of <hi>her Judgment,</hi> which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun with the <hi>Vials:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Chap.</hi> 18.</note> and then is the last <hi>Call</hi> out of <hi>Babylon,</hi> and the last Call to <hi>Repentance;</hi> for at the end of the <hi>Thunders unseal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi> in the <hi>Voices, John</hi> is bidden not to <hi>seal</hi> the <hi>Sayings</hi> of <hi>the Prophecy of this Book,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Chap.</hi> 22.10, 11.</note> viz.</hi> this last Part; and then it follows, <hi>He that is Filthy let him be Filthy still,</hi> and <hi>He that is Righteous,</hi> &amp;c. There shall be after the <hi>Vials</hi> begun, neither Repentance, nor Apostasie. At this Time the twenty four <hi>Elders,</hi> shewing the not yet <hi>Apostolick State,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Chap.</hi> 11.16. <hi>Chap.</hi> 15.2.</note> alone fall down, and sing the Song of Praise,</hi> in which Song the whole Multitude of those that <hi>had got the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory over the Beast</hi> joyn'd, but not as yet constituted <hi>under an uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versal Apostolick Ministry;</hi> and therefore only <hi>one</hi> of the four <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Creatures</hi> appears.</p>
            <p>The first <hi>Vial</hi> makes all the <hi>marked Servants of the Beast</hi> as loathsome as those that had the <hi>Botch</hi> of <hi>Egypt</hi> upon them;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Chap.</hi> 16.1. <hi>throughout.</hi>
               </note> so that their very Earth abhors them.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The second embargoes all the Beasts Idolatrous Trassick, making the <hi>Sea</hi> of his <hi>Catholick Church</hi> as innavigable as the <hi>Blood of a dead Man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. The third makes all <hi>Aque-ducts</hi> of Idolatrous Doctrines, for Profit, and Pleasure to the <hi>Beasts Palace,</hi> as dangerous and bloody as he had formerly made the Channels of the pure Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Life; on which Account the Righteousness of this Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, however slander'd, is justified.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The fourth falls upon the <hi>Sun of the Imperial Profession of Christian Religion,</hi> in which the <hi>Beasts Kingdom</hi> had its Supreme Light, however debauched by it; and the <hi>Sun</hi> suffering nothing it self, <hi>scorched Men</hi> with its Light and Efficacy, as with <hi>Fire,</hi> so that they were <hi>angry,</hi> and <hi>blasphemed,</hi> but repented not; and even
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:54329:40"/>curs'd that <hi>Imperial Christianity,</hi> as separated from their Papal Fable.</p>
            <p n="5">5. The fifth <hi>Vial</hi> is poured out upon the <hi>Seat or Throne of the Beast, Rome</hi> and the <hi>Papal Territory,</hi> or as it is called, St. <hi>Peters Patrimony,</hi> which reduced his Kingdom to that Ignobleness, and sordid state, that like the <hi>Egyptian Darkness,</hi> they feel it, and <hi>gnaw their Tongues,</hi> are <hi>angry, Blaspheme,</hi> and <hi>repent not,</hi> but are <hi>filthy still.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. The sixth <hi>Vial</hi> falls upon <hi>Euphrates,</hi> which prepares for the <hi>Jews,</hi> the <hi>Kings of the East,</hi> a passage over it, and, as I am bold to conceive, they are brought upon the <hi>Arms of the Persians</hi> those ancient deliverers of the <hi>Jews,</hi> from <hi>Litteral Babylon;</hi> in the beginning of which Monarchy the date of our <hi>great Prophetick Line</hi> enters; and within which, the <hi>Weeks</hi> of the <hi>Messiah</hi> begin, even under a <hi>Persian</hi> Prince, the Son of the most religious <hi>Esther;</hi> whose decree complementally built the <hi>Temple</hi> at <hi>Jerusalem;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matt.</hi> 2.1.</note> from which <hi>Persia</hi> the <hi>three Magi of the East</hi> came to worship <hi>Messiah</hi> at his Birth.</p>
            <p>And who knows, but these <hi>Persians</hi> are the <hi>Tydings out of the East,</hi> together with others out of the <hi>North,</hi> that trouble the <hi>Turk</hi> that <hi>King of the North,</hi> who shall now <hi>come to his end,</hi> and <hi>none shall help him,</hi> according to <hi>Dan.</hi> 11. <hi>ult.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And this above all makes the <hi>Nations Angry,</hi> for by the Sollici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations of the <hi>Beast, the false Prophet,</hi> and the <hi>Dragon,</hi> or <hi>Sathan</hi> acting the Interest of every one, they conspire, and <hi>bring down their Armies to Armageddon</hi> to their <hi>final Destruction.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here Christ gives an Alarm to <hi>Ephesus,</hi> summoning it to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend him in <hi>white Linnen with the Armies of Heaven.</hi> And now is the <hi>Tryal</hi> that comes on <hi>all the Earth,</hi> and therefore Christ sayes, <hi>Blessed is he that watcheth and keepeth his Garments, &amp;c.</hi> In this <hi>Tryal Philadelphia</hi> is especially kept as Christ promised, and also the <hi>undefiled Names in Sardis:</hi> and all that <hi>overcame,</hi> others being in Danger <hi>to walk naked,</hi> and Men <hi>see their shame.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7. The seventh <hi>Vial</hi> brings us to the two.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>It is done, It is done:</hi> the Destruction of <hi>Babylon</hi> and <hi>the New Jerusalem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>First, the <hi>Armies</hi> are gathered together, and <hi>he that is faithful</hi> and <hi>True,</hi> to whom <hi>the Heavens open</hi> to let him out in highest State, comes forth on his <hi>white Horse,</hi> as at first; and the <hi>Armies of Heaven follow him, &amp;c.</hi> on <hi>white Horses, in Linnen,</hi> clean, and white, according to the full Description, <hi>Cap.</hi> 19. In this
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:54329:41"/>Congress the <hi>Beast</hi> and <hi>false Prophet</hi> are <hi>taken,</hi> and <hi>cast alive into the Lake of Fire,</hi> The <hi>Remnant</hi> are <hi>killed with the Sword of Christs Mouth; the Dragon is laid hold on, and bound; The Cityes of the Nations fall,</hi> Mahometanism, and Paganism, before the Glory of Christ.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Great Babylon</hi> is <hi>remembred before God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cap.</hi> 11. <hi>ult. Cap.</hi> 16. <hi>ult. Cap.</hi> 18.</note> and hath the <hi>full</hi> and perpetual Execution of <hi>Judgment</hi> upon <hi>her.</hi> At which are the <hi>Thundrings, Lightnings, Earthquake,</hi> and <hi>that Hail,</hi> so unparal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lel'd; with <hi>Daniels</hi> time of <hi>trouble, such as never was since there was a Nation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All the Time from the very <hi>first Vial,</hi> the <hi>New Jerusalem</hi> is <hi>coming down from Heaven,</hi> in preparation, for the <hi>first Angel of the Vials shewed</hi> it to <hi>John;</hi> but it is not fully understood, till after the <hi>last Vial,</hi> according to the order wherein the <hi>Vision</hi> is given.</p>
            <p>And so we are come to the end of the 45 <hi>Prophetick Days, or Years,</hi> which will be in the <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 1772, and to <hi>the end</hi> of <hi>Dan.</hi> 1335 Dayes, and to the end of the 2300 <hi>Evenings</hi> and <hi>Morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings,</hi> that begun at the <hi>fall of Babylon,</hi> and the <hi>restoring Jerusa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem</hi> in the Letter, (from which time in <hi>Prophetick</hi> Account, <hi>Mysti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Babylon</hi> was rising) and end at the <hi>fall of</hi> that <hi>Mystical Babylon,</hi> and the <hi>New Jerusalem;</hi> which is a Reason of great value, why the <hi>Vision</hi> begins so long before, not only the Antitype, the <hi>Beast,</hi> but the Type <hi>Antiochus,</hi> who is so plain a Type, that not one Word in the Exposition of the <hi>Vision,</hi> but suits more lively to the Antitype than Type, as also the <hi>Sealing,</hi> and <hi>shutting up the Vision,</hi> because it was for <hi>many Dayes,</hi> but if it had only reached to <hi>Antiochus,</hi> It had been for fewer Dayes, then any one of <hi>Daniels</hi> principal <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions,</hi> which ever, whereas it is indeed commensurate with the longest, that is, with every one describing the <hi>Monarchies</hi> before Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teral <hi>Babylons fall</hi> in their common end; and with that <hi>Cap.</hi> 10, 11. <hi>c.</hi> 12. describing the three <hi>Monarchies</hi> in the beginning, and end, after Literal <hi>Babylons</hi> fall, being its just parallel.</p>
            <p>As now the Time grows nearer to the fulfilling of all Things, so the <hi>Testisications</hi> of it will grow <hi>louder</hi> and <hi>clearer,</hi> both to invite to the <hi>Waters of Life</hi> all <hi>that Thirst,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Apoc. 22.</note> and to terrifie Offenders, and the Prayers of Saints <hi>for Christ's Coming</hi> grow more carnest and vehement.</p>
            <p>By this understanding of the <hi>Times,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Chron.</note> we may, as the Children of <hi>Issachar,</hi> know what <hi>Israel ought to do,</hi> in Holy Doctrines, Worship, and Practise, in Humble Hopes, Expectations, and Desires; we may better judge of Churches and Constitutions,
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:54329:41"/>than by any Records of Antiquity; we may see the dreadful Mischiefs Men fall into by running both out of Christ's Order and Time, in offering by Seditious, Turbulent, or Rebellious Commotions, to hasten his Kingdom, who will do all by purest and most unblemish'd Instruments, and by Princes themselves, in <hi>his own Times:</hi> and most undoubtedly by our Princes of <hi>Great Brittain</hi> among others; beginning, as we may hope, and ought to pray, in our present Gracious Sovereign, preserv'd to the long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est course of Life: Wherein all his Procedures shall be most Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious at the last Rising of the Witnesses, even far above the first <hi>Reformation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which, as in some Nations, it might have some Stains of disor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, so they may be purging out to this day by Sufferings, though to the greater Purification of those <hi>Churches</hi> in other Regards.</p>
            <p>Where the <hi>Reformation</hi> was most Regular by Princes, there hath it been most blessed with Peace and Prosperity, though even that may have been misimproved to more imperfect Reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons on other Accounts.</p>
            <p>It is most dangerous to <hi>add or take away from this Book,</hi> by any Misinterpretations to Tumultuary, or <hi>Popular Reformations,</hi> punish'd both here, and hereafter without <hi>Repentance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is nothing now to be added, but a most brief Descripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the <hi>New Jerusalem,</hi> with the contrary Unhappy State, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>current; which having not been generally truly represented, hath been as much praejudg'd in better Accounts of it; but is most ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessary to be known, for every single Person is infinitely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd in it, seeing <hi>the taking away from any Man</hi> his <hi>Part in the Holy City,</hi> is one of the severest Threats of this Book, in which, if every man might not have a Part, it were of no force at all;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The New Jerusalem</hi> then, is a state of Glory, but with a <hi>Gulf,</hi> and <hi>Lake</hi> of Misery on the other side, each respecting every man: and each is Three-fold.</p>
            <p n="1">1. There is the Happiness of the extraordinary Servants of God, <hi>Prophets, Apostles, Martyrs;</hi> Glorious Souls invested with Glorious Bodies: <hi>Many of them that sleep in the Dust, shall awake to everlasting Life: And they that are wise, shall shine as the Stars; and that turn many to Righteousness, as the brightnsss of the Firma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi> Christ gives the <hi>Martyrs</hi> in <hi>Smirna a Crown of Life. I saw the Souls of them that were beheaded;</hi> &amp;c. and <hi>they Lived.</hi> These are in a visible Heaven, so that their Glory comes down on Earth; and they <hi>Reign on Earth;</hi> And <hi>for ever and ever,</hi> in Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity;
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:54329:42"/>
               <hi>over them the second Death hath no power.</hi> They, <hi>as the Lamb's Wife,</hi> make that <hi>Heavenly Jerusalem,</hi> that does not remove from Heaven; but comes down in its Lustre from thence, with the <hi>Glory of God,</hi> and <hi>the Lamb;</hi> and an <hi>innumerable Company of Angels</hi> over it; a City of much higher Priviledges than can agree with any State on Earth.</p>
            <p>It is much to be fear'd, there is a Misery on the other side, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>current; <hi>The Beast, the False Prophet,</hi> and the <hi>Babylonish Woman,</hi> the <hi>Popes,</hi> and their <hi>Hierarchy,</hi> not repenting, are to be raised at this Time; but not as the <hi>Blessed Children of this First Resurrection,</hi> but made visible in Bodies and Souls in Torment; for, the <hi>Beast</hi> and <hi>false Prophet</hi> are <hi>cast alive into the Lake,</hi> where the <hi>Devil</hi> is cast at the last Judgment, and <hi>the Dead that are given us then; not written in the Book of Life;</hi> which is <hi>the Second Death.</hi> What then can be the Sense? but that Souls and Bodies are cast into it, when they are cast alive into it; <hi>Many that sleep in the Dust shall awake to everlasting Shame and Contempt. The Smoke of</hi> Babylon's <hi>Torment ascends for ever, and ever.</hi> These Torments are visible to the <hi>Heavenly Jerusalem, Rejoyce over her; Thou Heaven,</hi> and ye <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Prophets,</hi> and <hi>Appstles;</hi> visible to the misorable <hi>Kings,</hi> and <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants of the Earth, that slain with the Sword of Christ's Mouth, bewail her burning.</hi> Visible in such degrees to the <hi>Church</hi> on Earth, that they <hi>look on the Carcasses of the Men that have transgressed against God,</hi> whose <hi>Worm dies not, and their Fire is not quench'd.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The Souls of all the <hi>Holy Servants of God, both Small</hi> and <hi>Great,</hi> have rewards by Enlargements of Glory, and free Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versation in <hi>this Holy City,</hi> though not in such a visible Glory as before described. All that <hi>overcome</hi> of every <hi>Church, eat of the Tree of Life, are not hurt of the second Doath, drink of the Water of Life,</hi> and in a Word, <hi>inherit all things;</hi> are of the <hi>Blessed called to the Marriage Supper of the Lamb, have Right to the Tree of Life,</hi> and <hi>to enter through the Gates into the City:</hi> And because Holy men and Women, <hi>that do his Commands</hi> in all times, are to be successive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly from this <hi>Appearance of Christ</hi> translated into this <hi>New Jerusalem,</hi> therefore All are invited to come to these <hi>Waters of Life</hi> that run in the <hi>Chrystal River,</hi> that <hi>thirst for them,</hi> and <hi>to take freely of them;</hi> and the <hi>blessedness</hi> of a <hi>Right to the Tree of Life,</hi> and <hi>to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> &amp;c. is generally pronounc'd on all that <hi>do his Commands;</hi> for as the <hi>Testimony of Jesus</hi> throughout all the Scripture is the <hi>Spirit of this Prophecy,</hi> so is the Obedience to his Commands in all his Gospul, the <hi>Reading, Hearing,</hi> and <hi>Keeping the Sayings of this Book.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="75" facs="tcp:54329:42"/>
            <p> On the other side, miserable are those Souls that have not overcome by inward, personal Grace, of what Church soever, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> In general, all impure and impenitent, more signally, <hi>they that have worshipped the Beast,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>they are tormented before God and the Lamb;</hi> and <hi>the Holy Angels; the Fowls,</hi> the cruel and ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacious <hi>Spirits of the Power of the Air, feast on their Flesh: they can in no wise enter into the City,</hi> but are <hi>without as Dogs: the high Hill</hi> of <hi>Jasper,</hi> and the <hi>Angels at every Gate,</hi> preclude them, as <hi>Adam</hi> of old, <hi>out of Paradise.</hi> They are slain (that is, condemn'd) with <hi>the Sword of Christ's Mouth;</hi> they <hi>have their Part</hi> in, though not <hi>cast alive into the Lake, which is the Second Death,</hi> when Soul and Body are cast into it; God <hi>adds to them the Plagues written in this Book.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. The <hi>New Jerusalem</hi> is the most happy State of the Church of God, both of <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Gentiles</hi> here on Earth; in which shall be <hi>fulfill'd all things that have been spoken of by the Prophets since the Foundation of the World,</hi> so far, as can agree with the State of Man fallen on Earth: There shall be bountiful Rays from <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels,</hi> and <hi>Saints</hi> in <hi>Jerusalem above;</hi> yet there shall be such a Preseuce of <hi>God,</hi> and <hi>the Lamb above</hi> them, as shall preserve the Church most pure from any Idolatrous Respects to them, as is prophesied in the double, severe Prohibition of <hi>John</hi>'s double Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer of <hi>Worship to the Angel,</hi> that reveal'd the <hi>New Jerusalem to</hi> him, and the <hi>Angels</hi> utter Refusal of it, as keeping the Words of <hi>this Book.</hi> The Churches Eyes shall be only on the <hi>one God,</hi> and <hi>one Mediator,</hi> and his <hi>Blood, the only Propitiation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whatever was amiss in <hi>the Churches,</hi> is quite taken away. <hi>Ephesus,</hi> though Apostolical in its Beginning, yet because <hi>it left its first Love</hi> by the <hi>Mystery</hi> of <hi>Babylon's Iniquity beginning to work,</hi> lost the <hi>Place of its Candlestick</hi> in the <hi>New Jerusalem,</hi> that it might not mislead by its Pattern. <hi>Smyrna,</hi> though a <hi>Church</hi> into which <hi>all the innumerable Company of Martyrs</hi> were adopted, and, as such, hath the <hi>Crown of the New Jerusalem above,</hi> yet because of the <hi>blaspheming,</hi> or Idolatrizing <hi>Synagogue</hi> of <hi>Satan,</hi> over shading it by degrees, can be no Pattern of the <hi>Church</hi> on Earth: nor <hi>Perga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus,</hi> having those <hi>that hold Balaam's Doctrine;</hi> nor <hi>Thyatyra,</hi> suffering <hi>Jezabel;</hi> nor <hi>Sardis,</hi> because her Reformation not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, nor her <hi>Garments undefiled;</hi> but only <hi>Philadelphia,</hi> as per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly <hi>Apostolick;</hi> and the <hi>Synagogue of Satan</hi> not suffered to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed, but brought <hi>to worship at her Feet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Cities of the Nations, Mahometanism</hi> and <hi>Paganism fallen, the Beast,</hi> and <hi>false Prophet in the Lake.</hi> Babylon <hi>sunk, as a Mill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stone,
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:54329:43"/>to be found no more;</hi> that is, <hi>Popery</hi> all destroy'd; with its <hi>My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stery,</hi> and <hi>Synagogue of Satan,</hi> in <hi>Ephesus,</hi> and <hi>Smyrna.</hi> Its Throne and <hi>Balaamitism</hi> cut off by the two edged <hi>Sword of Christ's Mouth</hi> in <hi>Pergamus;</hi> its <hi>Jezabel,</hi> and <hi>her Children, killed with Death;</hi> the <hi>Depths of Satan</hi> proclaim'd, and abhorred in <hi>Thyatyra; Sar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dis,</hi> her <hi>Depths Garments</hi> are thrown off, and <hi>Nakedness</hi> chosen rather; <hi>Philadelphia's Synagogue of Satan</hi> is not suffered to proceed, but brought to Humiliation. Thus <hi>the Sanctuary is cleans'd.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Dragon,</hi> or <hi>old Serpent, Satan, is bound, to deceive the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons no more for</hi> 1000 Years: there shall be then no false Religion, no Persecution; for, the <hi>Kings of the Earth,</hi> and <hi>the Nations,</hi> shall <hi>bring their Glory</hi> and <hi>Honour</hi> to the <hi>New Jerusalem above,</hi> by do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all Service to the <hi>Church</hi> on Earth, as the Beams of that above are reflected on that below. And <hi>the Nations of them that are Sav'd shall walk in the Light of that</hi> Jerusalem <hi>above,</hi> as the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est Enforcement of all Holiness and Rule of it. The <hi>Leaves of the Tree of Life</hi> shall allay, and heal all the Scorchings of Tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>Thus <hi>the New Jerusalem</hi> is the <hi>Paradise of God,</hi> not the <hi>High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est Heaven,</hi> yet far above Earth.</p>
            <p>The Church in its <hi>Abundance of Truth and Peace</hi> is <hi>the New Jerusalem on Earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>These two must not be confounded, lest we marr the Divine Pourtray of the <hi>Holy City.</hi> Both make up <hi>Ezekiel's Vision.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That <hi>above</hi> hath no <hi>Sorrow, Pain, Death,</hi> nor <hi>any Sin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This <hi>below,</hi> however it excell all former States, yet hath Death, though after long Life; and Sin; private Temptation, though not of publick Influency: There shall not be <hi>an Infant, that hath not fill'd up his Days,</hi> but the <hi>Sinner, an hundred Years old, shall dye accurs'd;</hi> The <hi>rest,</hi> or <hi>succession of the dead live not till the</hi> 1000 <hi>years ended;</hi> therefore they dye as at other Times: And <hi>nothing desiling</hi> can enter to the last the <hi>New Jerusalem.</hi> There is all that Time Invitations <hi>to the Waters of Life</hi> by <hi>Thirst</hi> for them; Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monitions <hi>to do his Commands;</hi> Comminations against all Impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity; a continual Right, as Men dye, <hi>to the Tree of Life,</hi> &amp;c. and a <hi>Justice</hi> in Seclnsion from it; all which argue a State of Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfection <hi>below. Above</hi> only is Perfection.</p>
            <p>By Calculation of Time, this Blessed State will begin 'ere the seventh thousand of the World enters, but as near as within 240 Years: so there will remain so many after the 1000 Years, dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:54329:43"/>the Time of God's bearing with the Old World before the Flood, 'ere the Eight Thousand of the World can begin.</p>
            <p>How much God will allow the World out of it, as a space be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the 1000 Years and Judgment we cannot divine: for the Church after so Blessed a State (the <hi>New Jerusalem</hi> being drawn up to Heaven again and <hi>Satan</hi> loos'd) declines in <hi>Loadicea's Luke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warmness,</hi> and the World grows salvage in <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog's Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing.</hi> After therefore some Time allowed to <hi>Loadicea,</hi> to be <hi>zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous,</hi> and <hi>repent, Fire comes</hi> down on <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog; Satan</hi> is thrown into the same Eternity of Punishment, and Deprivation of all Power and Action, as the <hi>Beast and False Prophet;</hi> the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penitent of <hi>Laodicea</hi> are <hi>spued out;</hi> the <hi>White Throne is set, from which Heaven and Earth fly away,</hi> and they that <hi>overcome</hi> sit down with Christ on his Throne; the Day of Judgment begins <hi>on all the Dead.</hi> And whatever <hi>is not found written in the Book of Life</hi> is cast into <hi>the Lake of the Second Death.</hi> And after the seventh thousand Sabbath of the <hi>New Jerusalem</hi> pass'd away (though in some Respects also a <hi>Lord's Day Sabbath</hi>) the eighth thousand, or <hi>Lord's Day Sabbatism,</hi> ever <hi>continues to the People of God.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PAg. 3. l. 2., after God. l. 4.; after Church. l. 20. <hi>read</hi> very. p. 4. l. 19. dele in <hi>Egypt.</hi> l. 29. <hi>r.</hi> 430. p. 5. l. 14. <hi>r.</hi> 450. l. 22. <hi>r.</hi> untill. p. 6. l. 9. <hi>r.</hi> hath. p. 11. l. 6. 561. p. 13. l. 20. 559. p. 14. l. 19. <hi>r.</hi> at. p. 16. l. last, <hi>r.</hi> for 8. p. 17. l. 23. <hi>r.</hi> Fourteens. p. 19. l. 10. <hi>r.</hi> libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral. p. 22. l. 16. dele if. p. 23. l. ult. <hi>r.</hi> is. p. 24. l. 1. at the end of the line, <hi>r.</hi> is included; p. 26. l. 2. after Enemies, <hi>r.</hi> or. l. 22 <hi>r.</hi> the solemnly. p. 30. l. 13. after thought, <hi>r.</hi> it; p. 44. l. 33. dele the. p. 46. l. 5. <hi>r.</hi> Beasts. l. 26.; after more. p. 46. l. 19. <hi>r. Theodosius.</hi> p. 52. l. 12. dele is after 666. in marg. <hi>r.</hi> 725. l. 30. <hi>r.</hi> Potters. p. 53. l. penult. <hi>r.</hi> Freedoms. p. 59. l. 13. <hi>r.</hi> Types for Times. p. 72. marg. <hi>r.</hi> 1 Chron. 12.32.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb facs="tcp:54329:44"/>
            <pb n="79" facs="tcp:54329:44"/>
            <head>A POSTSCRIPT OR Additional View OF What may, in Dr. <hi>More</hi>'s Apocalyptick Sentiments, particularly in his late An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer to <hi>Remarks upon his Expositions,</hi> &amp;c. by <hi>S.E.</hi> or <hi>Arithmet. Apocalipt.</hi> affect the precedent Calendar; and a <hi>Vindication</hi> of the <hi>Calendary Part</hi> from it.</head>
            <p>I Am much concern'd to seem to repugn any thing in the Writings of so great and excellent a Person, as the most Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious and Learned Dr. <hi>More;</hi> from whom all the Literate World hath received so much Light, the Christian World so great Evidences of the Truth and Reasonableness of Christian Religion, and the Protestant Churches so great Assurances both from Reason and expounded Prophecy; and to whom my own Obligations are so great for Conduct into Apocalyptical Contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plations. But my Belief is, It is the true Mind of the Prophecy he is concerned for; and in the Pursuit of that, he is not unwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to enter a Dissent to the most worthy Mr. <hi>Mede,</hi> for whose Memory he hath so great a Value: nor is it a little Satisfaction to me, I am fully convinc'd of the Certainty of his Fundamentals. What may be objected to the foregoing Calendar from his Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timents, in the Calendary Part, and the Answers to it, now follow.</p>
            <div n="1" type="objection">
               <pb n="80" facs="tcp:54329:45"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> I.</head>
               <p>The <hi>vision of taking away the daily Sacrifice,</hi> is restrained to <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiochus,</hi> who swallows up the whole literal Sense of the 2300 <hi>Even<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings</hi> and <hi>Mornings,</hi> which therefore can be no Line of Time so extended to the <hi>End</hi> of all beyond him.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="1" type="answer">
               <head>
                  <hi>Answ.</hi> I.</head>
               <p>The plain literal Sense of the 2300 <hi>Even.</hi> and <hi>Morn.</hi> is the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent of the whole <hi>Vision,</hi> though it be call'd from the principal Notes of its Time, <hi>The Vision of the daily, &amp;c.</hi> for it is not said, <hi>How long shall be the Time of the taking away the daily Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice?</hi> but, <hi>How long the Vision of it?</hi> Now <hi>the Vision</hi> plainly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins at the Fall of Literal <hi>Babylon,</hi> goes along through the <hi>Persian</hi> Monarchy, down by the <hi>Grecian, and its Division to four,</hi> to the <hi>Roman,</hi> and so to <hi>Antichrist;</hi> and is not near so adequate in na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural <hi>Nycthemers</hi> to <hi>Antiochus</hi> his Tyranny, as to the whole <hi>Visi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> in <hi>Prophetick</hi> ones.</p>
               <p n="2">2. It is very evident by the Words, the Prophecy expends on each; its chief Eye is in every <hi>Vision</hi> of the <hi>four Monarchies</hi> upon the <hi>Roman.</hi> In every <hi>Vision</hi> of the three <hi>Monarchies,</hi> it is chiefly on <hi>Antiochus,</hi> till it passes by him to the <hi>Roman;</hi> and in the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> it chiefly insists upon what is most commensurate to <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>christ;</hi> so that <hi>Antiochus</hi> is set as the connexive Joynt between the <hi>Grecian</hi> and <hi>Roman Monarchy,</hi> and as an <hi>Antichrist</hi> fore-typing the true <hi>Antichrist;</hi> at which <hi>Dan.</hi> was so <hi>astonish'd</hi> and <hi>sick,</hi> even at that <hi>Vision</hi> of the <hi>daily Sacrifice,</hi> not looking upon <hi>Antiochus</hi> as an open Enemy of the <hi>Jews,</hi> less amazing so, than <hi>Titus</hi> or <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drian,</hi> who destroyed <hi>Jerusalem,</hi> and the <hi>Temple</hi> finally: which <hi>Dan.</hi> had reveal'd to him in the end of the 70 <hi>Weeks</hi> Vision, without any such <hi>Astonishment.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If this then be undeniable, what wonder is it, that a Line of Time should be drawn over <hi>Antiochus,</hi> as a Type to <hi>Antichrist</hi> the Antitype, reaching from literal <hi>Babylon</hi> falling, to mystical <hi>Babylon</hi> falling, from <hi>Literal Jerusalem</hi> restor'd, to the <hi>New Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>salem.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And seeing just then Historical Scripture in a manner ended, and a Prophecy, reaching to the end, had begun by <hi>Ezekiel,</hi> and that by him God had fettled the use of prophetick <hi>Days</hi> for <hi>Years,</hi> how reasonable is it, a Line, according to that Settlement, should be given by <hi>Daniel</hi> the Prophet of the <hi>End</hi> of all, so <hi>delighted</hi> in, to the very <hi>End</hi> of all? <hi>Prophetick</hi> Scripture being as noble, and deserving to be adorn'd with a Line of Time equally to it, as
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:54329:45"/>
                  <hi>Historick,</hi> which hath indisputably such a Line to <hi>Cyrus.</hi> And that it is veil'd under the <hi>Vision</hi> of the <hi>daily Sacrifice,</hi> taken away as if it was only coextended to that, and under 2300 <hi>Evenings, Mornings,</hi> pertains to the Secresie of the Prophecy. Yet God had begun, and plainly given the Key of that Cypher of <hi>Days</hi> for <hi>Years</hi> by <hi>Ezekiel,</hi> as hath been often noted.</p>
               <p n="3">3. That <hi>Rome</hi> is Mystical <hi>Babylon,</hi> even <hi>Romanists</hi> acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, though they mean <hi>Heathen Rome.</hi> Now, as the Eye of Scripture hath been always on Literal <hi>Babylon</hi> from the <hi>Tower of Babel,</hi> and <hi>Nimrod the great Hunter</hi> before the Lord his founding its Empire, to its rising higher in <hi>Baladan,</hi> or <hi>Nabonazar,</hi> the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond <hi>Belus,</hi> as <hi>Tho. Lydiat</hi> supposes, (just with whose Reign be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, it is observable <hi>Rome</hi> was founded) so hath it the same Eye on this Mystical <hi>Babylon;</hi> the proper <hi>Base</hi> of the <hi>Woman Wickedness</hi> is the Mystical <hi>Land</hi> of <hi>Shinar, Zech.</hi> 5.11. and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is no wonder it draws a Line of Time from <hi>Babylon</hi> to <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon,</hi> as the perpetual Opposite to <hi>Jerusalem.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="objection">
               <head>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> 2.</head>
               <p>But it is said, the <hi>Vision of the Evening</hi> and <hi>Morning</hi> is <hi>true,</hi> or plain Sense, as the <hi>Truth</hi> of the <hi>little Horn, Dan.</hi> desir'd to know,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Dan.</hi> 8.</note> was the plain meaning of it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="answer">
               <head>Answ.</head>
               <p>There is indeed the plain Sense of part of the <hi>Vision</hi> given, and a fuller Exposition of <hi>Antiochus</hi> in the true <hi>Antichrist.</hi> But it is also observable. <hi>Apoc.</hi> 21.6. and <hi>c.</hi> 22.6. it is said, <hi>These Words are true and faithful,</hi> and <hi>these Sayings are faithful and true;</hi> and c. 19. v. 9. <hi>These are the true Sayings of God.</hi> Where it is evident, there was much of Prophetick Veil, or Parable: and these seem to allude to this very Expression in this Vision; which terminates in the <hi>cleansing the Sanctuary,</hi> and the <hi>breaking Antichrist without hand,</hi> fulfill'd in the Apocal. on occasion of which, these Words are us'd; and so the Line reaches to the just end of the Vision accomplished, and this <hi>Item</hi> given of it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="objection">
               <head>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> 3.</head>
               <p>But if it be granted, (as that excellent Person professes himself inclin'd to grant) there may be a Line of Prophetick Time in these 2300 <hi>Even. Mornings,</hi> yet it is most reasonable it should begin at <hi>the taking away the daily Sacrifice by Antiochus.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="answer">
               <head>Answ.</head>
               <p>This Objection is before answer'd, that it is a Line of Time adequate to the whole Vision, which begins with <hi>Cyrus</hi> at <hi>Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon</hi>'s
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:54329:46"/>Destruction; and running on to the end of all, as de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="objection">
               <head>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> 4.</head>
               <p>But if the Line of 2300 <hi>Ev. Morn.</hi> could be suppos'd to begin at <hi>Cyrus,</hi> yet the 1335 days, <hi>Dan.</hi> 12. cannot be set to any other Point of Time than <hi>Antiochus;</hi> for, it is expresly dated from <hi>ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king away the daily Sacrifice:</hi> and that is enough to destroy the Calendar.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="answer">
               <head>Answ.</head>
               <p>As there was a taking away the <hi>daily Sacrifice</hi> by <hi>Antioch.</hi> in Type, so by the <hi>Beast,</hi> who hath giv'n the whole History of <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiochus</hi> recorded, I <hi>Maccab.</hi> 1. from <hi>v.</hi> 41. to <hi>v.</hi> 58. in a larger Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter since his height of Reign and Number 666; I desire the knowing Reader to compare them, especially in four Partic.</p>
               <p n="1">1. His Command on All to be of one Idolatrous Way.</p>
               <p n="2">2. All Desilement of true Religion brought in.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The Books of Divine Law destroy'd, and those kill'd with whom they were found.</p>
               <p n="4">4. The <hi>Israelites</hi> drove into secret Places, like the <hi>Woman into the Wilderness.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And what can be a more express Representation of the <hi>daily Sacrifice taken away,</hi> than the <hi>Court</hi> without the <hi>Temple,</hi> where the Altar of <hi>Holocausts</hi> stood, given to <hi>the Gentiles;</hi> where the true <hi>Israelites</hi> had occasional Recourse on account of <hi>Sacrifice?</hi> and this just at the 42 Months of the <hi>Beast</hi> beginning. For it was the <hi>Altar of Incense within the Temple,</hi> where then the true Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shippers were, retired from Publick to Private Worship.</p>
               <p>Or if because, that great Person carries that <hi>Vision</hi> of the <hi>Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple</hi> so far otherwise, we do not insist too hard upon it now, yet the very Pollution of the People's <hi>Outer Court,</hi> or the very <hi>Holy City trodden under Foot by the Gentiles,</hi> shews the constant publick Worship taken away, or in the <hi>Jewish</hi> Phrase the <hi>Daily Sacrifice,</hi> see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Place where they use to come for that Worship, was fill'd with <hi>Gentiles:</hi> but I shall have Occasion further to make Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course to this <hi>Vision,</hi> and to confirm my first Sense.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="objection">
               <head>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> 5.</head>
               <p>The <hi>Beasts</hi> Time begun before 400, and that spoyles the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lendars Account.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="answer">
               <head>Answ.</head>
               <p>God alone is Judge, when that begun; when, and how long the <hi>Synagogue</hi> of <hi>Sathan</hi> was overballauced by the true Church; (so long the Church was pure) and when that <hi>Synagogue</hi> out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weighed
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:54329:46"/>the true Church; and to shew that in the half Time, from the Resurrection of Christ,
<note place="margin">Apoc. 6.</note>
                  <hi>viz.</hi> at <hi>Alexander Severus</hi> his Death that especial Note of Attention by a <hi>Voyce in the midst of the Beast</hi> is given; both directing to the Time, and the just Judgment of God concerning the true Time of the <hi>Churches Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity,</hi> by <hi>weighing it,</hi> as it were in the Scales all along, and finding it (just at that time doubled) too <hi>light, viz.</hi> at 404 years end, or <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no vulg.</hi> 437. and what other Account, or meaning can be given of it, I desire any one to give: I have not found its Sense yet at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted by an Interpreter.</p>
               <div type="argument">
                  <p>For the Arguments establishing a sooner Time used by that excellent Person: I confess I am not satisfied in them: <hi>Vitalpan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus</hi> his Proportions betwixt the <hi>outer-Court</hi> and the <hi>Temple mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sured,</hi> shewing the Time of the Churches Purity.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Answ.</head>
                  <p>If <hi>Vitalpandus</hi> his measures, even to minutes, be Canonical, as they cannot be supposed, yet the <hi>Apocalyptick</hi> Text seems not at all to point by the <hi>measuring</hi> to Time; but to the Churches Purity or Agreement with <hi>Ezekiels</hi> measures, and though the beautiful Analogy of Place and Time, leading to it by the Expositors cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious management be very grateful to the Contemplation, yet I do not find, they can conclude the Judgment, yet with Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to so much a greater.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. I do not see the Proportion, as between seven and two, can be any wayes ascertain'd as to point of Place, since <hi>Vitalpandus</hi> his measures are adjusted to the <hi>Temple,</hi> but the <hi>Vision</hi> is supposed to refer to the <hi>Tabernacle,</hi> and the <hi>City</hi> to make the <hi>outer Court,</hi> by the reverend Expositor, therein consenting with Mr. <hi>Mede.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>But the Tabernacle</hi> and all its <hi>Courts</hi> can bear no Proportion with the City, if that be the <hi>outer Court,</hi> and to make the <hi>Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples outward Court,</hi> the <hi>outward Court</hi> meant in one regard, and the <hi>City</hi> the <hi>outward Court</hi> in another, looks like an Injury to the <hi>Prophetick</hi> Scheme.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. But with all due Regard to such incomparable Expositors, it seems most natural, that the Church, Symbolizing with the <hi>Eremitical Woman,</hi> was retired into the <hi>Temple,</hi> worshiping before the <hi>golden Altar of Incense,</hi> the <hi>daily Sacrifice being taken away</hi> from the <hi>four Horns</hi> of which, upon the prevalent Prayers of the whole Number, was heard that Judicial <hi>Voice, Loose the four Angels</hi> (<hi>viz:</hi> the <hi>Turks</hi> on the <hi>Beasts</hi> Kingdom) <hi>bound in Euphrates:</hi> though ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:54329:47"/>different from the <hi>Prayers of all Saints,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Apoc. 9. Apoc. 8.10.</note> and the <hi>silence</hi> of the People in the Time of Incense in the <hi>outer Court</hi> not yet defiled.</p>
                  <p>For that the <hi>outer Court</hi> was at first lest out of <hi>measure,</hi> at the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry time <hi>Christ was riding out to conouer,</hi> and bring <hi>all Nations</hi> into it, seems not to comport with the <hi>Divine Prophecy:</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore till the Apostasie, must needs be supposed to be <hi>measured;</hi> the Church of Christ consisting so much of Gentile Converts.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Although it be hence concluded, the first <hi>Vision</hi> of the <hi>open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Book</hi> does not begin so high as the 7 <hi>Churches</hi> or <hi>Seals,</hi> yet this is according to the true <hi>Apocalyptick Order,</hi> which first com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleats the History of the <hi>Trumpets</hi> begun to the very end of <hi>Apoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyptick</hi> Time, and then begins from the very first in the <hi>Woman cloathed with the Sun,</hi> as a new set of Visions.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="argument">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Argum.</hi> 2.</head>
                  <p>The second Proof of the 42 <hi>Months</hi> beginning before 400 is, that Invocation of Saints had entered somewhat before it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Answ.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ephesus</hi> had left its <hi>first Love,</hi> and there was a <hi>Synogogue of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than;</hi> there were many Corruptions, and Beginnings of Apostasie, but the True Church still overballanced in the sight of God, till the very Time, he decided the <hi>Church</hi> as visible <hi>too light,</hi> and the <hi>Beasts Kingdom</hi> risen.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="objection">
               <head>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> 6.</head>
               <p>The Seals point only upon great Events in the Empire, and do not describe a Line of Time, and so cannot contribute to a Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lendar of <hi>Prophetick Time.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="answers">
               <div n="1" type="answer">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Answ.</hi> 1.</head>
                  <p>The first, and most genuine <hi>Apocalyptick Sense of sealing,</hi> is stay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Events, till their just Season; <hi>Ʋnsealing</hi> is letting them out into Event; keeping secret is but a Secondary, and Inclusive Sense, as will appear to any serious Considerer of the Prophetick use of it, so that <hi>Sealing</hi> and <hi>Ʋnsealing,</hi> or <hi>Revealing,</hi> signifie su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream Government, which Christ at first not appearing to <hi>receive at Gods Hand, John wept</hi> so much, to signifie the <hi>Apostles Trouble,</hi> when they despair'd of our <hi>Lords Rising</hi> to Reign, till Risen. On which is given a most elegant Scheme, <hi>Apoc.</hi> 5. and an <hi>Elder</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forms <hi>John,</hi> as one of them <hi>slow of Heart to understand the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets;</hi> that is, <hi>Daniel</hi> thus inform'd him, as I have said in the Calendar, and it confirms the <hi>Elders</hi> being of the <hi>Jewish</hi> Church, a <hi>Kingdom</hi> of <hi>Priests</hi> all crown'd, that Church and Kingdom be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing united.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="answer">
                  <p n="2">
                     <pb n="85" facs="tcp:54329:47"/> 2. It is most evident by History, such a space of Time runs out from the first <hi>Seal</hi> to the ten Kings Rising, and the Emperours becoming but Ghosts of Imperial Power, being the Let of the <hi>Beasts</hi> Kingdom, so <hi>taken out of the way;</hi> that is, the space of 404 Years from the Resurrection.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="objection">
               <head>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> 7.</head>
               <p>The Witnesses are risen, and out of their Sack-cloth, and that some Years ago, and therefore the 1260 Years are also so long expir'd; which utterly subverts the Calendar.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="answer">
               <head>Answ.</head>
               <p>This being the great Objection, requires the most distinct An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer. I shall therefore briefly explain my full Sense; in somethings adding to, in some things correcting what is not so fitly express'd in the Calendar; by which, I hope the distance betwixt so ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerable an Exposition, and my humble Attempt will grow much less.</p>
               <p>I observe then, the Characters of the Time of the Churches Apostasie are in <hi>Daniel,</hi> and the <hi>Revelation</hi> given eight Times; and every Time with a diverse Application, either in regard of those to whom they are given: or, to their slate, on the Account of which they are so given.</p>
               <p n="1">1. To the <hi>Beast, Time, Times, half a Time,</hi> in <hi>Daniel</hi> twice;
<note place="margin">Dan. 7.</note> once, <hi>as wearing out the Saints of the most high,</hi> and <hi>changing Times and Laws,</hi> once, as <hi>scattering the Power of the Holy People:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Dan. 12.</note> the first of which I interweave with the <hi>Witnesses three dayes,</hi> and a <hi>half lying dead, &amp;c.</hi> the second with the <hi>Woman in the Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, her Time, Times, and half a Time, hid from the Face of the Serpent.</hi> Which together are four of the eight Times forementi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned.</p>
               <p n="2">2. To the <hi>Beash</hi> are given 42 <hi>Months,</hi>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, to be in Life,
<note place="margin">Apoc. 13.</note> Motion, and Action, though of different Degrees, first of grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, or ascending, then of declining or descending; and between both, of a firm consistent state. To the <hi>Gentiles</hi> are allowed 42 <hi>Months</hi> also, of possessing the <hi>outer Court,</hi> and to <hi>tread the Holy Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty under foot</hi> in that space.
<note place="margin">Apoc. 11.</note>
               </p>
               <p>The first of these I interlink with the <hi>Witnesses</hi> 1260 <hi>Dayes, Prophecying in Sackcloth.</hi> The second with the <hi>Womans</hi> 1260 <hi>Daies,</hi> in which she hath <hi>a Plaoe prepared of God</hi> where she <hi>shall be fed.</hi> And these are the four other Times of the mentioned eight, and make them up.</p>
               <pb n="86" facs="tcp:54329:48"/>
               <p> Now the Golden Key of all these Characters of Time is (as the Excellent Expositor styles it) the <hi>Three Days,</hi> and a <hi>Half;</hi> for they teach us to sort them to four and four. The thrice named <hi>Time, Times,</hi> and <hi>half a Time</hi> with themselves: the twice nam'd 42 Months, and as often nam'd 1260 Days with themselves.</p>
               <p>And though they are all in strict Sense coextended, neither more, nor less Time, yet in their Application to Events, they differ much: for the three <hi>Days and a half,</hi> by their Allusion to our <hi>Lord's three Days of Death</hi> and <hi>Burial,</hi> teach us, that they themselves, with the thrice nam'd <hi>Time, Times, Half a Time,</hi> have, as our <hi>Lord's three Days,</hi> a Time within a Time, or a Kernel of Time, fill'd and impregnated with the height of those Events, with which they are charg'd.</p>
               <p>Even as then those <hi>three Days of our Lord</hi> were of equal length with any other three <hi>Nycthemers,</hi> or Days, and Nights, yet the Evening only of the first of them, <hi>viz.</hi> the sixth Day; the second, <hi>viz.</hi> the seventh Day entire; the Evening and <hi>early Morning</hi> of the third, <hi>viz.</hi> the first <hi>Day</hi> of the <hi>Week</hi> till he rose, were reple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish'd with the Highest of that great Event, the <hi>Death,</hi> and <hi>Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial</hi> of our <hi>Lord Jesus Christ.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Just so the <hi>Time, Times, Half Time</hi> of the <hi>Beasts</hi> Kingdom, or <hi>wearing out the Saints of the most High, changing Times,</hi> and <hi>Laws,</hi> meets in the sullness of Event, with the Witnesses <hi>lying dead</hi> three <hi>Days</hi> and a <hi>Half,</hi> (though they yet speak as <hi>Abel,</hi> or Prophecy, but unburied, because the <hi>People, Kindreds,</hi> &amp;c. furnish'd a Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cession immediately) only in the end or Evening of the <hi>Beasts first Time,</hi> the intire space of his <hi>two Times,</hi> the <hi>Early Morning</hi> of his <hi>Half Time</hi> till they arose, and proportionably in the <hi>Evening</hi> of the <hi>Witnesses first day,</hi> the <hi>whole of their two Days,</hi> and the <hi>Day-break</hi> of the <hi>Half Day,</hi> these only being fill'd with the Event.</p>
               <p>Agreeably the same Parts of the <hi>Beasts</hi> Time joyn with the like Parts of the <hi>Woman in the Wilderness,</hi> her <hi>Time, Times, Half Time,</hi> in that top of the Event, the Beasts <hi>scattering the Power of the Holy People,</hi> as into a <hi>Wilderness,</hi> and the <hi>Womans</hi> being not only in the <hi>Wilderness,</hi> but being <hi>hid so close,</hi> as <hi>from the face of the Serpent,</hi> that he knew not where to find a True Church, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinct from the false one, to assault it; which abundantly answers that Cavil of <hi>Rome,</hi> Where was your <hi>Church</hi> before <hi>Luther?</hi> Even in <hi>the Wilderness, hid from the Face of the Serpent,</hi> driven thither by the cruel <hi>Antichristian Beast.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="87" facs="tcp:54329:48"/>
               <p> At her Entrance into the <hi>Wilderness,</hi> he had indeed such an Eye of it, that he threw out the Flood of the <hi>Barbarians</hi> upon the whole Name of Christianity, that he might be sure to reach it. When the <hi>Dragon</hi> had given his <hi>Seat</hi> to the <hi>Beast,</hi> he intended to ruine it by the <hi>Beast;</hi> but when it was thus <hi>hid,</hi> he knew not how to meddle with it as a Church, but in <hi>her Seed,</hi> that <hi>kept the Commands of God,</hi> and the <hi>Testimony of Christ.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But now, as these intimate Parts of this one, and the same Time in its several Characters, are satiated with their due Events, so they are in their other Parts perfectly coequal with the 42 Months, and the 1260 Days; and share with them in the lower Degrees of the same Events.</p>
               <p>For the whole <hi>Time, Times,</hi> and <hi>Half Time,</hi> the <hi>Beaft</hi> is <hi>in do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> in a lower Degree, tho he cannot <hi>wear out the Saints</hi> all the time, nor <hi>change Laws</hi> and <hi>Times</hi> throughout, and so they cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>respond with his 42 <hi>Months.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Analogously the <hi>whole three Days,</hi> and a <hi>half,</hi> united with the 1260 Days, the <hi>Witnesses Prophecy in Sack cloth,</hi> though they do not all that time lye Dead under universal Anathemaes, Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munications, all kinds of Spiritual, so call'd, and Civil Death. And correspondently the <hi>Gentiles treading the outer Court,</hi> and <hi>Holy City,</hi> 42 Months, the <hi>Woman</hi> is shut within the <hi>Temple,</hi> and fed there, as in a Solitude, or Wilderness of Holy private Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship, the <hi>whole Time, Times,</hi> and <hi>half a Time,</hi> as well as 1260 Days, tho she be not all that time hid <hi>from the face of the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent:</hi> He having many Glances and Glimpses of her, till the Evening of her <hi>first Time,</hi> and after the Morning of her <hi>Half Time,</hi> he bath again fuller Sights of her in the Reformed Churches, tho yet not out of the Wilderness: and thus the 1260 <hi>Days,</hi> and the <hi>Time, Times,</hi> and <hi>Half Time</hi> of the <hi>Woman,</hi> are conjoyn'd.</p>
               <p>By all which it appears, Time at large hath a less full Presence of the Event, and admits a Contrary; Intimate Time hath a full Presence of the Event, and admits no Contrary.</p>
               <p>The Time of the Beast's Power <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> only, before he grew up to his Apocalyptick Number 666, allowed the Witnesses to <hi>finish their Testimony</hi> as living <hi>Witnesses,</hi> but not their <hi>Prophecy;</hi> in temonstrating against the growing Corruptions, and denouncing Divine Judgments, call'd, <hi>Bringing down Fire from Heav'n, smi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the Earth with Plagues, turning Water into Blood.</hi> It allowed a Visibility of the Church, though as <hi>in a Wilderness,</hi> that she
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:54329:49"/>might be known where she was: but at that his Number <hi>Bestia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nism</hi> covers all. The <hi>Witnesses</hi> are <hi>all Dead</hi> in Law, and so judg'd by all, that though they are seen, none consider them but as dead Men: their Testimony, as Heresie and Blasphemy, lyes <hi>dead</hi> also.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Woman</hi> cannot be found, even by the <hi>Serpent</hi> himself, so quick-sighted by his Malice as well as Nature; but the <hi>Half Day</hi> and <hi>Half Time</hi> approaching, the <hi>Witnesses</hi> have in the Reforrn'd Churches a <hi>Spirit of Life</hi> in their <hi>Prophecy,</hi> and <hi>stand on their Feet.</hi> Some are call'd up into Place of Dignity, as into Heaven; but not as they shall be at the end of 1260 Days, for each first and last part of all the Characters of Time must have Degrees of the Event, else they could not have a Foundation to be so di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinguish'd. Even our <hi>Lord's</hi> first night was a beginning to dye in his Agony, being betray'd, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and till the Evening of the first Day of the Week, he appear'd not to a Number; as not publickly <hi>risen,</hi> till the end of the third day.</p>
               <p>The Witnesses are <hi>yet in Sackcloth</hi> then.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Those in most splendid Condition, if truly <hi>Witnesses,</hi> mourn for the Abominations and Impenitency of so great a Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of Christians; as the <hi>Beast,</hi> and <hi>Woman of Babylon</hi> yet have under them: over whom <hi>Christ Jesus our Lord,</hi> that <hi>Manly birth caught up to Heaven,</hi> bears the Imperial Name.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Many of the Witnesses surrounded with the <hi>Bestian Power</hi> in several Parts of his Territories, are truly in <hi>Sack-cloth,</hi> and ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry little remov'd from <hi>Death</hi> of all kinds; which shall not be, when the 1260 <hi>Days</hi> are expir'd.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The <hi>Synagogue of Satan</hi> keeps <hi>Philadelphia</hi> low, would fain <hi>shut its Door, open'd</hi> to it by Christ, as if it were no Church. So that it <hi>keeps the Word of Christ's Patience,</hi> which shall not continue beyond the fore-nam'd 1260 Days; then its <hi>Door</hi> shall be <hi>wide</hi> and <hi>effectual,</hi> daily more and more to <hi>the New Jerusalem,</hi> and the <hi>Synagogue of Satan</hi> cringe, and <hi>worship at its Feet,</hi> and know and acknowledge <hi>Christ's Love to it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Church</hi> in the <hi>Reform'd Churches</hi> is so conspicuous, as it were on <hi>Mount Sion with the Lamb,</hi> and his <hi>Father's Name seen in their Fore-head,</hi> and <hi>written</hi> at length, not <hi>sealed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yet being in a State of Separation from so great a Part of the Christian World, in Profession of that Religion, however Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>statiz'd, it may well be call'd a Wilderness Condition; which shall not continue such, the 1260 Days being past.</p>
               <pb n="89" facs="tcp:54329:49"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thyatyra,</hi> or the <hi>Protestant Churches</hi> within the Pawes of the <hi>Beast,</hi> are much more in the <hi>Wilderness;</hi> and let the <hi>Grecian Churches,</hi> and those that communicate most with their Doctrine and Worship, be also remembred to be at the same time made more splendid.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Church of Sardis,</hi> tho not in the Apostasie of <hi>Babylon,</hi> yet hath <hi>defiled Garments;</hi> and within the <hi>Reformed Churches,</hi> tho not imputable to them, being not of their Constitution, although of their Permission or Connivance, there is found a <hi>Synagogue of Satan.</hi> Both which Evils will daily lessen, till they vanish at the end of the 1260 days, as pertaining to the Wilderness State.</p>
               <p>To conclude then, Till after the full Expiration of the time of the Apostasie, being in Power, as a <hi>Throne,</hi> or <hi>Kingdom,</hi> in all its coextensive Characters, the <hi>Witnesses</hi> are not in full <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>calyptick</hi> Sense risen, as that Golden Key of the Time, the <hi>three Days</hi> and <hi>Half</hi> also, assures us: for till the Emphatical <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, or after <hi>three Days</hi> and a <hi>Half,</hi> fully past, they <hi>rise</hi> not.</p>
               <p>And that that is not yet (besides the Credit of our Calendar) is apparent, in that since the Reformation there have been no Effects, like those that are to signalize the end of the 1260 <hi>Days,</hi> agreed by all not to have determined with the Beginnings of it. What can we find since the Year 1650 to ascribe such Effects to, in the <hi>Protestant Churches,</hi> more than before? or what <hi>Sounds</hi> of the <hi>Seventh Trumpet</hi> and its great <hi>Voices,</hi> since the Reformation setled (or of the <hi>Vials</hi> since the Year 1650.) have yet reached our Ears? Which shall immediately fill the Air under the whole Heaven, after those days expir'd to remark to us their Expira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; or how is the <hi>Mahometan</hi> Woe past?</p>
               <p>What <hi>Tenth</hi> of the <hi>City</hi> hath fall'n since the Reformation past? that is, Which of the <hi>Beasts Ten Horns,</hi> or <hi>Ten Kingdoms,</hi> for so I expound his <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, or Tenth, have fall'n off from him since 1600? But they shall wholly fall off, when the <hi>Witnesses</hi> are ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly risen: for the seventh <hi>Trumpet</hi> is an intimate part of Time, so full of its own Event, as to admit no <hi>Reigning Bestianism,</hi> even as <hi>Reigning Bestianism</hi> in its intimate Time, suffer'd no <hi>Witnesses to live.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This rightly apprehended, removes the Mistake on one side, that the <hi>Beast</hi> was not <hi>risen,</hi> when he was indeed <hi>risen,</hi> because he was not at first at the Elevation of 666. And on the other fide, it assures us, the Apocalyptick Prophecy is not fulfill'd yet so far as the compleat <hi>Rising of the Witnesses, for the mighty Works</hi>
                  <pb n="90" facs="tcp:54329:50"/>of it <hi>have not yet shewn forth themselves;</hi> and then not the seventh <hi>Trumpet sounded,</hi> nor any of the <hi>Vials poured out.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Objections against this Assertion of the <hi>Witnesses</hi> being not <hi>risen,</hi> thus explain'd easily fall off; tho urg'd by so strong a Hand.</p>
               <div n="1" type="objection">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Object.</hi> 1.</head>
                  <p>The Latitude of <hi>Months</hi> for the fulfilling Events, in some Parts of them may so disagree with the narrower Lines of <hi>Day,</hi> too narrow for the Months, that the Prophecy may be made to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradict it self, and to speak true and not true, as to point of Time and Events, together. True in the Months, not in the Days.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Answ.</head>
                  <p>As the height of Events is by the Prophecy determined to the intimate part of the <hi>three Days,</hi> and <hi>three Times,</hi> and a <hi>half,</hi> so the Duration of the Event at large is by the Prophecy coextend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the very <hi>last Day</hi> of the 1260, and cannot end sooner: and therefore the <hi>Days</hi> must over-rule the <hi>Months,</hi> as being more pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cisely fix'd in Point of Time; even as the highest Events must have been coextended, had not the Prophecy, with design, cut out the Time into larger Cantons, that Parts of them being full of the highest of those Events affix'd to them, might answer for the rest, and particularly into three Days and a half; that by the Allusion of our <hi>Lord's</hi> three Days, we might know how to interpret, as hath been declar'd.</p>
                  <p>And though the Prophecy be more distinct in the <hi>Apocal.</hi> than in <hi>Daniel,</hi> yet will it not argue any Improvements of Omnisci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ency, any more than the Clearness of the New Testament excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the Old, infers any such thing: not to add, that according to our Calendar, the 1260 <hi>Days,</hi> though ioyn'd with 30 more, are made Correspondents in <hi>Daniel</hi> with the <hi>Time, Times, &amp;c.</hi> and so as exact to a <hi>Day</hi> as the <hi>Apocal.</hi> is.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="objection">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Object.</hi> 2.</head>
                  <p>The Greatness of the Events requires a larger Scope, than of a Prophetick Day or Year, to be fulfill'd in.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Answ.</head>
                  <p>The Preparations to the Events may be so going on before, that the Events themselves may, as <hi>the Israelites going</hi> out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> be the <hi>self same Day;</hi> and so the <hi>Beasts</hi> last <hi>Month</hi> may by its greater Compass, allow Room for those Preparations about its latter end, though not fulfilled till the last Day. But when God will <hi>work, who can let it? Nullum tempus occurrit Regi.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="objection">
                  <pb n="91" facs="tcp:54329:50"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Object.</hi> 3.</head>
                  <p>The Expectation of the <hi>Witnesses</hi> yet to rise, disquiets Mens Thoughts into Turbulency, and gives them meaner Esteems of the Reformation, and the present State of the Church.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Answ.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. The <hi>Prophecy anathematizes</hi> all such disorderly Motions, whether the <hi>Witnesses</hi> are risen or not: for it will be fulfill'd by the Princes themselves, Christian Princes, and by Instruments <hi>in pure Linnen,</hi> not as in the Trumpets by <hi>Mahometan,</hi> much less by popular Tumults.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. The very Hopes or Desires that <hi>Babylon</hi> should <hi>fall,</hi> as eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one knows, as yet, it is not fall'n, may be charg'd with the same ill Consequences.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. The Reformation is acknowledg'd within it self to be, the <hi>Witnesses Risen,</hi> and the <hi>Church out of the VVilderness;</hi> but not to the full Sense of the <hi>Prophecy,</hi> the <hi>Beast</hi> yet being in Power, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</p>
                  <p>It is also certain, the Witnesses can no more lye dead, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, in the <hi>Street of the City.</hi> The Rain-bow on the Head of Christ assures, that Deluge shall return no more. <hi>Sardis</hi> and <hi>Philadelphia,</hi> those <hi>Protestant Churches,</hi> shall continue till <hi>Babylon's Fall,</hi> and the <hi>New Jerusalem,</hi> to assure against such a Death.</p>
                  <p>Any bloody Eruption or Massacre is no otherwise to be fear'd from that Region of Blood, than from any Tyrannick Power. A Calamity, all sinful Times and Places may be obnoxious to by Divine Judgment, from any Hand of Potency unlawfully used, and let out by Divine Displeasure upon our Provocations, and so from a <hi>Popish,</hi> but not as the <hi>Apocalypt, Beast</hi> foretold of.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. If the <hi>Prophecy</hi> it self hath not charg'd the <hi>Reformed Churches,</hi> some of them I mean, <hi>with desiled Garments,</hi> or want of pressing on to the utmost Principles of the <hi>Reformation,</hi> and among them, though not of them, impeach'd <hi>a Synagogue of Satan,</hi> as an Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my to <hi>Philadelphia;</hi> the Witnesses being not risen will only give hopes of Accessions of Glory to all <hi>Reformed Churches</hi> by their <hi>Rising;</hi> and that the <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> at their <hi>Rising,</hi> the same with <hi>the Rest</hi> in <hi>Thyatyra, giving Glory to God,</hi> will encrease the Peace and Safety, as well as Splendor of the <hi>Reformation:</hi> which can be no unwelcome News to every sincere <hi>Protestant.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Nor can the Progress of Things by <hi>Voices,</hi> or great Ministra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the Gospel, and <hi>Vials</hi> or Executions of <hi>Judgment</hi> to <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon's Fall,</hi> disturb the hearty Lovers of the Reformation, who
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:54329:51"/>hate Antichrist and <hi>Rome,</hi> so Impenitent, as <hi>the Vials</hi> History represents it.</p>
                  <p>There is no Reason the <hi>New Jerusalem</hi> should affright them that cordially pray for the <hi>Conversion of the Jews,</hi> and the bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in of the <hi>Fullness of the Gentiles.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>For what doth that intend, but that the Kingdom of Christ on Earth shall have the greatest Inlargement, when the <hi>ten Tribes,</hi> whose Iniquity <hi>Ezekiel</hi> bore prophetically till his <hi>Vistonal Jerusa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,</hi> shall with the two Tribes receive upon their <hi>Jerusalem,</hi> the <hi>Metropolis</hi> of the Church on Earth, the perpendicular Rayes of that <hi>Jerusalem,</hi> that comes down from <hi>Heaven;</hi> and therefore the <hi>Kings and Nations shall bring their Honour and Glory to it.</hi> And this shall be <hi>Life from the Dead,</hi> the Servants of God, <hi>Prophets, Apostles,</hi> and <hi>Martyrs,</hi> shall appear with <hi>Christ,</hi> as <hi>Moses,</hi> and <hi>Elias in Glory,</hi> or Glorious Bodies, as on the <hi>Mount of Transfigu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration</hi> to the three Apostles.</p>
                  <p>And as in a Pre-day of Judgment, Christ will gather to that <hi>Great Day of the Battel of God Almighty,</hi> or his Triumphal Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation, all those who have all along been prepar'd to it by the <hi>three Froggs</hi> or <hi>Spirits of Devils working lying Wonders, coming out of the Mouth of the Dragon,</hi> the <hi>Beast,</hi> and the <hi>False Prophet;</hi> that is, those who have by them been seduc'd to be the great Zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lots of <hi>Paganism, Mahometanism,</hi> and <hi>Antichristianism,</hi> Tyrants over the Witnesses of Divine Truth, and execute visible Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment upon them, and on the <hi>Beast, and false Prophet cast into the Lake alive,</hi> and <hi>Babylon,</hi> becoming a <hi>Habitation of Devils</hi> above all others.</p>
                  <p>Christ will then also remonstrate, but not with such Severity against <hi>Ephesus declining, Sardis</hi> her <hi>Defiled Garments, when he comes as a Thief,</hi> together with all that have not <hi>overcome</hi> in eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry the best Church; but honour <hi>Smyrna</hi> and <hi>Philadelphia,</hi> and the <hi>Overcomers</hi> of all <hi>Churches,</hi> with the great Honours of the <hi>New Jerusalem,</hi> in such Methods of Glory, Grace, and Equity, as we cannot before-hand define in Particulars, but may under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand in the Sum: <hi>For who is sufficient to declare these Wonders?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And why should this more disturb the World than the <hi>Day of Judgment, rewarding</hi> all <hi>according to their Works, Churches</hi> and <hi>Persons;</hi> which we profess we know not how soon it may come upon us?</p>
                  <p>Or than the continual Mentions of present Judgments in this World, which we acknowledge are justly hanging over our
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:54329:51"/>Heads: Or than the Declaration of Mercies, and Promises of all Blessings even in this Life to the Sincere, and pure Profession of the Doctrine, and Worship of the Gospel joyn'd with Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence?</p>
                  <p>There can be no Difference, but that we are used to the one, and suffer them to have their Circle with all the Affairs of the present Life; the other we are not so us'd to, and fear they should disturb this present Life. But we cannot blot out those two great <hi>Testifications</hi> of the <hi>Divine Prophecy, Whoever wiis, let him take of the water of Life freely, proceeding out of the Throne of God and the Lamb. And if any Man take away from the Words of this Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, God will take from his Part in the Book of Life,</hi> and <hi>out of the Holy City</hi> (in which every one may have a part) and <hi>from the Things Written in this</hi> Book.</p>
                  <p>Let none then, by shutting up Discourses of this <hi>Jerusalem,</hi> be hindred from thirsting for the Waters of its <hi>Chrystal River of Life,</hi> and so drinking of the Streams, that they may come at last, as they above do, to drink of the <hi>Fountain.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>Page 83. l. 12. and l. 16. for <hi>Vitalpandus</hi> read <hi>Vilalpandus.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>